<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /Users/grace/grobid-0.6.1/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Nutrition of the giant clam Tridacna gigas (L.). II. Relative contributions of filter-feeding and the ammonium-nitrogen acquired and recycled by symbiotic alga towards total nitrogen requirements for tissue growth and metabolism</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J S</forename><surname>Hawkinsa'</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">&quot;Plymouth Marine Laboratory</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">bAustralian Institute for Marine Science</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>West Hoe</addrLine>
									<postCode>PLl 3DH</postCode>
									<settlement>Plymouth, Plymouth, Townsville</settlement>
									<region>Queensland</region>
									<country>UK, Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Klumppb</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">&quot;Plymouth Marine Laboratory</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">bAustralian Institute for Marine Science</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>West Hoe</addrLine>
									<postCode>PLl 3DH</postCode>
									<settlement>Plymouth, Plymouth, Townsville</settlement>
									<region>Queensland</region>
									<country>UK, Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Nutrition of the giant clam Tridacna gigas (L.). II. Relative contributions of filter-feeding and the ammonium-nitrogen acquired and recycled by symbiotic alga towards total nitrogen requirements for tissue growth and metabolism</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<note type="submission">Received 10 October 1994; revision received 10 February 1995; accepted 3 March 1995</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.1" ident="GROBID" when="2021-09-14T02:15+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Amino-nitrogen requirements</term>
					<term>Ammonium assimilation</term>
					<term>Filter-feeding</term>
					<term>Giant clam</term>
					<term>Nitrogen budget</term>
					<term>Nitrogen recycling</term>
					<term>Nutrition</term>
					<term>Symbiosis</term>
					<term>Tridacna @gas</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>We compare the relative contributions of filter-feeding and ammonium-nitrogen translocated from algal symbionts (zooxanthellae) towards the total nitrogen requirements for tissue growth and metabolism in the giant clam Tridacna gigus. Isotope enrichments suggest that zooxanthellae</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>effected most if not all primary assimilation from high concentrations (~15 PM) of "N-ammonium. There was a net daily uptake of ammonium from natural seawater, which was modulated according to nutritional history, light history, ammonium concentration, and possible biological rhythmicity. Zooxanthellae also assimilated nitrogen excreted by host tissues, including 15N absorbed from ingested alga. Nearly 100% of the 15N subsequently released from zooxanthellae was incorporated in host tissues, with no significant loss from the clam over at least 10 days. Zooxanthellae therefore conserve and recycle essentially all nitrogenous end-products within T. gigas, affording giant clams a nutritional advantage over non-symbiotic bivalves. In further contrast with heterotrophic bivalves from particle-rich environments, T. gigas show longer gut passage times and high net and gross efficiencies (78.1 -+ 9.4% and 99.2 i-0.4%, respectively) with which organic nitrogen is absorbed from ingested particles. Filter-feeding and/or other non-autotrophic processes were essential as a source of nitrogen to maintain observed rates of juvenile growth, but declined in significance with increasing clam size. Even under cloudy conditions of limited irradiance, the total contribution of nitrogen acquired as ammonium by zooxanthellae exceeded the contribution from ingested particles in T. gigas larger than about 0.1 g, increasing to at least 45% of total nitrogen requirements in clams of 10 g. Ammonium-nitrogen translocated from zooxanthellae also satisfied all basal</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p>The giant clam Tridacna gigas is a prime candidate for mariculture; for despite living within the oligotrophic environment of coral reefs throughout much of the Indo-Pacific, it is the largest and fastest-growing of all bivalve molluscs <ref type="bibr">(Yonge, 1980;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Crawford et al., 1987;</ref><ref type="bibr">Heslinga &amp; Fitt, 1987;</ref><ref type="bibr">Lucas, 1994)</ref>.</p><p>Although T. gigus is already being raised in hatcheries <ref type="bibr">(Lucas, 1994)</ref>, the means by which this species achieves such spectacular growth, and the relative importance of different sources of nutrients, has remained controversial <ref type="bibr">(Fankboner &amp; Reid, 1990;</ref><ref type="bibr">Fitt, 1993;</ref><ref type="bibr">Lucas, 1994)</ref>. What is certain is that endosymbiotic algae known as zooxanthellae within the hypertrophied siphon (commonly refered to as mantle tissue) transfer excess carbon from photosynthesis to host tissues, possibly in quantities that are sufficient to satisfy respiratory requirements in T. maxima <ref type="bibr">(Trench et al., 1981)</ref>, T. gigus <ref type="bibr">(Fisher et al., 1985;</ref><ref type="bibr">Klumpp et al., 1992)</ref>, T. tevoroa and T. derusa <ref type="bibr">(Klumpp and Lucas, 1994)</ref>. <ref type="bibr">Southgate (1988)</ref> has also demonstrated assimilation of 14C-labelled carbohydrate and lipid from microcapsules ingested by T. gigus larvae. And recently, we have also helped to dispel earlier doubts over the importance of filter-feeding (e.g. <ref type="bibr">Ricard &amp; Salvat, 1977)</ref>, showing that particulate organic matter satisfied at least 65% of the total carbon needed for both the respiration and growth in small T. gigas <ref type="bibr">(Klumpp et al., 1992)</ref>. Given the additional potential for direct uptake of dissolved organic matter (DOM) <ref type="bibr">(Fankboner, 1971;</ref><ref type="bibr">Goreau et al., 1973)</ref>, it is clear that T. gigus is trophically opportunistic,</p><p>utilizing both autotrophic and heterotrohpic mechanisms to help satisfy nutritional requirements <ref type="bibr">(Yonge, 1980;</ref><ref type="bibr">Heslinga &amp; Fitt, 1987;</ref><ref type="bibr">Klumpp et al., 1992)</ref>.</p><p>Nitrogen often limits growth in the marine environment. Yet there are no previous data quantifying the significance of zooxanthellae, filter-feeding, or DOM to the requirements for protein-nitrogen in T. gigus or any other comparable symbiotic organism.</p><p>Rather, research has focused on a further source of nutrition, establishing that giant clams may effect net uptake of dissolved inorganic nitrogen <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Burris, 1983;</ref><ref type="bibr">Wilkerson &amp; Trench, 1986;</ref><ref type="bibr">Fitt et al., 1993)</ref>, and that tissue growth is stimulated in response to the addition of nitrogen as ammonium or nitrate to surrounding seawater <ref type="bibr">(Heslinga et al., 1990;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Braley, 1992;</ref><ref type="bibr">Belda et al.. 1993)</ref>. It is generally accepted that net uptake of ammonium from the environment by intact zooxanthellae-host symbioses occurs by passive diffusion down concentration gradients that are created by localized substrate depletion (e.g. <ref type="bibr">D'Elia et al., 1983)</ref>. Certainly, the haemolymph of T. gigus appears to be the immediate source of metabolites for zooxanthellae <ref type="bibr">(Rees et al., 1993)</ref> which are able to assimilate ammonium for the synthesis of amino acids <ref type="bibr">(Muscatine, 1980;</ref><ref type="bibr">Wilkerson &amp; Muscatine, 1984;</ref><ref type="bibr">Summons et al., 1986;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Anderson &amp; Burris, 1987;</ref><ref type="bibr">Wilkerson &amp; Trench, 1986)</ref>, and which occupy a unique tubular system that ramifies from a diverticulum of the stomach <ref type="bibr">(Norton et al., 1992)</ref>. Further, the uptake of dissolved inorganic nitrogen by T. gigus is photodependent, and does not occur in isolated host tissues <ref type="bibr">(Wilkerson &amp; Trench, 1986;</ref><ref type="bibr">Fitt et al., 1993)</ref>. Therefore, the uptake of inorganic nitrogen by symbiotic associations appears at least partially dependent upon primary assimilation by zooxanthellae. It has been suggested that assimilation by zooxanthellae of ammonium-nitrogen excreted by the host, and the subsequent recycling of that nitrogen when released as amino acids utilized by host tissues, is central both to the rapid growth of tridacnid clams <ref type="bibr">(Wilkerson &amp; Trench, 1986;</ref><ref type="bibr">Lucas, 1994)</ref> and to the general success of algal-invertebrate symbioses in nutrient-poor waters (e.g. <ref type="bibr">Muscatine &amp; Porter, 1977;</ref><ref type="bibr">Spencer Davies, 1992)</ref>. However, there is little information on the fate of nitrogen assimilated by zooxanthellae <ref type="bibr">(Griffiths &amp; Streamer, 1988;</ref><ref type="bibr">Spencer Davies, 1992)</ref>. In addition, there is current debate on whether host waste nitrogenous products are freely available to algal symbionts <ref type="bibr">(Douglas, 1988)</ref> and whether zooxanthellae are solely responsible for the assimilation of inorganic nutrients by the association. Having compared activities of both glutamine synthetase and glutamate dehydrogenase with ammonium flux with and without metabolic inhibitors in the Hydra-Chlorellu symbiosis, <ref type="bibr">Rees (1987)</ref> suggested that ammonium assimilation occurs primarily in the host tissues. It has also been proposed that this assimilation allows the host to regulate its population of symbionts by restricting their source of nitrogen, supplied as amino acids <ref type="bibr">(McAuley, 1987;</ref><ref type="bibr">Rees, 1987)</ref>, and that host-mediated assimilation occurs in symbioses involving zooxanthellae <ref type="bibr">(Miller &amp; Yellowlees, 1989)</ref>. These suggestions obviously question the extent to which ammonium-nitrogen excreted by the host is freely available for assimilation and recycling by zooxanthellae <ref type="bibr">(Douglas, 1988;</ref><ref type="bibr">Rees, 1991)</ref>.</p><p>In a related publication, we have described natural growth rates, dark respiration, die1 oxygen flux and the absorption of organic matter from suspended particles filtered by T. gigas <ref type="bibr">(Klumpp et al., 1992)</ref>. These results were used to quantify the relative roles of endosymbiotic photosynthates and filter-feeding in providing the carbon needed for growth and respiration.</p><p>Here, we report associated measures of die1 ammonium flux, host tissue excretion and the absorption of organic nitrogen from ingested food particles, together with studies that monitored the uptake and subsequent utilisation of nitrogen isotope 15N that was available to T. gigus both as dissolved "N-ammonium and "N-1abelled alga. Findings are used to assess the extent to which zooxanthellae may be responsible for primary assimilation of inorganic nitrogen, to establish whether ammoniumnitrogen excreted by the host is freely available for assimilation and recycling by the zooxanthellae, and to quantify size-dependent contributions both of filterfeeding and algal symbiosis towards the total amino-nitrogen requirements for clam tissue growth and metabolism.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Materials and methods</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.">Origin and maintenance of clams</head><p>The work described below was undertaken during June, 1988 using T. gigas from the mariculture unit at Orpheus Island Research Station (OIRS), North Queensland, Australia. Initially, these clams were reared to juvenile size within raceways as described by <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Crawford et al. (1986)</ref>. Clams were then transferred to the reef flat at 2 cm shell length, where they grew to experimental size (4-6 cm shell length) over the next 5 months.</p><p>Experiments using the stable isotope of nitrogen "N to study the uptake kinetics and subsequent utilisation of nitrogen were undertaken at OIRS. Experiments studying diurnal cycles or the effects of light-history on net fluxes of oxygen and/or ammonium were undertaken using clams transferred in May, 1988 from OIRS to the Australian Institute of Marine Science (AIMS). Before experimentation, clams were acclimated in open-air flow-through raceways of unfiltered natural seawater for 3 days at OIRS, and up to 21 days at AIMS. Seawater was of similar temperature (22.5 2 3.O"C) at OIRS and at AIMS. Determinations of net absorption efficiency were undertaken on board the RV Harry Messel in the lagoon of Davies Reef (18.8"S, 147.2"E), using natural faecal pellets from clams that had previously been transplanted from OIRS to that lagoon in November, 1987.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.">Measuring daily net fluxes of oxygen and ammonium-nitrogen</head><p>A data-logging respirometer that monitors irradiance, temperature and oxygen tension in four replicate chambers at 1-min intervals (technical details and data analysis are described in <ref type="bibr">Klumpp et al., 1987)</ref> was used to compare daily net fluxes of oxygen and ammonium-nitrogen under a natural light regime at AIMS. The respirometer was positioned immediately below the surface of seawater in the same open-air flow-through raceway to which clams had been acclimated. One clam of 11.5 to 12.1 (mean + 2 SE = 11.7 f 0.3) cm shell length was placed in each of the four respirometer chambers. Each chamber contained 2.5 1 of seawater, which was completely and automatically replaced by flushing at 90-min intervals throughout the 24 h of measurements. Net oxygen flux ( pmole . clam ' . h-') was determined by least-squares regression of PO, against the time between seawater flushings, and separate means computed for each of the 16 incubations undertaken per clam. To measure the average net ammonium flux ( pmole . clam ' . h-') for each clam during the same incubations, duplicate 15 ml seawater samples were collected by syringe through a 0.2 pm filter from rubber sampling ports. These samples were collected up to 3 min after flushing, and less than 5 min before the next water replacement. Control samples were collected in the same way from a beaker containing 2.5 seawater standing in the same raceway, replacing that seawater by hand at the times of respirometer flushing. All samples were frozen in capped polyethylene vials at -20°C which is known to stabilise ammonium concentrations (e.g. <ref type="bibr">Degobbis, 1972)</ref>. Automated analyses of ammonium content were undertaken within 2 wk of sample collection as described by <ref type="bibr">Ryle et al. (1981)</ref>. The sensitivity of these analyses was k-O.02 PM. Initial concentrations of ammonium in the incubation seawater -0.5 PM.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.">Establishing the effects of darkness and clam size on net fluxes of ammonium-nitrogen</head><p>To establish effects of darkness on net ammonium flux (,uniole * clam-' * h-l), and to determine the relationship between clam size and excretion of ammoniumnitrogen by the host tissues, the same four individual clams that had been used to compare daily net fluxes of oxygen and ammonium-nitrogen (refer above), as well as two other size-classes (with shell lengths of 1.1 2 0.1 and 19.4 2 1.2 cm, respectively) that had been acclimated under identical conditions, were transferred to another flow-through raceway situated within a constant-temperature room (24.5 + 0.5"C). This indoor raceway was supplied with seawater which had been filtered (0.5 pm) to remove all food particles. After one day, net ammonium fluxes were measured under an irradiance of 600 ,uE. rn-*. s-' from a 500-W quartz halide lamp. Clams were then maintained in total darkness, and net ammonium fluxes monitored after 2, 6, 10 and 13 days.</p><p>Net ammonium fluxes were measured by incubating four clams from each of the large and intermediate size-classes separately within beakers containing 8 and 2 1 of membrane-filtered (0.25 pm) seawater, respectively. For the smallest size class, two clams were incubated together in beakers containing 50 ml of seawater, for each of six replicate groups. Each incubation was standardized over 4 h in the same constant temperature room (24.5 2 0.5"C). Red light of low intensity was used to see during those incubations. Duplicate 15 ml seawater samples were collected at the beginning and end of each incubation by syringe through a 0.2 pm filter. Samples were then stored at -20°C before measuring ammonium contents using phenol-hyperchlorite according to <ref type="bibr">Grasshoff &amp; Johannsen (1972)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4.">Determining ammonium uptake both by particle-fed or particle-starved clams, the proportional translocation of nitrogen from zooxanthellae to host tissues, and faecal losses of nitrogen assimilated as dissolved ammonium</head><p>To establish whether starving clams of suspended particles influenced rate of ammonium uptake, six clams were taken from the open air raceway that contained natural unfiltered seawater at OIRS. They were subsequently isolated for 48 h within separate beakers containing 2 1 of membrane-filtered <ref type="bibr">(0.2 ,um)</ref> seawater, changing that seawater at 12-h intervals, whilst the beakers were positioned in that same raceway. Ammonium uptake by these particle-starved clams was then compared with that of a further six clams from natural unfiltered seawater.</p><p>All clams were 4.5 to 5.5 cm shell length, with a dry tissue weight of 238 2 26 mg. Each clam was incubated separately in glass beakers containing 400 ml of membrane-filtered (0.2 ,um) seawater spiked with NH,Cl to an initial concentration of 15 PM, whilst situated within the raceway of prior acclimation. Duplicate 5 ml seawater samples were collected after 0, 30, 60, 90, 120, 150, 180 and 210 min from incubations of particle-fed clams, but only after 0 and 210 min from particle-starved clams, and each sample analysed immediately for ammonium content using phenol-hyperchlorite according to <ref type="bibr">Grasshoff &amp; Johannsen (1972)</ref>.</p><p>To monitor the subsequent fate of ammonium-nitrogen assimilated by particlefed clams, the NH,Cl used to spike these incubations of particle-fed clams was isotopically-labelled such that more than 99% of all ammonium-nitrogen was "N (Europa Scientific Limited, Crewe, UK). A total of 39 clams from natural unfiltered seawater were incubated as described above. Following 210 min of incubation within ammonium-"N chloride, these particle-fed clams were returned to the open air raceway, and four clams sampled after 0.25, 2, 4, 6, 24, 48, 94 and 245 h. All zooxanthellae were immediately collected from the mantle of each clam by homogenisation and centrifugation. Each mantle was homogenised in 5 ml filtered seawater using an Ultra Turrax homogeniser at full speed for 1 min. The homogenate was then centrifuged at 1000 rpm for 5 min, before retaining the pelleted zooxanthellae.</p><p>In addition, the foot, adductor muscle and gills, which contain less than 10% of all zooxanthellae within the clam, were collectively homogenised and centrifuged as described above. Regular microscopic examination not only confirmed the purity of our pelleted zooxanthellae, but also that the supernatant, including the "cap" of homogenised tissues sitting on the surface of that supernatant, was only comprised of animal cells and bacteria. Therefore, the supernatant and "cap" from collective homogenisations of foot, adductor muscle and gills were retained as host tissue. Each sample was placed within a screw-top glass vial, and dried to constant weight at 60°C before capping and storage.</p><p>To confirm the assimilation of inorganic nitrogen by zooxanthellae, and to determine the proportional translocation of nitrogen assimilated by zooxanthellae to host tissues, the percentage abundance of stable isotope "N was later measured within these samples of zooxanthellae or host tissues using continuousflow isotope-ratio mass spectrometry (Europa Scientific ANCA-MS).</p><p>To allow calculations of the total abundance of '"N, we dissociated the zooxanthellae from all tissues of five individual clams of similar size (4.5 to 5.5 cm shell length, with a mean ? 2 SE dry tissue weight of 231 2 8 mg). This was done by homogenising mantle and non-mantle tisssues separately, resuspending and centrifuging the pellet of zooxanthellae three times for each sample, using a whirlimixer to resuspend the pellet in filtered seawater, and discarding all supernatants. Microscopic observation then established no remaining "contamination" by host tissue, before pooling the pelleted zooxanthellae from each clam onto separate 4.7 cm GFC filters. We also excised the total soft tissues from a further four clams, and dried all samples to constant weight at low temperature (60°C) before storage in a desiccator. The total soft tissues were ground to a powder with mortar and pestle, and the protein contents both of zooxanthellae and total soft tissues determined according to <ref type="bibr">Lowry et al. (1951)</ref>. Nitrogen equivalents were computed by dividing total protein by 5.8 <ref type="bibr">(Gnaiger &amp; Bitterlich, 1984)</ref> before calculating the average total nitrogen within zooxanthellae and host tissues (by difference) for these six clams. These average total nitrogen values were multiplied by individual measures of the fractional enrichment of r5N above natural background levels to give the enrichment (pg. clam-') of "N within either the zooxanthellae or host tissues. It is worth emphasising two points here: (1) we were conservative in keeping only the purist fractions of host tissue or zooxanthellae for 15N analyses; and (2) the absolute enrichments of 15N within all zooxanthellae or all host tissues from each clam were calculated by multiplying the measured fraction of "N in each sample by accurate measures of the total nitrogen in either the zooxanthellae or host tissues from other clams of similar size. By these means, each sample retained for 15N analysis did not depend on the complete separation of all zooxanthellae from all host tissues within each clam. Following the incubation of clams in ammonium-'5N chloride, to quantify the subsequent egestion of "N in faeces, the six clams that had previously been particle-starved as described above were immediately transferred to shallow open-topped beakers submerged within the raceway of acclimation. All faeces produced by each clam were collected for filtration onto 2.5 cm GFC filters following intervals of 6, 24 and 48 h. The filters were dried to constant weight at 60°C and stored in a desiccator before analysing each sample both for total nitrogen content and the abundance of stable isotope "N.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.5.">Measuring absorption by the host of nitrogen from ingested particles, including gut passage time and the direct uptake by zooxanthellae of nitrogen from host tissues</head><p>Absorption efficiencies for ingested particles were measured in clams feeding upon natural seston in the lagoon of Davies Reef using the ash to ash-free ratio method of <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Conover (1966)</ref>. Faeces were collected, and correction made for pellets that contained healthy undigested zooxanthellae, as described by <ref type="bibr">Klumpp et al. (1992)</ref>. Nitrogen contents of food and faeces were determined using an elemental combustion analyser (Carlo Erba 1108) with acetanilide standards. The above measures are of net absorption efficiencies, taking into account metabolic faecal losses that are secreted into but not reabsorbed from the gut <ref type="bibr">(Hawkins &amp; Bayne, 1992)</ref>. To measure the gross efficiency of absorption, which takes no account of metabolic faecal losses, as well as to measure approximate gut passage time, and to confirm the uptake by zooxanthellae of nitrogen absorbed across the hosts gut epithelium, a culture of the unicellular alga Zsochrysis galbana was homogenously labelled with '"N as described by <ref type="bibr">Hawkins &amp; Bayne (1984)</ref>. This labelled alga was separated from '"N-labelled medium by centrifuging (2500 rpm for 5 min) and resuspending in filtered seawater two times before being administered to 38 clams of 5.5 to 6.5 cm shell length, with a dry tissue weight of 464 + 28 mg. Each clam was maintained for 4 h within separate beakers, each containing 4 1 of the same unfiltered seawater to which clams had acclimated, having added sufficient labelled alga to achieve an initial concentration of 7500 I.</p><p>galbana cells . ml ' . Immediately following this incubation, aliquots of the 15Nlabelled culture, as well as all '"N-labelled alga remaining within the beakers that had been used to incubate 6 of the 38 clams, were collected separately on 4.7 cm GFC filters. The same six clams were transferred to shallow open-topped beakers submerged within natural unfiltered seawater in the raceway of acclimation. All faeces produced by each of these six clams were subsequently pipetted onto separate 2.5 cm GFC filters after intervals of 1.2, 2, 3, 4, 5, 8, 9, 10.75 and 21 h. Filters were dried to constant weight at 6O"C, and stored in a desiccator before analysing each sample for the abundance of stable isotope "N. Ingestion of "N was calculated by subtracting the algal '"N that remained in each beaker after the removal of clams from the amount initially added to each beaker. Gross assimilation efficiency for "N was then calculated separately for each clam as [((15N ingested)-(total '"N egested as faeces over 21 h)) + ('"N ingested)] X 100. Regression analyses of the cumulative egestions of faecal 15N over time were used to estimate gut passage time as the interval after which 95% of all "N had been egested, applying a reciprocal square root transformation according to <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Bayne et al. (1989)</ref>.</p><p>Immediately following the same 4 h incubation, all of the other 32 clams that had been fed '"N-labelled alga were transferred back to natural unfiltered seawater in the raceway of acclimation.</p><p>Four of these clams were then sacrificed after each interval of 0, 2, 4, 8, 22, 45, 117 and 189 h, allowing separate determinations of the enrichment ( pg . clam ' ) of "N within zooxanthellae and host tissues. as described above.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.6.">Statistics</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>All statistical</head><p>tests and proceedures used in the analyses and presentation of data were undertaken using SYSTAT for Windows, Version 5 (SYSTAT Inc., Evanston, Illinois, USA).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Results</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.">The effects of darkness on net fluxes of ammonium-nitrogen</head><p>The mean (22 SE) dry soft tissue weights of clams from each size class were:</p><p>(1) 1.1 5 0.1 cm shell length = 1.7 t-0.3 mg;</p><p>(2) 11.7 2 0.3 cm shell length = 2.9 z 0.4 g: and</p><p>(3) 19.4 t 1.2 cm shell length = 17.3 + 4.1 g.</p><p>Changes in net ammonium flux (pmole . clam-' . h-') over 13 days following the transfer of three size classes of clam from full light to total darkness are illustrated in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref>. Immediately before excluding all light, there was a mean net influx of ammonium in the larger size classes. But after 2 days darkness, statistically significant (p &lt; 0.01) effluxes were recorded, which increased before reaching plateaux after 10 and 6 days, respectively <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">(Fig. 1)</ref>. In contrast, significant (p &lt; 0.001) net effluxes of ammonium were recorded in the smallest size class even before their transfer to darkness. Whilst net effluxes of ammonium in this group increased slightly after a further 2 days darkness, they remained unchanged (p &gt; 0.05) thereafter <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">(Fig. 1)</ref>. Therefore, relative to larger clams, net ammonium flux in smaller clams was less dependent upon light. Associated with these losses of ammonium-nitrogen, 33% of all experimental clams from the smallest size class had died after 13 days whilst starved of particles in total darkness. There was no mortality in either of the larger size classes.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.">The effects of clam size on host ammonium excretion, host protein requirements and total (gross) ammonium influx</head><p>Steady-state rates of net ammonium efflux following prolonged darkness are assumed to represent rates of ammonium excretion from the host tissues alone. When calculated from the fluxes measured after 10 and 13 days in darkness ( <ref type="figure">Fig.  l)</ref>, mean rates of ammonium excretion from host tissues were 10.77 ? 1.15 nmole, 2.34 + 0.15 pmole and 5.60 -C 1.05 pmole . h-' for clams with average total dry tissue weights of 1.7 mg, 2.9 g and 17.3 g, respectively.</p><p>These clams had also been starved of particulates, so that these net rates of excretion represented proteinnitrogen of endogenous origin, and did not include ammonium-nitrogen deriving from the catabolism of nutrients recently absorbed from ingested particles. The positive relationship evident between total dry tissue weight (W, g) and this excretion of endogenous protein-nitrogen as ammonium from host tissues (EN, pmole . h-" is best described by the allometric equation:</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">EN = 0.90 (0.80, 1.02) W".6y (z".03),<label>(1)</label></formula><p>where n = 12, r2 = 0.99, p &lt; 0.0001, and bracketed values indicate 95% CL. Mean (22 SE) rates of net ammonium efflux (-) or influx (+) measured at 600 pE*rn-'. ss', immediately before excluding all light, were -6.72 2 2.48 nmole, +0.05 ? 0.26 pmole, and +2.16 '-+ 4.78 ,umole * h-' for clams with average total dry tissue weights of 1.7 mg, 2.9 g and 17.3 g, respectively <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">(Fig. 1)</ref>. Therefore, total dry tissue weight (W, g) appeared to have a significant positive effect on mean net ammonium flux (NAF, pmole . h -'), best de scribed by the linear equation:</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">NAF = -0.01 ( t 1.64) + 0.17 ( + 0.13) W,<label>(2)</label></formula><p>where n = 14, r2 = 0.33, and p &lt; 0.03.</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">1.0 -1.3 CM SHELL LENGTH 5 YE -_--____________________________________--~-----. il,~;( L1 f ~ =,1 -2 ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' 1 0 5 10 15</formula><p>' -11.4 -12.1 CM SHELL LENGTH UPTAKE -3."""""""" 0 5 10 15 _.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8">-</head><p>18.1 -20.2 CM SHFXL LENGTH The difference between NAF measured in daylight and EN is assumed to represent the total (gross) uptake of ammonium associated with the photosynthetic activity of zooxanthellae in particle-starved clams (AZS, pmole . h '). Using the present net fluxes measured at 600 ,uE. rnm2. s ', the mean (52 SE) rates of AZS were 4.05 + 1.60 nmole, 2.39 -+ 0.39 pmole and 7.77 + 5.12 ,umole . h-' for clams with average total dry tissue weights of 1.7 mg, 2.9 g and 17.3 g, respectively.</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">4 6 - -1 z- LLi 4- UPTAKE ______________________ I 1 -8 ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' 0 5 10 15 TIME (d)</formula><p>The positive relation evident between AZS (pmole . h-') and total dry tissue weight (IV, g) is best described by the allometric equation: <ref type="figure">".80 (zo.o6)</ref>, <ref type="formula">3</ref>where y1 = 12, r2 = 0.98, and p &lt; 0.0001. <ref type="figure">Fig. 2</ref> illustrates a die1 pattern of natural irradiance and associated net fluxes of both oxygen and ammonium in mid-sized experimental clams (11.7 ? 0.3 cm). The decrease in irradiance following a peak before 0800 was due to increased cloud. It remained cloudy for the rest of the day, so that the cycle of irradiance peaked at 279 puE.rn-*.</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">AZS = 0.78 (0.60, 1.02) W</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3.">Daily net fluxes of oxygen and ammonium-nitrogen</head><p>ss', compared with what would have been about 600 ,uE + mm*. s-' on a cloudless day.</p><p>Even on this overcast day, we observed large net production of oxygen, which occured at rates that were symmetrical about each peak in irradiance <ref type="figure">(Fig. 2)</ref>. Over the full die1 cycle, clams were net producers of oxygen (1.06 ? 0.11 mmole 0, . clam-' .24 h-". There was a constant net consumption of oxygen throughout the period of darkness <ref type="figure">(Fig. 2)</ref>, of which more than 95% is assumed to represent respiration by the host tissues alone (c.f. <ref type="bibr">Klumpp et al., 1992)</ref>. Compared with oxygen, net ammonium fluxes were not as dependent upon irradiance <ref type="figure">(Fig. 2)</ref>. However, net influx decreased throughout the hours of darkness between about 1700 and 0500, ultimately resulting in a significant net efflux from each clam. The subsequent transition to a state of net influx started before 0530, apparently before first light <ref type="figure">(Fig. 2)</ref>. Over the full die1 cycle, there was a significant (p &lt; 0.05) net influx of ammonium, which averaged (-C2 SE) 2.06 5 0.59 pmole . clam-'.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.4.">Ammonium uptake both by particle-fed or particle-starved clams, the proportional translocation of nitrogen from zooxanthellae to host tissues, and faecal losses of nitrogen assimilated as dissolved ammonium</head><p>Ammonium depletions during incubations with spiked seawater are illustrated in <ref type="figure">Fig. 3</ref>. Clams that had been feeding upon natural particles took up ammonium at only half the rate of those that had been maintained for the preceeding 48 h in filtered seawater (t value = 5.66, df = 10, p &lt; 0.0001) <ref type="figure">(Fig. 3)</ref>. Uptake of ammonium was therefore stimulated in response to particle starvation. Experimental clams of 4.5 to 5.5 cm shell length had an average (+2 SE) total wet tissue weight of 1.542 5 0.55 g, and contained 95.92 (L4.27) mg protein, of which 7.44 (51.48) mg (7.8%) was within zooxanthellae. Based upon these average protein contents, and direct measures of the atom% of nitrogen isotope "N, <ref type="figure">Fig. 4</ref>    <ref type="figure">Fig. 4</ref>. Time-courses of the enrichments by "N (mean t 2 SE) both in all zooxanthellae (0 and dashed line) and in all host tissues (+ and solid line) separated from individual T. gigas after the incubation of whole clams in ammonium-'5N chloride. All clams were of 4.5 to 5.5 cm shell length, with a mean + 2 SF dry tissue weight of 238 i-26 mg. Lines were fitted by least-squares.</p><p>and equations given in the text.</p><p>this establishes that over the full time-course of 245 h, a minimum of 83.8% of the '5N-ammonium lost from zooxanthellae was translocated to host tissues. Cumulative egestion of '"N within faeces (F, ,ug "N enrichment) from clams that had been starved of suspended particles for 48 h before incubation in "N-1abelled ammonium increased over time (T, min) according to the following linear equation: F = 0.008 ( f 0.025) + 0.0027 ( i 0.0008) T, <ref type="bibr">(6)</ref> where n = 18, r2 = 0.74, and p &lt; 0.0001.</p><p>There was therefore a significant loss of '"N within faeces. But Eqs. 4 and 6 show that the cumulative egestion of "N as faeces over the 48 h of collection represented an average of only 0.5% of the coincident loss from zooxanthellae. This was consistent with data indicating that there was no significant reduction in the atom % 15N (mean +-2 SE) within total soft clam tissues over the full experimental period of 245 h (0.611 k 0.248%) after being removed from incubation in ammonium-"N chloride (0.480 + 0.106%).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.5.">Absorption by the host from ingested particles, gut passage time and the direct uptake by zooxanthellae of nitrogen from host tissues</head><p>Organic nitrogen in natural particles ingested by T. gigas on Davies Reef was absorbed with a mean (?2 SE) net efficiency of 78.1 -C 9.4%.</p><p>Mean rates of faecal "N egestion (pug excess 15N clam-' . h-') by each clam (n = 6) over time following the ingestion of "N-1abelled alga are illustrated in <ref type="figure">Fig.  5</ref>. Whilst highly variable between individuals, these rates were greatest after about 4 h, and had returned to statistically insignificant levels after 16 h <ref type="figure">(Fig. 5</ref>). Average gut passage time (22 SE), when 95% of all faecal 15N had been egested, was 14.4 + 8.7 h. Over this time, 15N was absorbed with a mean (22 SE) gross efficiency of 99.2 + 0.4%. <ref type="figure">Fig. 6</ref> shows how mean 15N enrichments (pug clam-') both in host tissues and in zooxanthellae increased rapidly to asymptotic maxima over time after  <ref type="figure">Fig. 5</ref>. Time-course of the rate of 15N egestion (mean t 2 SE, n = 6) in faeces from T. gigas of 5.5 to 6.5 cm shell length, with a mean -t 2 SE dry tissue weight of 464 2 28 mg. Data are for "N in excess of natural levels, and are plotted at the mid-point of time over which each faecal sample was collected. The dotted line starts from the mid-point of the 4-h period over which clams ingested "N-labelled alga. . Time-courses of the enrichment by "N (mean t 2 SE) both in all zooxanthellae (0 and dashed line) and in all host tissues (+ and solid line) separated from individual T. gigas that had ingested "N-labelled alga over the previous 4 h. All clams were of 5.5 to 6.5 cm shell length, with a mean 2 2 SE dry tissue weight of 464 -t 28 mg. Lines were fitted by eye, with asymptotes which match the mean maximal enrichments that have been calculated for all data collected after 22 h (refer Results).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Materials</head><p>and Methods was 31.8 2 4.5 pug 15N clam-', indicating a mean absorption efficiency of (26.6/31.8) X 100 = 83.6%, which compares well with our indirect measure (described above) of the net efficiency with which clams absorbed organic nitrogen from natural particulates (78.1 I? 9.4%).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.6.">Relative contributions of zooxanthellae and filter-feeding to host nutrition</head><p>High performance liquid chromatography has been used to show that ammonium is the only nitrogen waste product excreted in bivalves studied to date (e.g. <ref type="bibr">Manahan et al., 1983)</ref>. Further, all clams studied here were sexually immature, so that production was only deposited as somatic tissues. Total aminonitrogen requirements for host-tissue growth (mg N . day-' ) may therefore be estimated as the sum of observed tissue growth (mg N. day-') and associated excretion of ammonium-nitrogen by host tissues (mg N. day ~I). Growth in shell length of T. gigas over 28 months in Davies Reef lagoon was essentially linear, from 1.7 cm to 19 cm at an average rate of 0.209 mm. day-', while dry tissue weight (W, g) varied with shell length (L, mm) according to the allometric equation:</p><p>W= (0.34 X lo-") L3.3h <ref type="bibr">(Klumpp et al., 1992)</ref>. These relations indicate that clams of 0.001 g (1.08 cm shell length), 0.1 g (4.25 cm), 1 g (8.43 cm) and 10 g (16.7 cm) dry tissue weight grew at rates of 66.7 ,ug, 1.7 mg, 8.6 mg and 41.8 mg dry tissue weight * day-', respectively. The average (22 SE) nitrogen content of total dry clam tissues was 7.22 2 0.07%, and has been used to convert the above estimates of daily growth in total tissue biomass to nitrogen equivalents <ref type="table">(Table 1)</ref>. The rates with which clams clear water of all suspended particles (clearance rate) remained essentially unchanged throughout day and night, and were similar at Davies <ref type="bibr">Reef and AIMS (Klumpp et al., 1992)</ref>. Respiration rates for clam host tissues were also independent of site and light-history <ref type="bibr">(Klumpp et al. ibid)</ref>. Given such constancy in rates both of feeding and of metabolism, we have assumed that the excretion of ammonium by host tissues measured in the laboratory at AIMS can be related to natural rates of feeding and growth recorded on Davies Reef.</p><p>The rate with which particulate nitrogen was absorbed by clams is calculated as the product of clearance rate, concentration of available nitrogen, and absorption efficiency. We have shown that clearance rate (CR, 1. h-') varied with clam dry tissue weight (IV, g) according to the allometric function: CR = 1.85 IV"'" <ref type="bibr">(Klumpp et al., 1992)</ref>. Seasonal data describing the availability of suspended organic particles in the lagoon at Davies Reef indicate average annual concentrations of 97 ,ug. carbon 1-l and 8 pug nitrogen. ll', giving a C:N ratio of 12 <ref type="bibr">(Klumpp et al., 1992;</ref><ref type="bibr">and Klumpp, unpubl. data)</ref>. These data have been used with our present measure of net absorption efficiency to calculate size-dependent differences in the rates with which particulate nitrogen were absorbed by T. gigas <ref type="table">(Table 1)</ref>.</p><p>When calculated using both the average NAF that we recorded during daylight (0700 to 1600) ( <ref type="figure">Fig. 2)</ref> and EN measured after 10 days darkness in clams of the same size (11.4-12.1 cm shell length; <ref type="figure">Fig. l)</ref>, then the total (gross) 24 h uptake of ammonium by zooxanthellae represented 97.4 + 1.2% of the total 24 h ammonium influx computed using all rates of NAF that we recorded over the full diurnal cycle. Therefore, we have used allometric Eq. 3 describing the relation between total dry tissue weight and total (gross) uptake h-' of ammonium by zooxanthellae at 600 puE. rn-'. s-' to estimate AZS over 24 h in clams of each size class <ref type="table">(Table 1)</ref>.</p><p>We have established that zooxanthellae effected most, if not all, primary assimilation of dissolved ammonium taken up from the surrounding seawater by T. gigas <ref type="figure">(Figs. 3 and 5)</ref>. In addition both to that primary assimilation and to the uptake of endogenous protein-nitrogen excreted following the catabolism of host tissue, zooxanthellae assimilate ammonium deriving from deamination by the host tissues of exogenous protein-nitrogen that has recently been absorbed from ingested particulates <ref type="figure">(Fig. 6</ref>). Such assimilation was not included within our above measures of AZS, that were calculated as NAF in particle-fed clams during daylight plus EN measured in particle-starved clams during prolonged darkness. To estimate this additional uptake by zooxanthellae under natural conditions of particle availability, it is notable that efficiencies of nitrogen conversion [(net protein balance/protein absorption) X 1001 appear reasonably constant in nonsymbiotic shellfish, when about 12% of all protein-nitrogen absorbed in excess of <ref type="table">Table   I</ref> Growth and metabohsm in four we classes of giant clam 7'. g,ga. to compare the relative utdisatlons of metabohsable mtrogen and carbon <ref type="bibr">(refer Klumpp et al.. lY92)</ref>. and to illustrate the estimated relative contributions of ammomum-mlrogrn translocated from Tooxanthellae (AT) wsu mtrogen absorbed from mgested partxles (A) towards the total requirements  CLAM DRY TISSUE WEIGHT (g) <ref type="figure">Fig. 7</ref>. The estimated proportional contributions of (i) translocation from zooxanthellae of nitrogen assimilated as ammonium and (ii) absorption from filtered particles towards both the total nitrogen and the total carbon (data from Klumpp et al.. 1992) required for observed tissue growth and metabolism in T. @gas of different dry tissue weights. <ref type="figure">(Fig. 3)</ref>. Such uptake also required exposure to light <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">(Figs. 1 and 2</ref>) (cf. <ref type="bibr">Wilkerson &amp; Trench, 1986)</ref>. Compared with net oxygen fluxes, net ammonium fluxes were not as dependent upon irradiance, so that net uptake continued well into the night, although declining to a state of net efflux <ref type="figure">(Fig. 2)</ref>. In addition, net uptake recommenced at least 1 h before first light, implying associated biological periodicity <ref type="figure">(Fig. 2)</ref>. The result was that we recorded significant net daily uptake of ammonium by T. gigas monitored over 24 h in natural unspiked seawater containing about 0.5 FM ammonium <ref type="figure">(Fig. 2)</ref>. Stimulation of net ammonium uptake in response to starvation, and the continuing net uptake of ammonium for several hours in darkness, both imply the compensatory filling of internal pools, as is consistent with passive diffusion down concentration gradients created by localized substrate depletion (refer Introduction). Zooxanthellae comprise 8% of the total protein content of the symbiosis (refer Results). Yet after 3 h incubation in ammonium-"N chloride, more than 50% of the 15N retained by T. gigus was present in zooxanthellae <ref type="figure">(Fig. 4)</ref>; and the mean (22 SE) atom% enrichment of lSN within zooxanthellae was 5.554 +-1.546%, compared with only 0.370 + 0.022% in host tissues. Given that some of the 15N in host tissues must have been 15N-ammonium within haemolymph, this suggests that zooxanthellae were responsible for most if not all primary assimilation of the 15N-labelled ammonium.</p><p>Certainly, it is well-established in anthozoan symbiosis systems that photosynthesis is required to provide the carbon skeletons for assimilation of inorganic nitrogen <ref type="bibr">(Muscatine &amp; D'Elia, 1978)</ref>. However, it should be remembered that the initial concentration (15 ,uM) of the present pulse of "N-1abelled ammonium was well in excess of natural levels. Where host tissues do assimilate significant ammonium, as in the Hydra-Chlorellu symbiosis <ref type="bibr">(Rees, 1987</ref><ref type="bibr">(Rees, , 1991</ref><ref type="bibr">and refer Introduction)</ref>, then the pathway effecting that assimilation is usually fully saturated <ref type="bibr">(Spencer Davies, 1992)</ref>. Therefore, when a clam is exposed to high concentrations of ammonium, as in the present study, symbiotic algae will assimilate any ammonium not assimilated by hosts tissues. It follows that assimilation of ammonium by host tissues may be of proportionally greatest significance when there is little ammonium within the surrounding seawater. Our findings also establish the rapid direct uptake by zooxanthellae of nitrogen that had been absorbed by host tissues from ingested alga <ref type="figure">(Fig. 6)</ref>. Within 22 h of ingesting that alga, zooxanthellae contained [2.7 + (2.7 + 23.9)] X 100 = 10% of all the '"N that had been absorbed by each clam (refer Results). Given that zooxanthellae comprise 8% of all protein in the T. gigas symbiosis, this again suggests unrestricted access by the zooxanthellae to nitrogen, which in this case was within amino acids and/or ammonium deriving from the hosts digestion and/or deamination of ingested nutrients. <ref type="bibr">Griffiths &amp; Streamer (1988)</ref> showed that the major early products of 14Cphotosynthesis in T. gigas include glucose, oligosaccharides and amino acids, and described how these products are each translocated from zooxanthellae to the host. Our findings suggest that most if not all the nitrogen within those amino acids had been first assimilated by zooxanthellae, rather than by host tissues. We have also shown that an average of 94.7 (83.8, 106.9)% of the "N released by zooxanthellae was subsequently incorporated within host tissues <ref type="figure">(Fig. 4</ref>, and refer Results). Carbon budgets suggest that the host receives a similar proportion of 90 to 95% of the carbon that is fixed daily by zooxanthellae <ref type="bibr">(Fitt, 1993)</ref>. But perhaps most striking are present observations that enrichments by "N in both the zooxanthellae and host tissues remained statistically unchanged from 22 h up until at least 189 h after ingesting 15N-labelled alga <ref type="figure">(Fig. 6)</ref>, and that the atom% "N within total soft tissues of T. gigas remained statistically unchanged for at least 10 days after incubation in ammonium-'"N chloride (refer Results). Therefore, collective findings indicate that zooxanthellae help to recycle and conserve close to 100% of all the nitrogenous end-products excreted by host tissues. Such impressive retentions could only be achieved if essentially all ammonium-I J. <ref type="bibr">Exp. Mar. Biol. Ecol. 190 (1995) 263-290</ref> nitrogen excreted by the host is freely available for assimilation and recycling by the zooxanthellae in T. gigas. This is in obvious contrast to what has been proposed for the the Hydra-Chlorella symbiosis <ref type="bibr">(McAuley, 1987;</ref><ref type="bibr">Rees, 1987</ref><ref type="bibr">Rees, , 1991</ref><ref type="bibr">and refer Introduction)</ref>.</p><p>Such high retentions are also of interest given the observation that giant clams persistently release live, whole zooxanthellae in their faeces <ref type="bibr">(Ricard &amp; Salvat, 1977;</ref><ref type="bibr">Lucas, 1993)</ref>. Similar release was observed in the present study, suggesting that the loss of nitrogen in undigested zooxanthellae is trivial, when considered as a proportion of the total uptake. Indeed, we have shown that less than 1% of all '"N assimilated by zooxanthellae was lost within faeces collected over the following 48 h (refer Results).</p><p>As an example among lamellibranchs lacking algal symbionts, retention efficiencies do not exceed 90% of the protein-nitrogen absorbed in Mytilus edulis of similar dry tissue weight <ref type="bibr">(Hawkins &amp; Bayne, 1991)</ref>. The higher efficiency observed here is clearly of major ecological significance, helping to explain how T. gigas achieves the fastest tissue growth of any bivalve, despite living in waters that are notoriously poor in nitrogen (refer Introduction). These findings also confirm that this symbiosis is of mutual benefit, with an evident selective advantage over free-living plants and animals, and which helps to explain the general success of similar symbioses in coral reef environments.</p><p>Quite apart from the uptake of inorganic nitrogen, we have confirmed that T. gigas also functions as a typical filter-feeder, utilizing the suspended particulate matter available in reef waters <ref type="bibr">(Klumpp et al., 1992)</ref>. Here, we report an average (22 SE) gut passage time of 14.4 5 8.7 h in T. gigas of 464 2 28 mg dry tissue weight. This is far longer than a gut passage time of about 2.9 h in the lamellibranch mussel M. edulis of similar size, as predicted using an established weight exponent <ref type="bibr">(Hawkins et al., 1990)</ref> applied to equivalent data for mussels feeding actively in a particle-rich environment <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Bayne et al., 1989)</ref>. Longer gut passage times increase the potential for extraction of nutrients from ingested matter, thus helping to explain why both net and gross absorption efficiencies recorded here for organic nitrogen in T. gigas (78.1 -+ 9.4% and 99.2 2 0.4%, respectively) were very much higher than previously recorded in M. edulis (56.1 ? 35.5% and 80.8 2 1.7%, respectively; <ref type="bibr">Hawkins and Bayne, 1984)</ref>. As a possible explanation both of longer gut passage time and such high assimilation efficiencies, <ref type="bibr">Yonge (1936)</ref> observed that the ducts leading into the digestive diverticula of tridacnid clams appear exceptionally wide, that "every opportunity is taken of passing material into them", and that "only as a last resort is it (material) passed into the mid-gut" (p. 294). This suggests that, compared with other lamellibranchs, a far higher proportion of the particles ingested by T. gigas are digested</p><p>intracellularly.</p><p>An additional possible explanation of the higher assimilation efficiencies in T. gigus is that suspended POM may have been be more digestible over Davies Reef than in previous studies of M. edufis at temperate latitutes. However, we favour the first explanation, involving greater intracellular digestion and longer gut passage times. The remainder of this discussion will consider metabolic requirements for nitrogen, and the relative extent to which filter-feeding and nitrogen taken up as ammonium before translocation from zooxanthellae satisfy those requirements in T. gigus of different dry tissue weight. Rates of net ammonium excretion measured here in clams starved of particles whilst maintained in darkness for more than 10 days may be assumed to reflect basal maintenence requirements for endogenous protein as a source of energy in the host tissues alone (MRH, mg protein.</p><p>day-'). These requirements varied with total dry tissue weight (IV, g) according to the allometric equation: MRH = 1.77 (1.56, 1.99) W".69 (+".03),</p><p>where n = 12, r2 = 0.99, and p &lt; 0.0001. The weight exponent of 0.69 (kO.03) is similar to that previously reported for protein maintenance requirements in feeding M. edulis as follows: <ref type="bibr">0.94 (0.82, 1.06) W'." (+o.'9), (8)</ref> where n = 5, r2 = 0.98, and p &lt; 0.001 <ref type="bibr">(Hawkins &amp; Bayne, 1991)</ref>. However, comparison of the intercepts for Eqs. 7 and 8 confirms that, even in particlestarved T. gigas, rates of nitrogen excretion from the host were almost twice (p &lt; 0.05) the full maintenance requirements for both endogenous and exogenous protein-nitrogen in M. edulis of similar dry tissue weight. This is consistent with previous data suggesting greater catabolic reliance upon proteinaceous substrates among bivalves from lower latitudes, where greater environmental stability may reduce the requirements for carbon-rich reserves <ref type="bibr">(Hawkins et al., 1987)</ref>. It is significant that the assimilation by zooxanthellae of ammonium-nitrogen (AZS) was greater than the basal excretion of endogenous protein-nitrogen by host tissues (EN) in particle-starved T. gigas larger than 0.001 g dry tissue weight <ref type="table">(Table 1)</ref>. Therefore, if starved of particles, the host tissues of adult clams may obtain all basal nitrogen requirements from zooxanthellae, and larger T. gigus may actually be in positive nitrogen balance, although any growth would be slower than in clams feeding upon natural particles.</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">MR =</formula><p>In particle-fed clams, translocation of the nitrogen acquired as ammonium by zooxanthellae contributed an estimated 11% of the total requirements for tissue growth and metabolism in small clams of 0.001 g dry tissue weight, but this contribution increased with body size to a maximum of 45% in clams of 10 g dry tissue weight <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">(Fig. 7, Table  1</ref>). Alternatively, nitrogen ingested as particles contributed as much as 63% of the total requirements of very small clams, declining steadily to only 23% in clams of 10 g dry tissue weight <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">(Fig. 7, Table 1</ref>). We have earlier reported that T. gigas smaller than about 0.1 g dry tissue weight require carbon intake from both ingested particles and zooxanthellae to achieve observed rates of growth <ref type="bibr">(Klumpp et al., 1992)</ref>. Here, the contribution from filter-feeding towards total nitrogen requirements began to exceed the estimated contribution from algal symbionts in T. gigas of less than the same size (about 0.1 g dry tissue weight; <ref type="figure">Fig. 7)</ref>. In addition, it is notable that total host tissue excretion represented a fairly constant proportion (0.37 ? 0.02, mean &amp; 2 SE) of the total requirements for growth and metabolism in each size class (n = 4), so that zooxanthellae only began to contribute more nitrogen than was already excreted and recycled within clams larger than about 0.1 g dry tissue weight <ref type="figure">(Fig. 7)</ref>  <ref type="table">(Table  1)</ref>. Clearly, ingested particles and/or other non-autotrophic processes (refer below) were essential as a source of both the carbon and nitrogen required for observed rates of growth in juvenile T. gigas.</p><p>Greater observed dependence on suspended particulates and/or other nonautotrophic processes among small T. gigas should not be suprising. Clam larvae acquire all their zooxanthellae from surrounding seawater, so that newlymetamorphosed clams have fewer symbionts during the early stages of infection with zooxanthellae <ref type="bibr">(Fitt et al., 1986</ref><ref type="bibr">(Fitt et al., , 1993</ref><ref type="bibr">Fitt, 1993)</ref>. This helps to explain why, when starved of particles, T. gigas larvae did not survive beyond metamorphosis <ref type="bibr">(Southgate, 1988)</ref>. Similarly, in the present study, small T. gigas were the first to die when particle-starved during prolonged darkness (refer Results). Presumably, compared with larger clams, those smallest individuals and larvae lacked sufficient zooxanthellae to retain and recycle as much of the ammonium excreted when host tissues catabolized structural proteins as the main source of energy. Under natural cycles of daylight, greater dependence of small T. gigas on suspended particles may also reflect the observation that zooxanthellae are increasingly shaded as the mantle becomes relatively thicker in larger clams, with the result that photosynthetic rates in juvenile T. gigus become saturated at levels of irradiance that are commonly below ambient, whereas photosynthetic rates in larger clams are not saturated at even the highest natural light intensities <ref type="bibr">(Fisher et al., 1985)</ref>. Although not as obvious in gross terms, it should be remembered that particulate feeding may continue to play a lifelong role in helping to satisfy more specific requirements for essential amino acids, phosphorus and/or trace metals. Irrespective of size, ingested particles and ammonium-nitrogen acquired by zooxanthellae together satisfied a constant proportion of about 70% of total amino-nitrogen requirements for observed tissue growth and metabolism <ref type="figure">(Fig. 7</ref>). Yet ingested particles and zooxanthellae more than satisfied the total requirements for carbon; those requirements having been computed using the same observed rates of particle filtration and tissue growth ( <ref type="figure">Fig. 7</ref>; data from <ref type="bibr">Klumpp et al., 1992)</ref>. There are at least three possible explanations for this apparent shortfall in amino-nitrogen:</p><p>(1) Average net uptake of dissolved ammonium by T. gigus at Davies Reef may have been significantly higher than measured in our experimental seawater at AIMS. Indeed, we wonder if the net daily uptake of ammonium recorded at AIMS would have been higher on a brighter day, for irradiance was only half than expected on a cloudless day (refer Results). Ammonium uptake is certainly dependent upon light (Figs. 1 and 2) (cf. <ref type="bibr">Wilkerson &amp; Trench, 1986</ref>). although nothing is known of whether net uptake may be enhanced at greater irradiances.</p><p>A further possibility is that by measuring net flux in closed systems, we may have limited the availability of ammonia, thereby underestimating natural fluxes within the open sea. (2) T. gigus may effect net uptake of dissolved inorganic nitrogen either as ammonium or nitrate <ref type="bibr">(Wilkerson and Trench, 1986;</ref><ref type="bibr">Fitt et al., 1993)</ref> both of which stimulate tissue growth <ref type="bibr">(Heslinga et al., 1990;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Braley, 1992;</ref><ref type="bibr">Belda et al., 1993)</ref>. Rates of nitrate uptake were consistently less than of ammonium uptake, when offered separately <ref type="bibr">(Fitt et al., 1993)</ref> and nothing is known of any possible ammonium repression of nitrate uptake. However, we have recorded concentrations of up to 1.0 ,uM nitrate on the back of the reef flat at Davies Reef, compared with an associated maximum of 0.45 ,uM ammonium <ref type="bibr">(Klumpp &amp; Hawkins, unpubl. data)</ref>. Therefore, it is possible that T. gigas assimilated dissolved nitrogen as nitrate whilst growing on Davies Reef. (3) Some of the "missing" nitrogen may have been acquired by T. gigas as dissolved organic matter (DOM). The epidermis of T. gigus mantle is highly convoluted, being made up of microvilli with micropinocytotic channels, and therefore appears adapted for the active uptake of DOM <ref type="bibr">(Fankboner, 1971</ref>). The only confirmation of such uptake in tridacnids has been the work of <ref type="bibr">Goreau et al. (1973)</ref>, who described incorporation of [3H]-leucine from ambient seawater into the mantle and ctenidial epithelia of T. maxima. In other non-symbiotic bivalves, relatively recent work using high performance liquid chromatography under bacteria-free conditions has confirmed the uptake both of amino acids and sugars, which appear to satisfy very significant proportions of up to at least 24% of measured energy expenditure <ref type="bibr">(Hawkins &amp; Bayne, 1991)</ref>. Admittedly, uptake of DOM may only be important as a source of energy in small T. gigas, or during prolonged darkness. But as a potential additional source of amino-nitrogen, then DOM may be of greater general significance.</p><p>In conclusion, the spectacular growth of T. gigus results from a number of complementary processes. This study has established that organic nitrogen is absorbed with exceptional efficiencies from ingested particulates, due in part to slow gut passage times that may reflect a high proportion of intracellular digestion.</p><p>Alternatively, and despite current uncertainties raised by work on the Hydra-Chlorella symbiosis (refer Introduction), our results indicate that ammonium-nitrogen excreted by the host is freely available for assimilation and recycling by the zooxanthellae in T. gigas. The giant clam therefore retains and conserves essentially all nitrogenous end-products, which would otherwise be excreted from bivalves without algal symbionts.</p><p>In additional contrast to normal heterotrophic bivalves, zooxanthellae enable T. gigus to obtain dissolved inorganic nitrogen from surrounding natural seawater. Added potential for increased uptake from transient pulses both of ammonium and nitrate, as well as the <ref type="bibr">(enhanced)</ref> ability to absorb nutrients from ingested particles, collectively enable opportunistic acquisition according to circumstance. This means that the relative contributions from any one source are likely to differ with geographic location, environmental condition, and developmental stage. For example, we have shown that net uptake of inorganic nitrogen by zooxanthellae in large clams was modulated according to nutritional history, light history, and the concentration of available ammonium.</p><p>However, such uptake was not as significant in small clams, that required ingested particles and/or other non-autotrophic processes for observed growth. Further work is needed to establish the effects of irradiance on uptake of DIN, and to quantify uptake of DOM as a potential additional non-autotrophic source of nitrogen.</p><p>To help understand the true role of algal symbiosis, it will also be necessary to compare specific amino acid requirements of the host with what may be provided from zooxanthellae, as DOM, and/or from ingested particles.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Changes in mean (22 SE) net ammonium flux following the transfer of three size-classes of T. gigas from an irradiance of 600 FE. m ' s ' in unfiltered seawater to total darkness in particle-free water. Net ammonium flux in the light, immediately before transfer to darkness, is illustrated at day 0.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Fig. 2. Irradiance, net oxygen flux and net ammomum flux (mean i-2 SE) plotted against time of day for T. gigas with a mean (22 SE) shell length of 11.7 k 0.3 cm (2.997 k 0.407 g dry tissue weight). whilst maintained in an open-air raceway under the natural light regime.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Fig. 6. Time-courses of the enrichment by "N (mean t 2 SE) both in all zooxanthellae (0 and dashed line) and in all host tissues (+ and solid line) separated from individual T. gigas that had ingested "N-labelled alga over the previous 4 h. All clams were of 5.5 to 6.5 cm shell length, with a mean 2 2 SE dry tissue weight of 464 -t 28 mg. Lines were fitted by eye, with asymptotes which match the mean maximal enrichments that have been calculated for all data collected after 22 h (refer Results).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>absorption from Ingested partvzulates. takinp Into account both metabolx faecal low\ and faecal 10s~ of dwxded rooxanthellae (refer Matcrlals and Methods. and Results). "Measured followmg &gt;I0 days partvzle-starvation m thr dark. ' Computed as dcscrtbed m the Results for partlcle~frd clamp a? FX = (().I! x A). " Computed al L; = (,!,\I T EX). ' Computed as descrlhed m the Resulta a, AZ5 = (EV + .I'AF) urmg the separate fitted relatlom for EN (Eq. I) and NAF at 600 pE.rn-'.a? (Eq. 2). that wue each matured directl) in particle-starved clams. ' Computed a~ dewibed m the Results as AZF = (AZS t I-X). ' Computed as Ar = (AZF x O.YS). on the hasis of present findings that 95% ot "N-ammonium released by zooxanthellae uere subsequently mcorporated wthm host tissues (refer Results).</figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>We wish especially to thank J. Lucas and his team in the James Cook University clam mariculture project for their support at Orpheus Island Research Station, and for providing us with all experimental</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>maintenance requirements is excreted as ammonium <ref type="bibr">(Hawkins and Bayne, 1991)</ref>. Therefore, we have estimated this excretion of exogenous nitrogen by host tissues <ref type="bibr">(EX, mg N. d-')</ref> in T. gigas as 0.12 X protein absorption <ref type="table">(Table 1)</ref>. To calculate the total assimilation of ammonium-nitrogen by zooxanthellae in particle-fed T. gigas (AZF) (mg N. day-'), we assume that zooxanthellae assimilate all of both the endogenous and exogenous nitrogen excreted as ammonium by host tissues before that nitrogen is lost from the clam. This is probably not appropriate for the smallest T. gigas, as particle-starved clams smaller than about 0.06 mg dry tissue weight showed net losses of ammonium (refer Eq. 2 above). However, this would result in an overestimation of the nitrogen assimilated by zooxanthellae, and thus will not affect our conclusion that zooxanthellae contribute only a small fraction of the total nitrogen requirements of very young clams (refer Discussion).</p><p>On this basis, AZF (mg N. day-') has been calculated as (AZS + EX) <ref type="table">(Table  1)</ref>. In turn, we have computed the contribution of ammonium-nitrogen translocated from zooxanthellae (AT) to help satisfy the clam's nitrogen requirements as the total uptake of ammoniumnitrogen by zooxanthellae (AZF) multiplied by the mean fraction (0.95) of "N which, released from zooxanthellae, was subsequently incorporated within host tissues of our experimental clams ( <ref type="figure">Fig. 4</ref>) ( <ref type="table">Table 1)</ref>. <ref type="figure">Fig. 7</ref> illustrates the relative calculated contributions of organic nitrogen absorbed from filtered particles (A) and ammonium-nitrogen translocated from zooxanthellae (AT) towards the total requirements for observed tissue growth and metabolism (G + U) <ref type="table">(Table 1)</ref>. Nitrogen absorbed from ingested particles represented the main estimated contribution (&gt;63%) to the total requirements of very small clams, but this contribution declined steadily with increasing size to only 23% in clams of 10 g dry tissue weight. Alternatively, whilst almost insignificant in the smallest clams, the estimated contribution from zooxanthellae increased with size, becoming greater than from ingested particles for clams larger than about 0.1 g dry tissue weight. Irrespective of clam size, the collective contributions from both filtered particles and the ammonium translocated from zooxanthellae together satisfied a constant proportion of about 70% of the total requirements for observed tissue growth and metabolism ( <ref type="figure">Fig. 7</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Discussion</head><p>Our results confirm rapid non-saturating uptake of ammonium by T. gigas exposed to spiked seawater enriched to concentrations of up to 15 ,uM <ref type="figure">(Fig. 3</ref>). Similar findings have been reported both for T. crocea <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Burris, 1983)</ref> and T. gigus <ref type="bibr">(Wilkerson &amp; Trench, 1986;</ref><ref type="bibr">Fitt et al., 1993)</ref>. Presumably, this capacity for opportunistic uptake enables T. gigus to capitalise upon transient pulses in the natural environment, for greater availabilities of dissolved inorganic nitrogen are known to enhance tissue growth of the clam host (refer Introduction).</p><p>Among the novel findings reported here, net uptake of ammonium by T. gigus was modulated by previous nutritional history, doubling in particle-starved clams animals. We are also grateful to D. </p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J S</forename><surname>Hawkins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Klumpp</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Exp</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mar. Biol. Ed</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">190</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="263" to="290" />
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">A.J.S. Hawkins, D.W. Klumpp I .I. Exp. Mar. Biol. Ed. 190 (1995) 263-290</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Role of glutamine synthetase in ammonia assimilation by symbiotic marine dinoflagellates (zooxanthellae)</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="middle">S L J E</forename><surname>References Anderson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Burris</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1987" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">References Anderson. S.L. &amp; J.E. Burris, 1987. Role of glutamine synthetase in ammonia assimilation by symbiotic marine dinoflagellates (zooxanthellae).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mar. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">94</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="451" to="458" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Mar. Biol., Vol. 94, pp. 451-458.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Nutrient limitation in the giant clam-zooxanthellac symbiosis: effects of nutrient supplements on growth of the symbiotic partners</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">B L J S</forename><surname>Bayne</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Hawkins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="middle">&amp; J I P</forename><surname>Navarro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Iglesias</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mar. Ecol. hog. Ser</title>
		<editor>Belda. C.A., J.S. Lucas &amp; D. Yellowlees</editor>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">55</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="655" to="664" />
			<date type="published" when="1989" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Mar. Biol.</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">Bayne. B.L., A.J.S. Hawkins, E. Navarro &amp; J.I.P. Iglesias, 1989. The effects of seston concentration on feeding, digestion and growth in the mussel Myths edulis. Mar. Ecol. hog. Ser., Vol. 55, pp. 47-54. Belda. C.A., J.S. Lucas &amp; D. Yellowlees, 1993. Nutrient limitation in the giant clam-zooxanthellac symbiosis: effects of nutrient supplements on growth of the symbiotic partners. Mar. Biol., Vol. 117. pp. 655-664.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The giant clam: a hatchery and nursery culture manual. ACIAR Monograph No. 15. Australian Centrc for International Agriculture Research</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Braley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1992" />
			<pubPlace>Canberra</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Braley, R.D., 1992. The giant clam: a hatchery and nursery culture manual. ACIAR Monograph No. 15. Australian Centrc for International Agriculture Research, Canberra.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Uptake and assimilation of &quot;NH</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Burris</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mar. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">75</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="5" />
			<date type="published" when="1983" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Burris, R.H.. 1983. Uptake and assimilation of &quot;NH,&apos; by a variety of corals. Mar. Biol.. Vol. 75, pp. 1.5-155.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Assimilation of organic nitrogen by zooplankton</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Conover</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Limnol. Oceanogr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="338" to="345" />
			<date type="published" when="1966" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Conover, R.J., 1966. Assimilation of organic nitrogen by zooplankton. Limnol. Oceanogr.. Vol. 11. pp. 338-345.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Spawning induction, and larval and juvenile rearing of the giant clam Tridacna gigas</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Crawford</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Nash</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">&amp; J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Lucas</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Interdiscip. Sci. Rev</title>
		<editor>Crawford, C.M., J.S. Lucas &amp; J.L. Munro</editor>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="281" to="295" />
			<date type="published" when="1986" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Aquaculture</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">Crawford, C.M., W.J. Nash &amp; J.S. Lucas, 1986. Spawning induction, and larval and juvenile rearing of the giant clam Tridacna gigas. Aquaculture, Vol. 58, pp. 281-295. Crawford, C.M., J.S. Lucas &amp; J.L. Munro, 1987. The mariculture of giant clams. Interdiscip. Sci. Rev..</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">On the storage</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Degobbis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1973" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Degobbis, D., 1973. On the storage</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
