<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /Users/grace/grobid-0.6.1/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Economics, policy, supplies, forecasts 00/03457 Challenges for fuel cells as stationary power resource in the evolving energy enterprise</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Rastler</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Economics, policy, supplies, forecasts 00/03457 Challenges for fuel cells as stationary power resource in the evolving energy enterprise</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.1" ident="GROBID" when="2021-09-14T02:15+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>The primary market challenges for fuel cells as stationary power resources in evolving energy markets are reviewed. Fuel cell power systems have significant harriers to overcome in their anticipated role as decentralized energy power systems. Market segments for fuel cells include combined heat and power; low-cost energy, premium power; peak shaving; and load management and grid support. Understanding the role and fit of fuel cell systems in evolving energy markets and the highest value applications are a major challenge for developers and government funding organizations. The most likely adopters of fuel cell systems and the challenges facing each adopter in the target market segment are reviewed. Adopters include generation companies, utility distribution companies, retail energy service providers and end-users. Key challenges include: overcoming technology rusk; achieving retail competitiveness; understanding high value markets and end-user needs; distribution and service channels: regulatory policy issues: and the integration of these decentralized resources within the electrical distribution system.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>00/03458</head><p>Dry layer preparation and characterisation of polymer electrolyte fuel cell components Gulzow, E. e/ rrl. <ref type="bibr">Journul of Poner Sources, 2000, 86. (l-2)</ref> 352-362. The main problem for future fuel ceil commercialization is the cost of membrane-electrode assemblies (MEAS) satisfying both power density and lifetime requirements, At DLR, low-cost MEA production techniques are heing developed. These new MEAs are characterized and investigated with physical and electrochemical methods in order to study the power loss processes, the lifetime, the reaction mechanisms and in support of MEA development.</p><p>The possibilities for the characterization methods used will he demonstrated by various examples. At DLR, a new production technique based on the adaptation of a rolling process is developed for fuel cell electrode and MEA preparation.</p><p>After mixing the dry powder electrode material in a mill, it is hlown onto the membrane (or hacking) resulting in a uniformly distributed layer. This reactive layer is fixed and thoroughly connected to the membrane by passing them through a calender. In order to produce the second electrode, the same steps are repeated. This procedure is very simple and, as a dry process, avoids the use of any solvents and drying steps. A thickness of the reactive layer as low as 5 pm has been achieved, reducing the amount of catalyst needed and, thus, the costs. Electrochemical investigations have shown a performance comparable to that of commercial electrodes. The degradation of MEA for polymer membrane fuel cell (PEFC) components during the cell's lifetime, yields a change in the electrochemical hehaviour. The characterization of PEFC MEA-components after electrochemical operation has given information about the degradation of electrodes and membranes and about the change in the platinum distribution on the anode, whilst on the cathode, the platinum content is unchanged.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>00103459</head><p>Financial considerations of exploiting fuel cell technology MacKerron, G. Jortmul of Pmer <ref type="bibr">Sour~e.s. 2000, 86, (l-2)</ref>, 28833. Fuel cells were invented around 1839. If a technology is promising, hut not quite commercialised for 160 years, there is hound to he some scepticism from the rest of the world when it is announced, as it has been with increasing frequency in the 199Os, that fuel cells are on the verge of becoming commercial energy convertors. Observers have been told a similar story, though with less insistence, for many years. Nevertheless, it now appears to he true that fuel cells really are close to commercial status, and this means that practical questions about how they will enter the energy system start to become important.</p><p>Among these practical questions, economic and financial issues are clearly central. These economic and financial issues are now considered, not from a narrow perspective of financial analysis (though some technical issues of finance and economics are raised), but rather from an analysis of the wide range of factors that will impact on financtal and economic outcomes. In this process, some explicit attention is given to the status of the technologies, established and novel, that fuel cells must compete against, because the success of the fuel cell is at least as importantly determined by changes in the status of competing technologies as changes in fuel cells themselves.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>00/03460</head><p>Liberalisation -challenges and opportunities for fuel cells Baentsch, F. Journal of Pour Sources, 2000, 86, (l-2), 84-89. New technological developments always have to face the problem that they are new. Bemg new means that such technologies have to enter into market segments that are usually already more or less served by traditional techniques.</p><p>Therefore, initial market volumes are low and units are produced in only small quantities with relatively high associated costs.</p><p>Low market volumes and high costs could lead new technologies into a 'vicious ctrcle' where they never manage to break through the threshold of economic viability and therefore never manage to acquire substantial market share. Fortunately, technological developments and development of markets are not that deterministic.</p><p>One escape route out of such a 'vicious circle' is to develop a technology and its market stepwise. The development of photovoltaic cells may illustrate this stepwise approach.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>00103461</head><p>Long-term electricity demand in China -from quantitative to qualitative growth? von Hirschhausen, C. and Andres, M. Energy I'olicy. 2000, 28, (4), 231-241. This paper develops scenarios of electricity demand in China until 2010, at a national, a sectoral and a regional level. It takes into account the recent macroeconomic downturn in the Chinese economy and the potential effects of deregulation and price increases in the power sector. The mediumgrowth scenario hints at a gross electricity demand of 1500 TWh in 2010; should the structural change from agriculture and heavy industry towards light industry and services accelerate, electricity demand may he another 10% lower. These figures are significantly below the projections fixed in the government's ninth 5-year plan, which forecasts a demand of 2500 TWh. The aggregate and sectoral scenarios imply that current development plans for generating capacity and coal consumption until 2010, too, need to he scaled down. The disaggregation at the level of the 13 inter-provincial and provincial power grids hints at potential regional discrepancies: the large industrial areas in eastern China and the Central region are likely to face overcapacity,</p><p>whereas North China and the peripheral regions may face deficits.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>00103462</head><p>Reform of China's electric power industry. Challenges facing the government <ref type="bibr">Andrews-Speed, P. and Dow, S. Energy Polic,v, 2000, 28, (5)</ref>  the industry in such a way that fair competition may he introduced, at least in power generation, and at establishing a viable regulatory agency. Both tasks have the potential to he thwarted by a range of vested interests at different levels of government and industry.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>00103463</head><p>Reliability economies of scale for tropical island electric power Mayer, P. C. Energy Economics, 2000, 22, (3), 319-330. Island electric power systems have special reliability problems since island systems, in an emergency, are unable to tap power from a continental transmission grid. Analysis of a survey shows the effect of scale on a reliability criterion chosen by operators of tropical island power systems and the scale impact of historical decisions, Discussed are the implications for islands of the energy crises of the 1970s and of other unexpected changes in electric power use. Also considered is the impact on islands of new technological choices.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>00103464</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Strategic pricing of grid access under partial pricecaps -electricity distribution in England and Wales</head><p>Riechmann, C. Energy Economics, <ref type="bibr">2000, 22, l(2)</ref>. 187-207. It is perceived in public debate that monopolistic network operators (who are vertically integrated into competitively organized activities) would raise excessive access charges and derail competition by newcomers. Economic reasoning, however, suggests that the level of access charges is-at least in a stmple setting -irrelevant for the intensity of entry by newcomers. In a setting where access charges are price-cap regulated, theoretical considerations and empirical findings for the case of electricity distribution in England and Wales even suggest that inefficiently high access charges correspond with intense market entry. Efficiency concerns remain, nonetheless, If regulated by a practicable partial price-cap, the network operator may enforce monopolistic access charges in certain market segments. Access charges in other segments may he lowered strategically and may even he cross-subsidized.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>00103465</head><p>Urgent-response services for a fast-paced industry Douglas, J. <ref type="bibr">EPRI Journal, 2000, 25. (I)</ref>, 26-31. Recent power outages in major urban areas have highlighted the industry's growing need for quick technical responses to husiness-critical problems. Reductions of in-house engineering staffs have made such problems even more difficult to deal with in an emergency time frame, and many utilities are relying more heavily on outside expertise to provide timely solutions. Anticipating this need, EPRI has reconfigured some of its most valuable analysis and troubleshooting capabilities to mobilize urgent-response services for the industry. Much of this assistance will he provided by EPRI's specialized technology centres located throughout the country and hy EPRI-solutions -a new service-oriented subsidiary.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>00103466</head><p>Use of stainless steel for cost competitive bipolar plates in the SPFC Makkus, R. C. et crl. Jorrrnrrl o/' Power Svtrr~cs. 2000. 86, (l-2). 274-282.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Fuel and Energy Abstracts</head><p>November 2000 389</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>State Power Company and the abolition of the Ministry of Electric Power are important first steps on the path of reform, hut it seems that a clear plan is lacking. Objectives of the reform should include increasing the capacity to deliver power, constraimng the costs of the power</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">335-347.</cell></row><row><cell>China's electrical</cell><cell cols="2">power industry</cell><cell>requires</cell><cell>substantial</cell><cell>reform</cell><cell>if the</cell></row><row><cell cols="7">country's economic growth is to he sustained. The 1997 Electricity Law,</cell></row><row><cell>the creation of a industry, increasing</cell><cell>end-user</cell><cell cols="3">efficiency and minimizing</cell><cell cols="2">environmental</cell></row><row><cell cols="5">damage, Efforts should he directed at restructuring</cell><cell></cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
