<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /Users/grace/grobid-0.6.1/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">An assessment of the Sr/Ca ratio in shallow water hermatypic corals as a proxy for sea surface temperature</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">John</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Marshall</surname></persName>
							<email>john.marshall@anu.edu.au</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Research School of Earth Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Australian National University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>ACT 0200</postCode>
									<settlement>Canberra</settlement>
									<country key="AU">Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Research School of Earth Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Australian National University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>ACT 0200</postCode>
									<settlement>Canberra</settlement>
									<country key="AU">Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Malcolm</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Mcculloch</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Research School of Earth Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Australian National University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>ACT 0200</postCode>
									<settlement>Canberra</settlement>
									<country key="AU">Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Research School of Earth Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Australian National University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>ACT 0200</postCode>
									<settlement>Canberra</settlement>
									<country key="AU">Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">An assessment of the Sr/Ca ratio in shallow water hermatypic corals as a proxy for sea surface temperature</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<note type="submission">Received March 20, 2001; accepted in revised form April 8, 2002</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.1" ident="GROBID" when="2021-09-14T02:17+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>The high precision measurement of the Sr/Ca ratio in corals has the potential for measuring past sea surface temperatures at very high accuracy. However, the veracity of the technique has been questioned on the basis that there is both a spatial and temporal variation in the Sr/Ca ratio of seawater, and that kinetic effects, such as the calcification rate, can affect the Sr/Ca ratio of corals, and produce inaccuracies of the order of 2-4°C. In the present study, a number of cores of the massive hermatypic scleractinian coral Porites, from the central Great Barrier Reef, have been analyzed for Sr/Ca at weekly to monthly resolution. Results from a 24 year record from Myrmidon Reef show an overall variation from 22.7°C to 30.4°C. The record shows a warming/cooling trend with maximum warming centred on the 1986-1987 summer. While some bleaching was reported to have occurred at Myrmidon Reef in 1982, the Sr/Ca record indicates that subsequent summer temperatures were much higher. The 4.5 year record from Stanley Reef shows a maximum SST of 30°C during the 1997-1998 El Niño event. The calibrations from Myrmidon and Stanley Reefs are in excellent agreement with previously published calibrations from nearby reefs. While corals do not calcify in equilibrium with seawater due to physiological control on the uptake of Sr and Ca into the lattice of coralline aragonite, it can be argued that, provided only a single genus such as Porites sp. is used, and that the coral is sampled along a major vertical growth axis, then the Sr/Ca ratio should vary uniformly with temperature. Similarly, objections based on the spatial and temporal variability of the Sr/Ca activity ratio of seawater can be countered on the basis that in most areas where coral reefs grow there is a uniformity in the Sr/Ca activity ratio, and there does not appear to be a change in this ratio over the growth period of the coral. Evidence from several corals in this study suggest that stress can be a major cause of the breakdown in the Sr/Ca-SST relationship. Thermal stress, resulting from either extremely warm or cool temperatures, can produce anomalously low Sr/Ca derived SSTs as a result of the breakdown of the biological control on Sr/Ca fractionation. It is considered that other stresses, such as increased nutrients and changes in light intensity, can also lead to a breakdown in the Sr/Ca-SST relationship. Two of the main issues affecting the reliability of the Sr/Ca method are the calibration of the Sr/Ca ratio with measured SST and the estimation of tropical last glacial maximum (LGM) palaeotemperatures. Instead of producing a constant calibration, just about every one published so far is different from the others. What is obvious is that for most calibrations while the slope of the calibration equation is similar, the intercepts are not. While the cause for this variation is still unknown, it would appear that corals from different localities around the world are responding to their own particular environment or that certain types of environments exert a control on the corals&apos; physiology. Sr/Ca derived SST estimates for the LGM and deglaciation of 5°C-6°C cooler than present are at odds with estimates of 2°C-3°C cooling by other climate proxies. The apparent lack of reef growth during the LGM suggests that SSTs were too cold in many parts of the tropics for reefs to develop. This would lend support to the idea that tropical SSTs were much cooler than what the CLIMAP data suggests.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Stoichiometric trace element ratios within the aragonite skeleton of hermatypic corals are known to have temperature dependent seawater/coral partition coefficients that can provide a proxy for sea surface temperature (SST). Elemental ratios that have some temperature dependent correlation are known to include B/Ca <ref type="bibr" target="#b57">(Sinclair et al., 1998;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Fallon et al., 1999)</ref>, Mg/Ca <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">(Mitsuguchi et al., 1996)</ref>, Sr/Ca <ref type="bibr" target="#b58">(Smith et al., 1979;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Beck et al., 1992)</ref>, and U/Ca <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">(Min et al., 1995;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b54">Shen and Dunbar, 1995)</ref>. One of the most promising SST proxies has been the high precision measurement of the Sr/Ca ratio in coral skeletons using a combination of isotope dilution (ID) and thermal ionization mass spectrometry (TIMS) <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(Beck et al., 1992)</ref>, and more recently inductively coupled plasma-atomic emission spectroscopy (ICP-AES) <ref type="bibr" target="#b55">(Schrag, 1999)</ref>.</p><p>Sea surface temperature is a crucial parameter because of its linkage with climate phenomena such as El Niño. Only in the past two decades has a sufficient volume of instrumental data been acquired to observe the onset and development of El Niño, but even now our understanding of what initiates it and how it propagates is rudimentary because of the variability inherent in this phenomenon <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(Cane et al., 1995)</ref>. In order to create better prediction models it is necessary to extend the El Niño record back by several centuries so as to assess the frequency and magnitude of key variables, such as SST. While the instrumental record is very sketchy at this time scale, massive corals, such as Porites sp., have the ability to live for up to 300 -500 years or more, and, because their growth rate is commonly of the order of 1-2 cm yr Ϫ1 , it is possible to retrieve high resolution (weekly to monthly) SST records by measuring their Sr/Ca ratio. Modern scleractinian corals not only have the capability of providing continuous climate data, but, by means of radiocarbon and U-series dating, their fossil counterparts can provide snapshots of climatic conditions for the last few hundred thousand years or so, and possibly longer.</p><p>Hermatypic scleractinian corals contain about 7500 Ϯ 500 ppm Sr, although because of vital effects there can be distinct differences between genera <ref type="bibr" target="#b63">(Weber, 1973)</ref>. Apart from these vital effects, the ratio of Sr to Ca in the coral is believed to be controlled predominantly by two factors: (i) the Sr/Ca activity ratio of seawater; (ii) the Sr/Ca distribution coefficient between aragonite and seawater <ref type="bibr" target="#b58">(Smith et al., 1979;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Beck et al., 1992)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.1.">The Sr/Ca Activity Ratio of Seawater</head><p>Because of the long residence times of Sr and Ca in the oceans [5.1 ϫ 10 6 yr for Sr and 1.1 ϫ 10 6 yr for Ca <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Broecker and Peng, 1982)</ref>], it has generally been assumed that the Sr/Ca activity ratio has remained essentially constant over the past 100 000 years or so. This assumption has been brought into question recently as a result of model studies of Sr release from shelf carbonates during low sea level (glacial) events <ref type="bibr" target="#b59">(Stoll and Schrag, 1998)</ref>, and variations in foraminiferal Sr/Ca during late Quaternary glacial/interglacial cycles <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">(Martin et al., 1999;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b60">Stoll et al., 1999)</ref>. When Sr-rich aragonitic shallow marine sediments, such as corals and the green alga Halimeda, are exposed on the shelf during eustatic sea level lowering subaerial diagenesis of aragonite to low-Mg calcite by meteoric water occurs, resulting in the release of strontium. It has been proposed by <ref type="bibr" target="#b59">Stoll and Schrag (1998)</ref> that this may raise Sr/Ca seawater by to 2 percent. While this increase is small, it has the ability to produce a shift of 2°C-3°C in palaeotemperatures derived from coral Sr/Ca ratios. Measurements of the Sr/Ca ratio in planktonic and benthic foraminifera show variations of up to 12% over glacial/interglacial cycles <ref type="bibr" target="#b60">(Stoll et al., 1999)</ref>. While this variation is much greater than the model results of <ref type="bibr" target="#b59">Stoll and Schrag (1998)</ref>, a large part of it can be explained by selective dissolution of foraminiferal tests and other environmental effects such as temperature and pH <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">(Martin et al., 1999)</ref>. However, both <ref type="bibr" target="#b60">Stoll et al. (1999)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Martin et al. (1999)</ref> maintain that up to 3-5% can be attributed directly to Sr/Ca seawater variations.</p><p>From direct measurements of the Sr/Ca composition of seawater, it had earlier been noted that depletions of both elements of the order of 1-3% can occur in surface waters (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Brass and Turekian, 1974)</ref>. Much of this has been attributed to removal of Ca and Sr by surface dwelling organisms during skeletogenesis. Traditionally, the Sr/Ca value representative of the marine environment has been reported as 8.6 Ϯ 0.4 mmol mol Ϫ1 <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">(Kinsman, 1969)</ref>. Analyses of seawater samples by de <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Villiers et al. (1994)</ref> using ID-TIMS show significant variation in their Sr/Ca ratio (8.5-8.7 mmol mol Ϫ1 ). Additional Sr/Ca analysis of surface waters from the Atlantic and Pacific Oceans by de Villiers (1999) averaged 8.539 Ϯ 0.0045 mmol mol Ϫ1 , and it was suggested that surface waters are depleted by 2-3% relative to the deep ocean as a result of skeletal formation of celestite (SrSO 4 ) by acantharians (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Bernstein et al., 1987)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.2.">Temperature Dependence of the Sr/Ca Distribution Coefficient</head><p>The aragonitic skeletons of corals have a preference for Sr (0.65-1.1% by weight) rather than Mg (0.06 -0.43% by weight), whereas skeletons made of Mg calcite (such as coralline algae) typically have much higher Mg contents (3.4 -4.8% by weight). In general, aragonite will accommodate more Sr than calcite. The higher uptake of Sr into aragonite rather than calcite is a function of the higher distribution coefficient for the former <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Bathurst, 1976)</ref>. The distribution coefficient, D Sr A ϭ (Sr/Ca) aragonite /(Sr/Ca) seawater , for corals is considered to be close to unity <ref type="bibr" target="#b63">(Weber, 1973)</ref>, whereas for inorganically precipitated aragonite it is about 1.15 <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">(Kinsman and Holland, 1969)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>While D Sr</head><p>A for inorganically precipitated aragonite is strongly temperature dependent <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">(Kinsman and Holland, 1969)</ref>, earlier experiments regarding temperature dependence in corals were equivocal. Some workers (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b61">Thompson and Livingston, 1970;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b62">Thompson and Chow, 1955)</ref> found no correlation between temperature and Sr/Ca, whereas others (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Houck et al., 1977;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Kinsman, 1969;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b58">Smith et al., 1979)</ref> found that the Sr/Ca ratio varied as a simple function of temperature. In his comprehensive study of the incorporation of Sr into corals, <ref type="bibr" target="#b63">Weber (1973)</ref> found an inverse relationship between temperature and D Sr A , but considered growth rate and other "species effects" to be more important. Both field and laboratory studies carried out by <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Houck et al. (1977)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b58">Smith et al. (1979)</ref> further strengthened the case for temperature dependence. They maintained that there is a distinct linear relationship between the Sr/Ca ratio and the ambient water temperature at which the precipitation of skeletal aragonite occurs, which is basically independent of growth rate. They were also able to show that D Sr A for corals is significantly different from inorganically precipitated aragonite, and that D Sr A varies between different coral genera. This was attributed to some form of biological control, whereby the Sr/Ca ratio in the tissue of the coral is slightly modified from the seawater Sr/Ca ratio.</p><p>It was acknowledged by <ref type="bibr" target="#b58">Smith et al. (1979)</ref> that Sr/Ca ratios measured by such techniques as atomic absorption spectrophotometry (AAS) were hampered by a lack of precision. The errors associated with this method, when converted to temperature, were of the order of Ϯ2°C. As pointed out by <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Beck et al. (1992)</ref>, this is the same as the typical SST range observed in the tropics. It was not until the introduction of ID-TIMS <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(Beck et al., 1992)</ref> that it was possible to measure SSTs with an accuracy of better than Ϯ0.5°C.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.3.">Previous Work</head><p>In their original experiments <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Beck et al. (1992)</ref> measured the Sr/Ca ratio for the coral species Porites lobata from Noumea and Tahiti. The corals were sampled along the growth axis at roughly monthly intervals. Rather than calibrate the Sr/Ca directly against the in situ instrumental SST record, <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Beck et al. (1992)</ref> calibrated it against ␦ 18 O-derived SSTs from the same samples. Their relationship between Sr/Ca and SST of Sr/Ca ϫ 10 3 ϭ 10.72 Ϫ 0.0624 ϫ SST</p><p>is similar to the <ref type="bibr" target="#b58">Smith et al. (1979)</ref> calibration for Porites, but with greater precision. However, <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Beck (1994)</ref> later revised their original calibration [the revised calibration of Sr/Ca ϫ 10 3 ϭ 10.479 Ϫ 0.06245 ϫ SST is used hereafter for all references to <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Beck et al. (1992)</ref>], with the result that there was now a 4°C difference between the two. In their paper, <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Beck et al. (1992)</ref> show a good correlation between the instrumental SST records from Noumea and Papeete and the Sr/Ca-derived SSTs, with an average difference of 0.34°C between the two. While <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Beck et al. (1992)</ref> were able to show a good correlation between the Sr/Ca ratio and SST, a note of caution was introduced by de Villiers et al. <ref type="bibr">(1994)</ref>. They suggested that interspecific differences, variable calcification, and extension rates, and variability in the Sr/Ca composition of seawater could introduce significant errors (1-2°C) in the use of this method. In a subsequent paper <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(de Villiers et al., 1995)</ref>, the Sr/Ca-based proxy was further called into question on the basis of biological control of Sr/Ca uptake. They measured three specimens of Porites lobata from Hawaii; two of which were only 20 m apart and the Sr/Ca seawater showed no measurable difference. All three grew at the same rate of 12 mm yr Ϫ1 and SST records from both areas are substantially the same. Their results show three different trends in Sr/Ca, and consequently three distinctly different calibrations, with differences from the same reef as much as 2°C-3°C.</p><p>Evidence of biological control on the uptake of Sr/Ca has been refuted subsequently by several studies. In southern Taiwan, Sr/Ca measurements on Porites lobata and P. lutea by <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">Shen et al. (1996)</ref> showed that species differences and growth rate variations did not appear to affect the Sr/Ca-SST relationship. Similar conclusions were reached by <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Alibert and McCulloch (1997)</ref> for the central Great Barrier Reef, where they found that the relationship holds true for a large range of annual extension and calcification rates, but provided that sampling was conducted along the major growth axis. They found that sampling off axis introduced errors of 1°C-2°C because corallites from different growth periods were being sampled simultaneously, whereas this effect was negated by sampling along the major axis of growth. Such off axis sampling could account for the variable results of de <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Villiers et al. (1995)</ref>.</p><p>Another problem has been the lack of consistent calibration of the Sr/Ca ratio with SST. Ideally, the comparison between the coral Sr/Ca ratio and an in situ instrumental SST record for the same time period from the same reef is the best method, but, with a few exceptions, this has not proved feasible. The main reason is that few reefs in the world have recorded continuous SST measurements for any length of time. In only a few examples have the corals been calibrated against the in situ SST record (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Alibert and McCulloch, 1997;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Crowley et al., 1999)</ref>. However, even in this situation the calibrations can be nonuniform. <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Alibert and McCulloch (1997)</ref> derived separate calibrations for five Porites sp. from Davies Reef in the central Great Barrier Reef. While three corals (Davies 2, 8, 11) produced calibrations with an accuracy of Ϯ0.5°C, two others (Davies 3 &amp; A) showed errors of up to Ϯ1.5°C. This anomaly is further examined in the Discussion (see Sect. 5.5).</p><p>A major reason for testing the Sr/Ca thermometer on modern corals is to be able to accurately measure palaeotemperatures in ancient corals. The results of Sr/Ca-based palaeotemperature estimates of corals indicate that tropical SSTs during the LGM were some 5°C cooler than today <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(Guilderson et al., 1994)</ref>, with SSTs rising 5°C-6°C during the deglaciation phase between 8 -14 kyr <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(Beck et al., 1997;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Guilderson et al., 1994)</ref>. However, other proxy records, such as alkenones <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Bard et al., 1997)</ref> and stable isotope analysis of foraminifera from deep sea sediments <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(Curry and Oppo, 1997)</ref>, have produced palaeotemperatures for the LGM more in line with CLIMAP results, with maximum cooling of only 2°C-3°C <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(Crowley, 2000)</ref>.</p><p>While the veracity of the Sr/Ca ratio method has been confirmed from several sites, more work is still required to confirm it as a reliable proxy. In particular, Sr/Ca records from nearby reefs, the same reef, and even from the same coral head need to be examined in detail to demonstrate their reliability and accuracy. In order to produce an accurate SST record, there is a requirement for the coral record to be calibrated against a long term instrumental SST record. To date, very few studies have been able to measure Sr/Ca derived SSTs with in situ instrumental SST from the same reef. Many studies must rely on data from SST stations that are remote to the coral site (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">de Villiers et al., 1994)</ref>, and this is considered to be a significant uncertainty in deriving accurate Sr/Ca-SST relationships. The present study is designed to partly address some of the above requirements. A coral from Myrmidon Reef on the shelf edge of the central Great Barrier Reef <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">(Fig. 1</ref>) has been analyzed for Sr/Ca in order to compare it to a 9 year instrumental record from the same reef. This is one of the longest instrumental datasets on any reef so far that has also been analyzed for Sr/Ca. In addition, a three year Sr/Ca derived SST record from Stanley Reef, a mid-shelf reef about 130 km southeast of Myrmidon Reef <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">(Fig. 1)</ref>, has been produced. These two Sr/Caderived SST records are compared to others in the area, such as Davies Reef <ref type="bibr">McCulloch, 1997), Pandora Reef (McCulloch et al., 1994)</ref>, and Orpheus Island <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(Gagan et al., 1998</ref>) so as to determine if the Sr/Ca-SST calibrations from a single region are consistent. Using these results, and studies from elsewhere, we discuss the problems, both real and apparent, that have been raised regarding the reliability of the method.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">SAMPLES</head><p>Myrmidon Reef lies close to the edge of the continental shelf, approximately 150 km from the coast, and it is the outermost reef in this region ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref>). Because of its distance from the coast, it is not affected by mainland runoff, but it is subjected to periodic upwelling <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Andrews and Gentian, 1982)</ref>. The reef has been the focus on ongoing research by the Australian Institute of Marine Science (AIMS), and as part of this monitoring of reef processes an automatic weather station has been installed on the reef flat since late 1987. Sea surface temperature, measured at hourly intervals, has been one of the parameters measured almost continuously at this site. The largest break in recording up until July 1996 had been 31 days in February 1992, and only three breaks had occurred previously that were longer than 10 days.</p><p>Two modern corals were cored with an underwater drill at Myrmidon Reef in July 1996. The drill unit uses compressed air from a scuba tank to drive a pneumatic drill attached to a 50 cm long barrel. With the use of extension rods, it is possible to recover a 48 mm diameter core of up to 1.5 m in length. These cores were all taken from large (Ͼ1 m) Porites sp. heads from a site near the entrance of a prominent gutter at the northeastern end of the reef. Core Myr-2 from a Porites lutea colony growing at a depth of 8 m was selected for detailed Sr/Ca analysis in this study.</p><p>Stanley Reef lies some 150 km south east of Myrmidon Reef and 70 km south east of Davies Reef, on the inner edge of the reef tract <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">(Fig. 1)</ref>. The reef is one of the larger ones in the region, being some 15 km long and 10 km wide. It has a well developed reef front and windward reef flat, a large lagoon with numerous patch reefs, and a narrow leeward reef flat. Beyond the leeward margin there is a shallow submerged platform, with numerous patch reefs. Two large (Ͼ1.5 m), living Porites sp. heads from the shallow platform behind Stanley Reef, and another large head at Old Reef, directly to the south of Stanley Reef <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">(Fig. 1)</ref>, were drilled in January 1999. The top part of core St-1 drilled at a depth of 2.7 m was analyzed for Sr/Ca in this study.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">EXPERIMENT</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.">Coral Preparation</head><p>Prior to cutting the core in half, the tissue zone at the top of each core is immersed in 50% v/v H 2 O 2 for 24 -36 hours to oxidize any organic material. The cores are cut either by hand, using a conventional rock saw or bandsaw or, more commonly, a purpose-built cutting device consisting of a diamond blade mounted on a precision lathe. In the latter case, the coral core is mounted onto the bed of the lathe, and the center of the core is aligned with the blade. The lathe-mounted coral is automatically moved at slow speed into the blade to give an even, smooth cut. Each coral core is cut in half lengthwise, and one or several 8 mm thick slices are cut from one half. After the slice(s) is cut, it is cleaned in 18 M⍀ water in an ultrasonic bath for 30 minutes to remove any fine coral powder produced during cutting. The slice is then either air dried or dried in an oven at 25°C for 24 hours.</p><p>Each slice is examined under ultraviolet (UV) light to determine if there is any fluorescence. Either prior to or after UV light examination, the slice is x-rayed to produce an image of the density variation in the coral <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">(Fig. 2</ref>). X-radiography was carried out at public hospitals or private imaging clinics in Canberra. The coral slice is simply placed horizontally on a single sided emulsion film and exposed for 0.1 seconds at 40 mA and 42 kV. The positive print of the x-ray is used to count density bands to give some idea of the age and growth rate, and to determine the direction of the major growth axis. The major growth axis is often at an angle to the core, and sometimes several growth axes must be selected, with overlapping growth bands, in order to effectively sample down the core. The core is then cut along this axis (or axes) with a bandsaw.</p><p>For sampling, the 8 mm thick coral slice is mounted on a perspex holder attached to the base of a computer-controlled moveable table such that the growth axis edge extends out from the holder by about 1 cm, with a clearance of about 5 mm beneath. Using a 20 mm diameter drill bit, a ledge is cut by thinning the exposed edge from 8 mm to about 2 mm. This is done automatically by moving the table at a speed of 0.5 mm s Ϫ1 beneath the rotating bit and sequentially shaving a series of 5 mm wide cuts on both sides, until the 8 mm thick slice has been reduced to 2 mm along the growth axis. The slice is cleaned thoroughly in an ultrasonic bath partly filled with 18 M⍀ water, changing the water frequently, until no cuttings from the mill are discernable. Particular attention is paid to thoroughly cleaning the ledge.</p><p>After drying, the coral slice is once more mounted on the computer-controlled milling table. The table can be programmed to mill sequential samples at either 0.25 or 0.50 mm intervals, using a 2 mm diameter drill bit rotating at slow speed (100 rpm). At each sample interval the table is moved automatically so that the ledge comes into contact with the bit and mills into the ledge for a distance of 2.5 mm. The powdered sample is allowed to fall onto a small square of weighing paper placed beneath the ledge. The sample is placed into a 1.5 ml polypropylene microcentrifuge tube and capped. The drill then makes a clearing cut of another 1 mm, before moving the set sampling interval distance to the next sample. This process is continued ad infinitum, until the length of coral desired has been fully sampled. The sampling interval is varied, depending on the growth rate of the coral, but a coral growing at 1.2 cm yr Ϫ1 , and sampled every 0.25 mm will produce 48 samples per year of coral growth or nearly weekly resolution.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.">Analytical Methods</head><p>For each Sr/Ca analysis, 80 -150 g of the milled powdered coral is weighed and transferred to an acid-cleaned 1.5 ml polypropylene microcentrifuge tube for wet chemical preparation. The sample is dissolved in 0.775 ml of 0.5N HCl, and a volume equivalent to 4 g Ca is pipetted into a clean 1 ml Teflon beaker containing 4 -5 drops of mixed Ca-Sr isotope spike and 1-2 drops of dilute phosphoric acid. After evaporation of the solution to a small phosphoric acid "bead," the sample is loaded without any further chemical separation onto an outgassed Ta filament, oxidized at dull red heat in air, and loaded into the mass spectrometer. The isotope dilution analysis is conducted automatically in static mode on a Finnigan MAT 261 mass spectrometer with 7 faraday cups, allowing Sr and Ca to be analyzed sequentially, without needing to adjust the cup settings.</p><p>Several spikes were used throughout the course of this study. The first 50 mm of the modern Myrmidon Reef coral (Myr-2) was analyzed with a 42 Ca-43 Ca-84 Sr mixed spike prepared from standard inventory items from the Oak Ridge National Laboratory, Tennessee after removal of 86 Sr from the 43 Ca using Sr spec. TM , a Sr-specific ion exchange EIChrom resin. Instrumental mass fractionation in the Ca analysis is corrected with reference to the 42 Ca-43 Ca double spike, and mass fractionation in the Sr analysis with reference to the natural 86 Sr/ 88 Sr of 0.1194, both using a power law. This is the same spike used by <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">McCulloch et al. (1994)</ref>; <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Alibert and McCulloch (1997)</ref>; and <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Gagan et al. (1998)</ref>. The remainder of Myr-2 and all of St-1 were analyzed using a 43 Ca-84 Sr mixed spike. This differs from the original in that Ca is omitted and the mass fractionation correction is made relative to natural 42 Ca/ 44 Ca ϭ 0.31221 <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">(Russell et al., 1978)</ref> using an exponential law. Measurements by <ref type="bibr" target="#b51">Nelson and McCulloch (1989)</ref> on the RSES MAT 261 yielded a very similar Ca isotope composition to <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">Russell et al. (1978)</ref>. Analytical precision is 2-3 times better with the 43 Ca-84 Sr spike, mainly because the mass fractionation correction is applied over two mass units, compared to a single mass unit for the original spike.</p><p>Before routine analysis began, each spike is calibrated for its isotope composition and concentration with respect to gravimetric standard solutions. The primary laboratory standard is MIX-3, prepared from Johnson &amp; Matthey Specpure CaCO 3 and NBS-987 SrCO 3 assay standard. The Sr/Ca ratio in MIX-3 is 0.01827, similar to that in a typical coral. An independently prepared standard MIX-4, similar to MIX-3, confirms calibrations using MIX-3 to within 0.1%. The spikes are directly loaded into the MAT 261 and their isotope compositions measured. Instrumental mass fractionation in these direct measurements is assessed by also measuring mixtures of the spikes and the MIX-3 gravimetric standard and back-calculating the endmember isotope compositions.</p><p>The spike concentrations are monitored at regular intervals by measuring the gravimetric standard solution and other laboratory standards prepared from certain corals. Dilutions of these into 30 or 60 ml polypropylene bottles are available in the laboratory for routine use. Throughout the present study a standard was usually measured during each mass spectrometer analytical session.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">RESULTS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1.">Core Myr-2</head><p>The top 175 mm of core Myr-2 was analyzed for Sr/Ca using ID-TIMS. X-radiography of this coral shows well-defined annual growth bands with a prominent major growth axis at a slight angle to the core <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">(Fig. 2)</ref>. The X-radiography indicates that this particular head of Porites lutea has a growth rate of 7.5-10.5 mm yr Ϫ1 , although most of the coral has an average rate of around 8.0 mm yr Ϫ1 . A ledge was cut along the prominent growth axis shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 2</ref>, and the coral was milled at 0.25 mm intervals. At the rate of growth indicated from the x-ray, it was considered that the resolution at this sampling interval would be better than fortnightly.</p><p>The results from some 300 individual Sr/Ca measurements are shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 3</ref>. The Sr/Ca values for the top 2.5 mm of the coral (roughly equivalent to the thickness of the tissue layer) show a lack of variation over that growth interval. It has been noted previously that Sr/Ca ratios in the vicinity of the tissue layer can produce anomalous results. In several corals from Davies Reef, <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Alibert and McCulloch (1997)</ref> report anomalous Sr/Ca ratios in the tissue layer, which they attributed to remnants of organic material within this zone. However, while they recorded high Sr/Ca ratios at the top, the Sr/Ca ratios from Myr-2 are uniformly low. The cores from both sites were sampled during the austral winter/spring, July at Myrmidon Reef and October at Davies Reef. At this time of year, it would be expected that the Sr/Ca ratio would be relatively high, so the low Sr/Ca ratios in the top 2.5 mm at Myrmidon Reef are somewhat difficult to explain. It could be that the Sr/Ca ratio of the organic material is highly variable, and capable of masking skeletal Sr/Ca.</p><p>Elsewhere, the Sr/Ca results display an extremely good and fairly regular cyclical pattern, that has been shown previously to be an annual SST signal (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Alibert and McCulloch, 1997)</ref>. From the number of analyses per cycle, it is obvious that the resolution of the sampling is of the order of monthly, although most data points are centered around the peaks and troughs of the curve, where the resolution is as high as fortnightly. While only two samples were repeated, the reproducibility is considered to be better than 0.25% (Ͻ 0.15°C). From the distance between Sr/Ca maxima, the annual extension rate is shown to vary between 5-11 mm yr Ϫ1 over a period of 21 years, with an average extension rate of 7.7 mm yr Ϫ1 . The highest annual extension rate occurs for the 3 years, between 75 and 105 mm <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">(Fig. 3)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1.1.">Calibration</head><p>In order to calibrate the Sr/Ca record against the instrumental SST, the maxima and minima of the measured SST were overlain and matched with the Sr/Ca ratio. The resulting plot is shown in <ref type="figure">Figure 4</ref>. Here, the Sr/Ca record for the first 60 mm is matched against the weekly instrumental SST for Myrmidon Reef for the period 1988 -1997. The fit is particularly good, with general matching of both the amplitude and wavelength of both data sets. The Sr/Ca plot shows a lower temperature response in the summer of 1994, which amounts to a variation of about 1°C. We can find no obvious reason for this discrep- ancy; several repeat analyses of the Sr/Ca ratios on this part of the coral produced similar results, and comparison of the in situ instrumental SSTs with satellite SSTs did not show any difference.</p><p>To derive the calibration equation, a Williamson regression, identical to that used by <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Alibert and McCulloch (1997)</ref>, was carried out for the time equivalent Sr/Ca ratio and instrumental SST. A total of 112 out of 122 data points were analyzed; those data points omitted were from the mismatch in 1994. For the regression analysis, the Sr/Ca error was set at 0.000005 (2) which is equivalent to Ͻ0.2°C, while the error on the instrumental SST is considered to be 0.1°C. From the total number of data points analyzed, a calibration equation of Sr/Ca ϫ 10 3 ϭ 10.40 (Ϯ0.016) Ϫ 0.0575 (Ϯ0.0005) ϫ T <ref type="formula">2</ref>was derived. This is very close to the calibration calculated for Davies Reef <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Alibert and McCulloch, 1997)</ref> of Sr/Ca ϫ 10 3 ϭ 10.48 (Ϯ0.01) Ϫ 0.0615 (Ϯ0.0004) ϫ T. (3)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1.2.">Myrmidon Reef climatology</head><p>Using Eqn. 2 to convert the Sr/Ca ratio to SST and tying it to a common chronology with the instrumental SST, we can see a distinct temperature pattern for the past 24 years at Myrmidon Reef <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">(Fig. 5</ref>). The total SST variation from 1973 to 1996 is from 22.7°C (winter of 1982) to 30.4°C <ref type="bibr">(summer of 1986 -1987)</ref>. The average summer SST maximum is 29.0°C, while the average winter minimum is 23.8°C <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">(Fig. 5)</ref>. The SST pattern shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. 5</ref> indicates a warming trend from 1973 to 1987, followed by a cooling trend from 1987 to 1994, and a possible warming trend in 1995-1996. Although the latter warming trend is not that apparent in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 5</ref>, the instrumental data shows that this warming trend continued into 1998. The earlier warming trend is reversed slightly in 1983-1984, with the cool El Niño winter of 1982 being repeated in 1983 and 1984, while the 1983-1984 summer is 1.2°C cooler than those immediately before and after ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. 5</ref>). Between 1973 and 1987 the summer maximum SST increased by 1.7°C, while the corresponding winter minimum SST increased by 1.8°C. This is somewhat greater than the 1.3°C warming recorded at Davies Reef for the same period <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Alibert and McCulloch, 1997)</ref>. Conversely, between 1987 and 1994 there is a 1.8°C and 2.4°C cooling in summer and winter, respectively <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">(Fig. 5)</ref>.</p><p>One of the major consequences of this warming/cooling cycle is that between 1982 and 1991 the maximum summer SST exceeded the average value on 9 out of 10 occasions <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">(Fig.  5</ref>). During this period, the maximum SST reached or exceeded 30°C on four occasions. According to <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Lough (1999)</ref> this temperature represents the threshold for coral bleaching in this region. In <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. 5</ref> the 30°C threshold is 1°C higher than the average summer maximum, a figure that is often used as a minimum condition for the onset of bleaching (Hoegh-Guldberg, 1999). On the basis of temperature alone, one would have expected bleaching of the more susceptible Acropora and Pocillopora species to have occurred definitely during the summer of <ref type="bibr">1986 -1987, probably in 1982-1983 and 1984 -1985, and possibly in 1987-1988, but not in 1981-1982</ref>. This is exactly the opposite of what happened, with no signs of bleaching at Myrmidon Reef during the 1986 -1987 summer <ref type="bibr">(Berkelmans, private communication, 2000)</ref>, and no reports of bleaching in <ref type="figure">Fig. 4</ref>. Best fit of Sr/Ca ratio for Myr-2 (black) with the instrumental SST (grey) for Myrmidon Reef.</p><p>Sr/Ca in corals as a proxy for sea surface temperature the other years except for 1981-1982 <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Berkelmans and Oliver, 1999)</ref>. One of the major factors that can affect SST in the GBR is the onset of an El Niño event. While the largest effect of the El Niño cycle is the variability in rainfall along the coastal region of Queensland, there does tend to be a typical SST signal associated with that phenomenon. According to <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Lough (1994)</ref>, there are two components to the SST signal associated with El Niño. One is the cooler than average SST for the winter prior to the onset of El Niño, and the other is the warmer than average SST during the following summer when the El Niño is fully active. It is considered that SSTs during La Niña years stay relatively warm during winter.</p><p>The major El Niño events during the period of growth of <ref type="bibr">Myr-2 occurred in 1976</ref><ref type="bibr">Myr-2 occurred in -1977</ref><ref type="bibr">Myr-2 occurred in , 1982</ref><ref type="bibr">Myr-2 occurred in -1983</ref><ref type="bibr">Myr-2 occurred in , 1986</ref><ref type="bibr">Myr-2 occurred in -1987</ref>, and there was a prolonged El Niño event between 1991 and 1994. As with other corals analyzed by the Sr/Ca TIMS method in the central Great Barrier <ref type="bibr">Reef [e.g., Pandora Reef (McCulloch et al., 1994)</ref> and Davies Reef <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Alibert and McCulloch, 1997)</ref>], there is a distinct cooling in the winter of 1982 at Myrmidon Reef associated with the intense El Niño event of 1982-1983 ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. 5)</ref>. At Myrmidon Reef the Sr/Ca derived SSTs show a drop of around 7°C at the end of summer in 1982, compared to the average summer-winter SST range of 5.5°C, followed by an even larger rise from the winter of 1982 to the late summer in 1983 <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">(Fig. 5)</ref>. However, apart from this extreme event there does not appear to be the precise SST signal, as outlined by <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Lough (1994)</ref>, for the other El Niño events. The 1976 -1977 event shows neither unusual cooling nor warming; in fact, it shows the coolest summer for the whole period of the coral record <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">(Fig. 5)</ref>. The 1986 -1987 event is almost the exact opposite to the 1976 -1977 event, with the warmest winter of the period followed by the warmest summer. The 1991-1992 event shows winter cooling, but only moderate summer warming ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. 5)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2.">Core St-1</head><p>The top 75 mm of this Porites sp. was analyzed for Sr/Ca using ID-TIMS to derive a calibration for a modern Stanley Reef coral in order to calculate SST values for a mid-Holocene coral from the same reef. X-radiographs of the coral show reasonably good annual banding, with the low density band accounting for about two-thirds of the annual width. The width of the density banding suggests that the growth rate of this coral is of the order of 15-18 mm yr Ϫ1 . Under fluorescent light, the coral shows only one thin bright band for the entire core. Judging from the position of the band and the growth rate of the coral, this appears to be the equivalent of the 1974 flood, which is the largest on record for the Queensland coast.</p><p>A ledge was cut along the most prominent growth axis, and the coral was milled at 0.25 mm intervals. At the rate of growth indicated from the x-ray, it was considered that the resolution at this sampling interval would be better than weekly. A total of 115 individual Sr/Ca measurements were carried out on this coral, producing a 4.5 year annual cycle, with estimated growth rates of 16.2 to 17.0 mm yr Ϫ1 . The frequency of Sr/Ca analyses is better than fortnightly. While every second sample, in general, was analyzed, consecutive samples were analyzed for the peaks and troughs.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2.1.">Calibration</head><p>The Sr/Ca record was matched against the instrumental SST from Davies Reef; the closest site with in situ temperature recording <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">(Fig. 1)</ref>. The instrumental data was reduced from daily to weekly to better match the Sr/Ca data. Because the station at Davies Reef did not record SST data between 3 October 1994 to 21 May 1996, it was only possible to match the two records from June 1996 to February 1999, with two small breaks of about one month during this period. This is about the same length of time against which the Davies 2 coral was calibrated <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Alibert and McCulloch, 1997)</ref>. The resulting fit <ref type="figure">(Fig. 6</ref>) is very good, and both large-scale and fine-scale detail can be seen to match in many parts of the curves. A least squares regression analysis was carried out for the time equivalent Sr/Ca ratio and instrumental SST, similar to that used for Myr-2, with a total of 66 data points being analyzed. The error limits used were the same as for the Myrmidon Reef calibration. From the total number of data points, a calibration equation of Sr/Ca ϫ 10 3 ϭ 10.40 (Ϯ0.018) Ϫ 0.0587 (Ϯ0.0005) ϫ T (4) was derived.</p><p>The calibrated SST plot is shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure 7</ref>. While summer SSTs reach 29°C in the previous 3 years, during the summer of the 1997-1998 El Niño, temperatures reach 30°C. It is noteworthy that during the 1997 winter, SSTs were only moderately low, and the typical El Niño signal of cool winter followed by warm summer as outlined by <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Lough (1994)</ref> is not as apparent as during the 1982-1983 event. Of some note is the 1°C drop in temperature at the beginning of 1998 <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">(Fig. 7)</ref>. A similar drop over much of the GBR is present in the instrumental data in early January of the same year, which Lough (1999) attributed to short-term cooling following the passage of a tropical low that produced extensive flooding on the central Queensland coast. This 1998 cooling event also appears in the Sr/Ca record of a coral from Pandora Reef.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3.">Comparison of Calibrations from the Central GBR</head><p>Including the results presented here for Myrmidon and Stanley Reefs, to date, six reefs in the central GBR off Townsville have provided Sr/Ca-SST records measured on cored Porites sp. at one or several sites on each reef. These include Pandora Reef <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">(McCulloch et al., 1994)</ref> and Orpheus Island <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(Gagan et al., 1998)</ref> on the inner shelf <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">(Fig. 1)</ref>, and Davies and Wheeler Reefs on the mid-shelf <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Alibert and McCulloch, 1997)</ref>. It is the intention here to compare the TIMS-derived Sr/Ca-SST calibrations for all these reefs; the SSTs for Wheeler Reef were derived using the Davies Reef calibration, and are not discussed further.</p><p>While the calibration for Davies Reef is that derived by <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Alibert and McCulloch (1997)</ref> from in situ instrumental data, the original paper on the Pandora Reef Sr/Ca record (i.e., <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">McCulloch et al., 1994)</ref> used the revised calibration of <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Beck et al. (1992)</ref> from New Caledonia and the Porites lobata calibration of de <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Villiers et al. (1994)</ref> from Hawaii. Although the summer SST values from these two calibrations are similar, they can diverge by more than 2°C in the winter. Recently, <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Alibert et al. (1999)</ref> calibrated a modern Porites sp. head collected at Pandora Reef in October 1998 against in situ SSTs measured at nearby Orpheus Reef. Their calibration of Sr/Ca ϫ 10 3 ϭ 10.3 (Ϯ0.01) Ϫ 0.0542 (Ϯ0.0005) ϫ T</p><p>is similar to the revised calibration of <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Beck et al. (1992)</ref>, but very different from that of <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">de Villiers et al. (1994)</ref>. It is also within the error limits of the Davies Reef <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Alibert and McCulloch, 1997)</ref> and the Myrmidon and Stanley Reef calibrations. Five separate Sr/Ca-SST calibrations have now been derived for the central GBR <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">(Fig. 8)</ref>. Two of these (Davies and Myrmidon Reefs) are based on in situ SST measurements, two (Pandora and Stanley Reefs) are based on in situ SST measurements from nearby reefs, and one (Orpheus Island) is based on satellite SST data. Four of the calibrations are within the error limits of each other, whereas one, that from Orpheus Island <ref type="figure">Fig. 6</ref>. Comparison between Sr/Ca data from Stanley Reef (black) and the instrumental data from nearby Davies Reef (grey). <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(Gagan et al., 1998)</ref>, shows a difference of some 3°C from the others <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">(Fig. 8)</ref>. Again, the reason for the difference is not obvious. Even though the Orpheus calibration used satellite SSTs, there are no significant errors between satellite data and in situ SSTs that are currently being acquired for all these sites. The calibration from Orpheus Island is also very similar to calibrations derived for Java and Dampier, Western Australia by <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Gagan et al. (1998)</ref>. Davies, Stanley and Myrmidon Reefs occur on the outer half of the shelf and do not appear to be affected by freshwater discharge from the coast, whereas inshore reefs, such as Orpheus and Pandora are enveloped, during periods of high rainfall, by the freshwater plume from the Burdekin River to the south of Townsville. Lowering of salinity on these inner reefs during these discharge events is evident from the ␦ 18 O signal of the corals <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(Gagan et al., 1998;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b47">McCulloch et al., 1994)</ref>. However, the Sr/Ca activity ratio for inshore seawater does not appear to be adversely affected on an annual basis (Chantal Alibert, private communication, 1997), presumably because the discharges are relatively short lived.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">DISCUSSION</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1.">Strontium Incorporation into Hermatypic Corals</head><p>As outlined in the Introduction, the incorporation of Sr into the lattice of coralline aragonite is believed to be controlled mainly by the Sr/Ca activity ratio of seawater and the Sr/Ca distribution coefficient between aragonite and seawater <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(Beck et al., 1992)</ref>. However, the mechanisms that control trace element incorporation into the coral skeleton remain imperfectly understood. Simple inorganic models predict that trace element partitioning is dependent upon the ionic composition of the calcifying fluid, the calcification rate, and the temperature <ref type="bibr" target="#b56">(Sinclair, 1999)</ref>. Of these three factors, the coral has the ability to control, at least partly, the first two. While corals partition most trace elements at close to inorganic values, they do not calcify in equilibrium with seawater. For strontium this disequilibrium is relatively minor (e.g., D Sr A Ϸ 1.06 for Porites sp. and Ϸ1.13 for inorganic aragonite), but it does indicate that physiology does play a significant role in its uptake.</p><p>If corals are not calcifying in equilibrium with seawater, then to be a reliable temperature proxy it has to be assumed that the amount of disequilibrium is constant, if not for all corals, then at least at the generic or species level. The range of distribution coefficients for all corals is relatively small. <ref type="bibr" target="#b63">Weber (1973)</ref> calculated an average D Sr A of 1.01 Ϯ 0.03 for 47 genera of shallow water hermatypic corals, whereas <ref type="bibr" target="#b58">Smith et al. (1979)</ref>, on a more limited range of corals, suggested a value of 1.06.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>For Porites sp. corals from Taiwan, D Sr</head><p>A averages 1.056 Ϯ 0.003 <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">(Shen et al., 1996)</ref>, while for the central GBR the value is 1.052 (S. Fallon, private communication). There also appears to be little difference in D Sr A for the more common species of Porites, in particular P. lobata and P. lutea <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">(Shen et al., 1996)</ref>. While the data is limited, it seems reasonable to assume that this disequilibrium is constant for the genus most commonly used for Sr/Ca derived SST records in the Indo-Pacific region.</p><p>Corals also exert a fair degree of physiological control over their calcification rates. It has long been established that calcification in zooxanthellate corals is faster during the day than at night (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Goreau, 1959)</ref>, and several hypotheses have been advanced to explain how zooxanthellae can affect calcification  <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">(Johnston, 1980;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b37">Krishnaveni et al., 1989)</ref>. It is thought that as part of their symbiosis the zooxanthellae produce low molecular weight organic molecules that are readily metabolized by the coral to generate energy and enhance calcification. The zooxanthellae may also help the coral by removing waste products, such as PO 4 3Ϫ , SO 4 2Ϫ , and NO 3</p><p>Ϫ <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(Goreau, 1959)</ref>, all of which can have an inhibiting effect on calcification. It has also been proposed that removal of CO 2 by photosynthesis may also aid the calcification process <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">(McConnaughey and Whelen, 1997)</ref> by maintaining a neutral pH in the calcifying fluid. On the other hand, <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Marshall (1996)</ref> has suggested that, rather than enhance day time calcification, zooxanthellae actually suppress night time calcification.</p><p>The most serious objections to date regarding the reliability of the Sr/Ca method with regard to calcification rate have been raised by <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">de Villiers et al. (1994</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">de Villiers et al. ( , 1995</ref>. Their results from a Pavona clavus coral from the Galapagos Islands indicated that a change of annual extension rate from 6 to 12 mm yr Ϫ1 produced an apparent offset in SST of 1°C-2°C, with higher Sr/Ca values associated with the slower extension rate. The conclusion from this experiment was that variable extension rates do affect the amount of Sr uptake by the coral. Similarly, <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Alibert and McCulloch (1997)</ref> conducted experiments where they measured Sr/Ca ratios along both the growth axis and off axis. They found that off axis, the lack of space and less optimal conditions for growth result in small corallites and lower skeletal density, which shifted the Sr/Ca ratios by a variable amount toward high values, corresponding to a temperature shift of Ϫ1°C to Ϫ3°C. Whether the apparent temperature offset is caused by a real change in the Sr/Ca ratio in these off axis situations or by an overlap of corallites that have grown at different times of the year is hard to discern. However, it seems that the only way to overcome this disparity is to sample exclusively along the major growth axis. Because they did not do so, as indicated in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 11</ref> of <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">de Villiers et al. (1994)</ref>, appears to invalidate the de <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Villiers et al. (1994</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Villiers et al. ( , 1995</ref> argument regarding calcification rate. As pointed out earlier, subsequent work by <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">Shen et al. (1996)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Alibert and McCulloch (1997)</ref> has shown a lack of change in Sr/Ca as a result of changes in calcification rate.</p><p>While there does appear to be an obvious physiological control on the uptake of Sr into the lattice of coralline aragonite, and that corals are not calcifying in equilibrium with seawater, the above arguments would suggest that, provided only a single genus such as Porites sp. is used and that the coral is sampled along a major vertical growth axis, the Sr/Ca ratio should vary uniformly with the remaining variable-temperature.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2.">The Constancy of the Sr/Ca Activity Ratio of Seawater</head><p>Both the spatial and temporal constancy of the Sr/Ca content of seawater is seen as a necessary requisite to the reliability of Sr/Ca in corals as a proxy for sea surface temperature the Sr/Ca technique as a proxy for both modern and palaeo SSTs. It has been pointed out previously that there is a spatial difference in Sr/Ca in modern seawater of 2-3% globally, with the deep ocean more enriched relative to the surface (de <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Villiers, 1999)</ref>. Although this variability is very small, it does equate to an uncertainty of 2°C-3°C for Sr/Ca derived SST measurements. However, the Sr/Ca proxy in corals necessitates that records can only be obtained in the tropics, in seawater that is normally oligotrophic and is not usually susceptible to constant or intense upwelling. In such waters the average Sr/ Ca seawater value is considered to be 8.5 Ϯ 0.1 mmol mol <ref type="bibr">Ϫ1 (de Villiers et al., 1994)</ref>, and reported Sr/Ca seawater measurements in coral reef areas only vary between 8.464 and 8.551 mmol mol Ϫ1 <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Alibert and McCulloch, 1997;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Beck et al., 1992;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b53">Shen et al., 1996)</ref>. If the somewhat higher values of <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">Shen et al. (1996)</ref> are ignored (this is a coastal site where the corals are growing in the water intake pond to a nuclear power plant), this converts to a temperature difference of 0.8°C. On a regional basis, the difference between Sr/Ca seawater for Davies and Myrmidon Reefs in the central GBR <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Alibert and McCulloch, 1997)</ref> equates to a temperature difference of 0.42°C. So while there are variations in Sr/Ca seawater that produce a temperature difference of 2°C-3°C on a global basis, in most coral reef areas the difference is much smaller, and is within the error limits of the ID-TIMS method.</p><p>Of greater consequence for the use of the Sr/Ca thermometer in palaeoceanographic research is the apparent 1-2% change in Sr/Ca seawater as a result of Sr release from shelf carbonates during low sea level events <ref type="bibr" target="#b59">(Stoll and Schrag, 1998)</ref>. This increase has the ability to produce a negative shift of 2°C-3°C, which would account for the extremely low tropical SSTs reported by the Sr/Ca method during the LGM and ensuing transgression <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(Beck et al., 1997;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Guilderson et al., 1994</ref>), compared to other methods (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Bard et al., 1997;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Crowley, 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Curry and Oppo, 1997)</ref> which indicate a relatively milder tropical cooling during the LGM.</p><p>While the <ref type="bibr" target="#b59">Stoll and Schrag (1998)</ref> model accounts for the loss of Sr from shelf carbonates during low sea levels, it fails to predict the long term cumulative effects of adding additional Sr to the ocean during repeated glacial cycles. In relation to the shelf carbonates, the amount of Sr that is added to the ocean during each glacial event is not matched by an equivalent input of Ca; the latter is immobilized as the stable polymorph of CaCO 3 , low-Mg calcite. Consequently, the removal of Ca from seawater during the ensuing interglacial, in the form of shelf aragonite deposits, will leave an excess of Sr in the ocean because the distribution coefficient (D Sr A ) for corals and Halimeda will maintain the removal of Sr and Ca at a constant rate, meaning that the excess Sr that was added to the ocean during the glacial will not be removed. Over successive glacial/interglacial events this would result in an incremental increase in the Sr/Ca activity ratio of seawater. This does not appear to be the situation, however, because reported Sr/Ca ratios for the last interglacial corals from areas such as the Huon Peninsula and Western Australia are similar to modern values <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">(McCulloch and Esat, 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b48">McCulloch et al., 1999)</ref>. This suggests that there is some other mechanism for removing the excess Sr during the deglaciation. One possibility is an increase in dissolution of deep-sea carbonate sediments at this time, adding excess Ca and lowering Sr/Ca seawater <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">(Hodell et al., 2001</ref>).</p><p>However, both the model results of <ref type="bibr" target="#b59">Stoll and Schrag (1998)</ref> and the foraminiferal Sr/Ca ratios <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">(Martin et al., 1999;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b60">Stoll et al., 1999)</ref> do indicate that Sr/Ca seawater can change by several percent during glacial/interglacial events. On this basis it can be argued that Sr/Ca derived SSTs for the LGM may be overestimated.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.3.">Corals Under Stress-Do they Obey the Rules?</head><p>Radiochemical studies <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">(Ip and Krishnaveni, 1991)</ref> have found that the incorporation of 90 Sr into the coral skeleton is linearly dependent on the Sr concentration and is not affected by inhibitors such as potassium cyanide (KCN), darkness or the photosynthetic inhibitor 3-(3,4-dichlorophenyl)-1,1-dimethylurea (DCMU), whereas the Ca concentration becomes quickly saturated and is inhibited by all of the above. This suggests that some or all Ca ions are transported through the coral tissue to the calcifying site by a different pathway than Sr ions <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">(Ip and Krishnaveni, 1991;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Ip and Lim, 1991)</ref>. Under normal conditions this would mean that the Sr/Ca ratio in the calcifying fluid would be lower than inorganic aragonite. However, <ref type="bibr" target="#b56">Sinclair (1999)</ref> has proposed that if temperature conditions become more extreme, the enzymes that transport Ca ions would become less efficient, resulting in a lowering of the active Ca 2ϩ transport and a decreasing calcification rate. Because Sr is not affected to the same degree, it would be possible for the Sr/Ca ratio to shift upwards towards inorganic values.</p><p>Sr/Ca derived SSTs for a coral from Pandora Reef in the central <ref type="bibr">GBR (McCulloch et al., 1994)</ref> show an extreme cooling of about 3.5°C during the El Niño winter of 1982 compared to other minimum temperatures during previous and subsequent years. However, in comparison to the Sr/Ca derived SSTs, ship and satellite data recorded a negative SST anomaly of only 2°C. At the time it was considered by <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">McCulloch et al. (1994)</ref> that the exceptionally cold temperatures of the 1982 winter led to a breakdown of the biological control on Sr/Ca fractionation, and the coral system moved more towards inorganic fractionation. While this conclusion has remained largely unsupported, new and more convincing evidence is provided for a shift in the Sr/Ca ratio, this time at high temperatures, from another coral from Pandora Reef <ref type="figure">(Fig. 9)</ref>. This Porites sp. was sampled soon after the 1998 bleaching event when 87% of the inshore reefs of the GBR were affected <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Berkelmans and Oliver, 1999</ref>). This particular coral shows that during 1997, Sr/Ca ratios declined steadily into the summer of 1997-1998 as the El Niño took effect. This trend was slightly reversed in early January 1998 when a tropical low entered the area, and depressed temperatures momentarily. Subsequently, the Sr/Ca ratio fell to a low of 8.62 mmol mol Ϫ1 as the SST rose to 30.5°C by early February, but had risen rapidly to 9.13 mmol mol Ϫ1 (equivalent to 21.6°C) by the beginning of March, after which no growth was recorded <ref type="figure">(Fig. 9)</ref>.</p><p>The Sr/Ca-temperature record indicates that this particular coral was subjected to temperatures of nearly 32°C, some 2°C higher than the normal bleaching threshold, and warm enough to affect even a more resistant coral such as Porites. The implication here is that once the coral becomes thermally stressed there is inhibition of the Ca transport enzyme (Ca 2ϩ ATPase) to some extent, whereas Sr continues to be transported into the calcifying fluid at the normal concentration. The Sr/Ca J.F. Marshall and M.T. McCulloch ratio does not appear to be affected until a particular temperature threshold is reached. However, once bleaching is underway, the coral rapidly records an increase in the Sr/Ca ratio as relatively less Ca is made available to the calcifying fluid. Within a month the system has completely broken down and the coral stops calcifying.</p><p>The control that physiology and/or environment may have over the differences in transport behavior of Ca and Sr mentioned above may also be affected by variables other than extreme temperatures. According to <ref type="bibr" target="#b56">Sinclair (1999)</ref>, "if Ca 2ϩ transport is energy dependent, but Sr 2ϩ transport is not, then anything that influences the energy budget of the coral will result in a change in the relative rates at which the two ions are transported to the calcifying fluid." This could include variations in such parameters as light intensity and nutrients. In a study of a coral from Christmas Island in the eastern Indian Ocean <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">(Marshall, 2000)</ref>, it was considered that either a decrease in light intensity (as a result of increased macroalgal production) and/or an increase in nutrients might have affected the Sr/Ca ratio because the coral was growing in the same location as a phosphate loading terminal. The stress generated by either could have been enough to affect the transport behavior of Sr and Ca, resulting in an upward shift in the Sr/Ca ratio and hence lower apparent SSTs. In contrast, several corals from nearby Cocos (Keeling) Atoll appear to have experienced stress that resulted in only partial breakdown in the transport behavior of Sr and Ca, although it is obvious that periodically the situation has been serious enough to bring about a complete halt to calcification <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">(Marshall, 2000)</ref>. The reports of fish kills and coral mortality, seen from time to time in the lagoon, appear to be a result of algal blooms <ref type="bibr" target="#b64">(Woodroffe and Berry, 1994)</ref>. The corals sampled at Cocos are all exposed to open water, so the stresses so evident in the lagoon might only be partially affecting them. However, it is quite clear that corals under stress do not obey the rules.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.4.">Differences in Sr/Ca-SST Calibrations and Potential Causes</head><p>One of the most contentious issues of using the Sr/Ca ratio in corals as a proxy for SST has been the calibration of the Sr/Ca ratio with measured SST. If the Sr/Ca ratio of seawater and the Sr/Ca distribution coefficient between aragonite and seawater are sufficiently constant to be within the error limits of the TIMS method, then it could reasonably be expected that one calibration would suffice for all Porites sp. Unfortunately, just about every study of the Sr/Ca proxy for modern corals published so far using TIMS has produced a different calibration <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">(Fig. 10)</ref>. The spread in the calibrations equates to temperature differences of up to 4°C to 6°C for the normal range of Sr/Ca ratios.</p><p>What is apparent in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 10</ref>, and the list of calibrations shown in <ref type="table">Table 1</ref>, is that, with several exceptions, the slope of the calibration equation is similar, whereas the intercepts are not. This not only applies to TIMS-derived calibrations, but to others that have used techniques such as ICP-MS, ICP-AES, and HR-ICP-MS by solution, and LA-ICP-MS [e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Crowley et al. (1999)</ref>; <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Fallon et al. (1999);</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b55">Schrag, (1999)</ref>; <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Correge et al. (2000)</ref>]. On this basis, it can be argued that calibrations by de <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Villiers et al. (1994)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">Shen et al. (1996)</ref> are incorrect because their slope is either higher or lower than the rest <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">(Fig.  10)</ref>.</p><p>Some of the calibrations shown in <ref type="table">Table 1</ref> can be dismissed as not being precise enough, either with respect to the Sr/Ca <ref type="figure">Fig. 9</ref>. Plot of Pandora Reef Sr/Ca ratio (black) against instrumental SST record from nearby Orpheus Island (grey) for the period July 1996 to November 1998 showing the effects of bleaching on the Sr/Ca ratio in February/March 1998. measurement or the instrumental SST. For instance, the calibration of <ref type="bibr" target="#b58">Smith et al. (1979)</ref> can be discarded on the basis of imprecise Sr/Ca measurements because they used AAS, with errors of the order of 10 times that of TIMS. The precision of some of the ICP instruments are quoted to be as low as Ϯ0.05% (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b55">Schrag, 1999)</ref>, compared to Ϯ0.1% for ID-TIMS, and others quote ϽϮ0.3% (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Crowley et al., 1999)</ref>. Typically, LA-ICP-MS precision for Sr/Ca is Ϯ1.5% (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Fallon et al., 1999)</ref>, which equates to a temperature of Ϯ1.2°C.</p><p>The normal procedure for converting the Sr/Ca ratio to temperature has been to match the former with some form of temperature measurement, whether it be in situ instrumental SST, blended ship and satellite SST, or even another temperature proxy [e.g., ␦ 18 O <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(Beck et al., 1992)</ref>]. Of the 15 calibrations shown in <ref type="table">Table 1</ref>, only five are actually based on in situ SST measurements at the actual site itself (i.e., Amedee Lighthouse, New Caledonia and Davies and Myrmidon Reefs, central GBR). The Sr/Ca ratios of de <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Villiers et al. (1994)</ref> were calibrated against an SST station more than 100 km distant. The calibrations of <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Heiss et al. (1997)</ref>; <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Gagan et al. (1998)</ref> and Christmas Island <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">(Marshall and McCulloch, 2001</ref>) were derived from blended ship and satellite data. While this may not be as accurate as in situ measurements on the reefs, it does seem to have some veracity. However, the 1°ϫ 1°spatial smoothing does mean that relatively small scale, but significant anomalies, such as related to upwelling as seen at Christmas Island or narrow boundary currents as at Myrmidon Reef, are seldom measured with sufficient accuracy. Notwithstanding these problems, <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Gagan et al. (1998)</ref> were able to derive calibrations from three widely spaced sites that were in very good agreement with each other. One potential method of checking a calibration is to plot the slope of the calibration equation against the intercept. (This idea, communicated to us by both Dan Schrag and Tom Guilderson, is attributed to Harry Elderfield). <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 11</ref> shows a plot of the 15 calibrations listed in <ref type="table">Table 1</ref> together with the seawater value. A linear best fit of the data shows most calibrations lying along the line or within the error limits of the calibration, with only two of the calibrations, that of <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">de Villiers et al. (1994)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b55">Schrag (1999)</ref>, offset. The reason for this linear spread in the calibrations, and its tie-in with the seawater value is not immediately clear. The implication is that corals from different localities around the world are responding to their own particular environment or that certain types of environment exert a control on the corals' physiology.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.5.">Does Coral Size (Age) Matter?</head><p>It was mentioned previously that separate calibrations were derived for five Porites sp. from Davies Reef <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Alibert and McCulloch, 1997)</ref>, and that within the error limits three corals (Davies 2, 8, 11) produced similar calibrations (Ϯ0.5°C), whereas two others (Davies 3 and Davies A) showed errors of up to Ϯ1.5°C. In fact, there is a greater spread in the calibrations for the five Davies Reef corals than there is for the combined calibrations for Davies, Pandora, Stanley, and Myrmidon Reefs <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">(Fig. 8)</ref>. At Davies Reef both Davies 3 and Davies A are small heads. A similar situation is apparent for Holocene corals from Myrmidon and Stanley Reefs <ref type="bibr">(Marshall et al., 2002 submitted)</ref>. These produce results that are not in agreement with each other, indicating that the calibration derived from the modern coral is not appropriate to some (or all?) of them. From the core logs it is obvious that these are small heads, probably no longer than 20 cm. The suggestion here is that younger corals produce calibrations that are less reliable than larger, older heads, but why?</p><p>At this stage there is no obvious reason, but some insight might be derived from stable isotopes. In a study by <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Gagan et al. (1996)</ref> on supposed enrichment of 13 C during spawning events, the small, 15 year old head of Porites lobata from Ningaloo Reef shows no annual ␦ 13 C variation for some 6 years, and, when it does so, it is out of phase with the ␦ 18 O signal. This contrasts with the top of the larger, 300 year old colony from Pandora Reef, where both the ␦ 13 C and ␦ 18 O produce an in phase annual signal. The inference here is that immature or juvenile coral heads are somehow physiologically different from their more mature counterparts, and this is reflected in their intake of trace elements and isotopes. While this is highly conjectural at this stage, it needs to be confirmed by measuring both stable isotopes and Sr/Ca ratios on a suite of small and large heads which have grown preferably side by side. The reason for suspecting the size (age) of the Porites sp. is that, while in many papers the size of the coral is not mentioned, there is a distinct suspicion that the heads are small and were collected by hand rather than by drilling. In most cases only 1 to 6 years of growth is analyzed. It is significant that of the most seminal and/or critical papers on the Sr/Ca method (i.e., <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Beck et al., 1992;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">de Villiers et al., 1994</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">de Villiers et al., , 1995</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b47">McCulloch et al., 1994;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b53">Shen et al., 1996)</ref>, only one <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Alibert and McCulloch, 1997)</ref> refers to the size of the coral heads, although the coral from Pandora Reef measured by <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">McCulloch et al. (1994)</ref> is the same 300 year old head measured by <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Gagan et al. (1996)</ref>. From this it can be surmized that the lack of agreement for some calibrations <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">(Fig. 10)</ref>, compared say to the excellent agreement for the central GBR <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">(Fig. 8)</ref>, where only large heads (Ͼ25 years) were cored, is due to the size of the coral. Again, this concept awaits to be tested.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.6.">The Sr/Ca Ratio in Corals as an Accurate Palaeothermometer</head><p>While the calibration issue can be seen as a major drawback to the use of the Sr/Ca ratio in corals as a proxy for SST, it has been the estimation of palaeotemperatures using the Sr/Ca method that has perhaps engendered most discussion from palaeoceanographers. In particular, it has been the estimation of palaeo SSTs for the LGM and deglaciation that has raised the most controversy. As discussed earlier, Sr/Ca-based palaeotemperature estimates of corals indicate that tropical SSTs in the Atlantic Ocean during the LGM were some 5°C-6°C cooler than today <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(Guilderson et al., 1994)</ref>, and that SSTs rose some 6°C during the deglaciation phase between 8 -14 kyr in the south western Pacific Ocean <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(Beck et al., 1997;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Gagan et al., 2000)</ref>. These results are at odds with a variety of palaeoceanographic techniques.</p><p>In a recent paper, <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Crowley (2000)</ref> argues that a decrease in SST in the tropics of Ϫ5°C during the LGM would indicate that climate sensitivity is relatively high; in which case a doubling of CO 2 in the atmosphere by the next century would lead to a temperature increase of the order of 4.5°C. While <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Crowley (2000)</ref> takes to task other cool SST estimates for the LGM, such as those based on tropical snowlines and groundwater estimates, he refutes coral palaeotemperature-based estimates on the grounds that the calibrations should be derived from a regional gridded field, and must be validated against early 20th century instrumental records. While these may be seen as relatively minor issues compared to those mentioned above, it only applies to ␦ 18 O/SST calibrations and not necessarily to Sr/Ca-based SST estimates <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(Crowley et al., 1999)</ref>. With regard to trace element incorporation into corals, <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Crowley (2000)</ref> maintains that if the SST was some 5°C cooler, then corals during the LGM would be living under stressed conditions. As seen in the earlier part of the discussion, stress, particularly in the form of high and low SSTs, does result in an increase in the Sr/Ca ratio that can produce anomalously cooler temperatures.</p><p>On the other hand, if SSTs were cooler by 5°C, all but a few of the present-day coral reefs of the world would not survive. <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Crowley (2000;</ref><ref type="bibr">Fig. 5</ref>) attempted to show this, suggesting that for 95% of present-day coral reef sites it would be too cold. While he was trying to show that corals could not exist at</p><p>Ϫ5°C lower than present, but could at Ϫ2.5°C, there is, indeed, very little evidence to suggest that coral reefs did develop during the LGM. The only site documented in any detail is Barbados <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(Fairbanks, 1989)</ref>. One has to take into account that sea level was some 120 m lower than present, meaning that many LGM coral reefs would have had to establish themselves on the steep slopes of atolls or on the upper continental slope. While other factors, such as lack of substrate, increased sedimentation, etc., may have been deleterious to reef growth, it would be expected that LGM reefs would have grown in most parts of the tropics if SSTs dropped only by 2°C -3°C. This does not appear to be the case. Other areas where late Pleistocene/early Holocene (ca. 10 000 year old) reefs have been drilled, such as New Guinea and Vanuatu, would also be able to support reef growth at Ϫ5°C, according to <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Crowley's (2000;</ref><ref type="bibr">Fig. 5</ref>) estimation. It is ironic that here too the Sr/Ca SST estimate is also Ϫ5°C cooler than present.</p><p>So while there are pertinent arguments to suggest that Sr/Ca derived SSTs for LGM corals are overestimated because of changes to the Sr/Ca ratio of seawater or as a result of thermal stress, the almost total lack of coral reefs, except for a few areas in the tropics, indicates that it was too cold for them to develop during the LGM. In other words, by turning <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Crowley's (2000)</ref> argument around, if SSTs in the tropics were Ϫ5°C relative to present, then only 5% of coral reefs would survive. This does appear to have been the situation during the LGM.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.">CONCLUSIONS</head><p>Although the precise determination of the Sr/Ca ratio in corals provides a potent tool for measuring SSTs in both modern and fossil corals, serious doubts have been raised as to its reliability. Much of this stems from the fact that corals are not calcifying in equilibrium with seawater. While corals do not calcify exactly in equilibrium with seawater, their distribution coefficient is sufficiently close, and this disequilibrium appears to be constant at the generic level. It has also been established that corals, through their symbiotic zooxanthellae, can exert a fair degree of physiological control over their calcification rate. While some objection has been raised regarding the reliability of the Sr/Ca method with regard to calcification rate (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">de Villiers et al., 1994</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">de Villiers et al., , 1995</ref>, much of this can be discarded due to poor sampling techniques. Notwithstanding the obvious physiological control on the uptake of Sr into the lattice of coralline aragonite, it is suggested that, provided only a single genus or species is used, and that sampling occurs along a major vertical growth axis, then the Sr/Ca ratio should vary uniformly with temperature. The fact that most of the world's coral reefs occur in low productivity areas would appear to reduce the variability of Sr/Ca seawater to less than Ϯ0.4°C; well within the error limits of ID-TIMS or ICP-AES. At the temporal level, the modelled loss of Sr from shelf carbonates during low sea levels fails to predict the long term effects of adding additional Sr to the ocean during every glacial event. This would lead to an increase in Sr/Ca seawater over successive glacial periods, but last interglacial corals show no such increase, suggesting that other mechanisms, such as carbonate dissolution during each deglaciation, may be important in maintaining relatively constant Sr/Ca ratios.</p><p>Evidence from several corals in this study suggests that J.F. Marshall and M.T. McCulloch stress may be a major cause in the breakdown in the Sr/Ca-SST relationship. Thermal stress, resulting from either extremely warm or cool temperatures, is considered to lead to a reduction in Ca 2ϩ transport to the calcifying fluid, whereas Sr does not appear to be similarly affected, and an upward shift in the Sr/Ca ratio occurs. Evidence from Pandora Reef in the central GBR shows that both excess (bleaching) and extremely cool (Ͻ18°C) temperatures produce anomalously low Sr/Ca derived SSTs as a result of this breakdown of the biological control on Sr/Ca fractionation. It is considered that other stresses, such as increased nutrients and changes in light intensity, can also lead to a breakdown in the Sr/Ca-SST relationship.</p><p>This study suggests that while some of the previously published calibrations can be dismissed on the basis of inaccuracies in the Sr/Ca and SST measurements, there still appears to be sufficient evidence to suggest that the Sr/Ca-SST calibration is not constant. While many calibrations appear to be based on measurements from small (young) coral heads, the central GBR calibrations are based on cores of large (old) heads, and these seem to give the most reliable results. The fact that tropical LGM palaeotemperature estimates using the Sr/Ca method are 2°C-3°C cooler than other climate proxies is a cause for serious concern. However, it is argued here that the overall lack of evidence for reef growth during the LGM suggests that SSTs were too cold in most parts of the tropics for reefs to develop. This would lend support to the idea that tropical SSTs were much cooler than that proposed by CLIMAP data. Those arguments which suggests that Sr/Ca derived SSTs for LGM corals are overestimated because of changes to the Sr/Ca ratio of seawater or as a result of thermal stress need to be evaluated in more detail.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Map of the central GBR off Townsville showing the location of Myrmidon and Stanley Reefs, plus other reefs in the region where Sr/Ca results have been published.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>A positive print of an X-radiograph of the Porites lutea coral Myr-2. The coral was sampled along the major growth axis, shown as A-B in the figure.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Plot of Sr/Ca vs distance for the top of the Porites lutea core Myr-2. J.F. Marshall and M.T. McCulloch</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig. 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Plot of the Myrmidon Reef Sr/Ca derived SST (°C) against time for the period 1973-1996. J.F. Marshall and M.T. McCulloch</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig. 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Plot of Sr/Ca derived SSTs from 1994 to 1999 for Stanley Reef showing the warm El Niño summer of 1997-1998 and the 1°C drop in temperature in January 1998. J.F. Marshall and M.T. McCulloch</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Fig. 8 .</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Sr/Ca vs SST calibrations derived from the central GBR.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Fig. 10 .</head><label>10</label><figDesc>Plot of previously published calibrations showing their lack of uniformity. Table 1. List of published and unpublished Sr/Ca-SST calibrations. AAS, atomic absorption spectrophotometry. ID-TIMS, isotope dilution thermal ionisation mass spectrometry. HR-ICP-MS, high-resolution inductively coupled plasma mass spectrometry. LA-ICP-MS, laser ablation inductively coupled plasma mass spectrometry. ICP-AES, inductively coupled plasma atomic emission spectrophotometry. ICP-MS, inductively coupled plasma mass spectrometryϫ 10 3 ϭ 10.30 Ϫ 0.0542 ϫ SST Alibert et al. (1999) ID-TIMS 9 Sr/Ca ϫ 10 3 ϭ 10.375 Ϫ 0.0593 ϫ SST Marshall and McCulloch (2001) ID-TIMS 10 Sr/Ca ϫ 10 3 ϭ 10.40 Ϫ 0.0575 ϫ SST Myrmidon Reef (this study) ID-TIMS 11 Sr/Ca ϫ 10 3 ϭ 10.40 Ϫ 0.0587 ϫ SST Stanley Reef (this study) ID-TIMS 12 Sr/Ca ϫ 10 3 ϭ 10.383 Ϫ 0.0587 ϫ SST Crowley et al. (1999) HR-ICP-MS 13 Sr/Ca ϫ 10 3 ϭ 10.76 Ϫ 0.063 ϫ SST Fallon et al. (1999) LA-ICP-MS 14 Sr/Ca ϫ 10 3 ϭ 10.55 Ϫ 0.0514 ϫ SST Schrag (1999) ICP-AES 15 Sr/Ca ϫ 10 3 ϭ 10.73 Ϫ 0.065 67 ϫ SST Correge et al. (2000) ICP-MS</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Fig. 11 .</head><label>11</label><figDesc>Plot of calibration slope against intercept for all calibrations listed inTable 1(SW ϭ seawater value).</figDesc></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">Sr/Ca in corals as a proxy for sea surface temperature</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">J.F.Marshall and M.T. McCulloch   </note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Acknowledgments-We thank Daryl Burrows and Stewart Fallon for their assistance with the coral coring. Graham Mortimer gave advice on many aspects of the chemistry and mass spectrometry. Chantal Alibert provided unpublished results on Sr/Ca measurements of seawater from the GBR and performed the Sr/Ca analyses from Pandora Reef. Daryl Burrows carried out the original Sr/Ca analyses from the top part of the Myrmidon Reef coral. We thank Dan Schrag, associate editor Robert Byrne and two anonymous referees for their constructive criticism of the paper.</p><p>Associate editor: R. H. Byrne</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fine-scale chronology of major flood plumes from the Burdekin River as deduced from coupled Sr/Ca (TIMS) and Ba (LA-ICP-MS) measurements in a coral from the inner shelf of GBR</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Alibert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Fallon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Mcculloch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Kinsley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Berkelmans</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Research School of Earth Science Annual Report</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="127" to="129" />
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Australian National University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Alibert C., Fallon S. J., McCulloch M. T., Kinsley L., and Berkelmans R. (1999) Fine-scale chronology of major flood plumes from the Burdekin River as deduced from coupled Sr/Ca (TIMS) and Ba (LA-ICP-MS) measurements in a coral from the inner shelf of GBR. Research School of Earth Science Annual Report. pp. 127-129. Australian National University.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Strontium/calcium ratios in modern Porites corals from the Great Barrier Reef as a proxy for sea surface temperature: Calibration of the thermometer and monitoring of ENSO</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Alibert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Mcculloch</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Paleoceanography</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="345" to="363" />
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Alibert C. and McCulloch M. T. (1997) Strontium/calcium ratios in modern Porites corals from the Great Barrier Reef as a proxy for sea surface temperature: Calibration of the thermometer and monitoring of ENSO. Paleoceanography 12, 345-363.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Upwelling as a source of nutrients for the Great Barrier Reef ecosystem: a solution to Darwin&apos;s question?</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Andrews</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Gentian</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mar. Ecol. Prog. Ser</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="257" to="269" />
			<date type="published" when="1982" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Andrews J. C. and Gentian P. (1982) Upwelling as a source of nutrients for the Great Barrier Reef ecosystem: a solution to Darwin&apos;s ques- tion? Mar. Ecol. Prog. Ser. 8, 257-269.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Interhemispheric synchrony of the last deglaciation inferred from alkenone palaeothermometry</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Bard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Rostek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Sonzogni</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">385</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="707" to="710" />
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Bard E., Rostek F., and Sonzogni C. (1997) Interhemispheric syn- chrony of the last deglaciation inferred from alkenone palaeother- mometry. Nature 385, 707-710.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Carbonate Sediments and their Diagenesis</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">G C</forename><surname>Bathurst</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1976" />
			<publisher>Elsevier</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Bathurst R. G. C. (1976) Carbonate Sediments and their Diagenesis. Elsevier.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Beck</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">264</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">891</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1994" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Beck J. W. (1994) Science 264, 891.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sea-surface temperature from coral skeletal strontium/calcium ratios</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Beck</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Edwards</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Emi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Taylor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Recy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Rougerie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Joannot</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Henin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">257</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="644" to="647" />
			<date type="published" when="1992" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Beck J. W., Edwards R. L., Emi I., Taylor F. W., Recy J., Rougerie F., Joannot P., and Henin C. (1992) Sea-surface temperature from coral skeletal strontium/calcium ratios. Science 257, 644 -647.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Abrupt changes in early Holocene tropical sea surface temperature derived from coral records</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Beck</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Recy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Taylor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Edwards</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Cabioch</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">385</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="705" to="707" />
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Beck J. W., Recy J., Taylor F., Edwards R. L., and Cabioch G. (1997) Abrupt changes in early Holocene tropical sea surface temperature derived from coral records. Nature 385, 705-707.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Large-scale bleaching of corals on the Great Barrier Reef</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Berkelmans</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Oliver</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Coral Reefs</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="55" to="60" />
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Berkelmans R. and Oliver J. K. (1999) Large-scale bleaching of corals on the Great Barrier Reef. Coral Reefs 18, 55-60.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Acantharian fluxes and strontium to chlorinity ratios in the North Pacific Ocean</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Bernstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Betzer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Feely</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Byrne</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Lamb</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Michaels</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">237</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1490" to="1494" />
			<date type="published" when="1987" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Bernstein R. E., Betzer P. R., Feely R. A., Byrne R. H., Lamb M. F., and Michaels A. F. (1987) Acantharian fluxes and strontium to chlorinity ratios in the North Pacific Ocean. Science 237, 1490 - 1494.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Strontium distribution in GEOSECS oceanic profiles</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Brass</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Turekian</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Earth Planet. Sci. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="141" to="148" />
			<date type="published" when="1974" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Brass G. W. and Turekian K. K. (1974) Strontium distribution in GEOSECS oceanic profiles. Earth Planet. Sci. Lett. 23, 141-148.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Broecker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Peng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Tracers in the Sea. Lamont-Doherty Geological Observatory</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1982" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Broecker W. S. Peng T. H. (1982) Tracers in the Sea. Lamont-Doherty Geological Observatory.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Model studies of the long-term behavior of ENSO</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Cane</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Zebiak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Xue</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Natural Climate Variability on Decade-to-Century Time Scales</title>
		<editor>D. G. Martinson, K. Bryan, M. Ghil, M. M. Hall, T. R. Karl, E. S. Sarachik, S. Sorooshian, and L. D. Talley</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>National Academy Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="442" to="457" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Cane M. A. Zebiak S. E. Xue Y. (1995) Model studies of the long-term behavior of ENSO. In Natural Climate Variability on Decade-to- Century Time Scales (ed. D. G. Martinson, K. Bryan, M. Ghil, M. M. Hall, T. R. Karl, E. S. Sarachik, S. Sorooshian, and L. D. Talley), pp. 442-457. National Academy Press.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evidence of stronger El Nino-Southern Oscillation (ENSO) events in a mid-Holocene massive coral</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Correge</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Delcroix</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Recy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Beck</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Cabioch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Cornec</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Paleoceanography</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="465" to="470" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Correge T., Delcroix T., Recy J., Beck W., Cabioch G., and Cornec F. L. (2000) Evidence of stronger El Nino-Southern Oscillation (ENSO) events in a mid-Holocene massive coral. Paleoceanography 15, 465-470.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">CLIMAP SSTs re-visited</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Crowley</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Climate Dynamics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="241" to="255" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Crowley T. J. (2000) CLIMAP SSTs re-visited. Climate Dynamics 16, 241-255.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Validation of coral temperature calibrations</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Crowley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Quinn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Hyde</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Paleoceanography</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="605" to="615" />
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Crowley T. J., Quinn T. M., and Hyde W. T. (1999) Validation of coral temperature calibrations. Paleoceanography 14, 605-615.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Synchronous, high-frequency oscillations in tropical sea surface temperatures and North Atlantic Deep Water production during the last glacial cycle</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Curry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Oppo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Paleoceanography</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="14" />
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Curry W. B. and Oppo D. W. (1997) Synchronous, high-frequency oscillations in tropical sea surface temperatures and North Atlantic Deep Water production during the last glacial cycle. Paleoceanog- raphy 12, 1-14.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Seawater strontium and Sr/Ca variability in the Atlantic and Pacific oceans</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>De Villiers</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Earth Planet. Sci. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">171</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="623" to="634" />
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">de Villiers S. (1999) Seawater strontium and Sr/Ca variability in the Atlantic and Pacific oceans. Earth Planet. Sci. Lett. 171, 623-634.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Biological controls on coral Sr/Ca and ␦ 18 O reconstructions of sea surface temperatures</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>De Villiers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Nelson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Chivas</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">269</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1247" to="1249" />
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">de Villiers S., Nelson B. K., and Chivas A. R. (1995) Biological controls on coral Sr/Ca and ␦ 18 O reconstructions of sea surface temperatures. Science 269, 1247-1249.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Sr/Catemperature relationship in coralline aragonite: Influence of variability in (Sr/Ca) seawater and skeletal growth parameters</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>De Villiers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Shen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Nelson</forename><forename type="middle">B K</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geochim. Cosmochim. Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="197" to="208" />
			<date type="published" when="1994" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">de Villiers S., Shen G. T., and Nelson B. K. (1994) The Sr/Ca- temperature relationship in coralline aragonite: Influence of variabil- ity in (Sr/Ca) seawater and skeletal growth parameters. Geochim. Cos- mochim. Acta 58, 197-208.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A 17,000-year glacio-eustatic sea level record: influence of glacial melting rates on the Younger Dryas event and deep-ocean circulation</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Fairbanks</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">342</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="637" to="642" />
			<date type="published" when="1989" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Fairbanks R. (1989) A 17,000-year glacio-eustatic sea level record: influence of glacial melting rates on the Younger Dryas event and deep-ocean circulation. Nature 342, 637-642.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Corals at their latitudinal limits: laser ablation trace element systematics in Porites from Shirigai Bay</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Fallon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Mcculloch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Van Woesik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Sinclair</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Japan. Earth Planet. Sci. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">172</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="221" to="238" />
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Fallon S. J., McCulloch M. T., van Woesik R., and Sinclair D. J. (1999) Corals at their latitudinal limits: laser ablation trace element system- atics in Porites from Shirigai Bay, Japan. Earth Planet. Sci. Lett. 172, 221-238.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">New views of tropical paleoclimates from corals</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Gagan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Ayliffe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Beck</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Cole</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">R M</forename><surname>Druffel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Dunbar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Schrag</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Quart. Sci. Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="45" to="64" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Gagan M. K., Ayliffe L. K., Beck J. W., Cole J. E., Druffel E. R. M., Dunbar R. B., and Schrag D. P. (2000) New views of tropical paleoclimates from corals. Quart. Sci. Rev. 19, 45-64.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Temperature and surface-ocean water balance of the mid-Holocene tropical western Pacific</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Gagan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Ayliffe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Hopley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Cali</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Mortimer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Chappell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Mcculloch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Head</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">279</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1014" to="1018" />
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Gagan M. K., Ayliffe L. K., Hopley D., Cali J. A., Mortimer G. E., Chappell J., McCulloch M. T., and Head M. J. (1998) Temperature and surface-ocean water balance of the mid-Holocene tropical west- ern Pacific. Science 279, 1014 -1018.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Timing coral-based climatic histories using 13 C enrichments driven by synchronized spawning</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Gagan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Chivas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Isdale</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1009" to="1012" />
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Gagan M. K., Chivas A. R., and Isdale P. J. (1996) Timing coral-based climatic histories using 13 C enrichments driven by synchronized spawning. Geology 24, 1009 -1012.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The physiology of skeleton formation in corals. I. A method for measuring the rate of calcium deposition by corals under different conditions</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Goreau</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biol. Bull</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">116</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="59" to="75" />
			<date type="published" when="1959" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Goreau T. F. (1959) The physiology of skeleton formation in corals. I. A method for measuring the rate of calcium deposition by corals under different conditions. Biol. Bull. 116, 59 -75.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tropical temperature variations since 20,000 years ago; Modulating interhemispheric climate change</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Guilderson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Fairbanks</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Rubenstone</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">263</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="663" to="665" />
			<date type="published" when="1994" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Guilderson T. P., Fairbanks R. G., and Rubenstone J. L. (1994) Trop- ical temperature variations since 20,000 years ago; Modulating in- terhemispheric climate change. Science 263, 663-665.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Stable isotope and Sr/Ca-signals in corals from the Indian Ocean</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Heiss</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Camoin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Eisenhauer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W.-C</forename><surname>Dullo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Hansen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 8th International Coral Reef Symposium. Panama</title>
		<meeting>the 8th International Coral Reef Symposium. Panama</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1713" to="1718" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Heiss G. A., Camoin G. F., Eisenhauer A., Dullo W.-C., Hansen B. (1997) Stable isotope and Sr/Ca-signals in corals from the Indian Ocean. Proceedings of the 8th International Coral Reef Symposium. Panama, Vol. 12, pp. 1713-1718.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Late Pleistocene evolution of the ocean&apos;s carbonate system</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Hodell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Charles</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Sierro</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Earth Planet. Sci. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">192</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="109" to="124" />
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Hodell D. A., Charles C. D., and Sierro F. J. (2001) Late Pleistocene evolution of the ocean&apos;s carbonate system. Earth Planet. Sci. Lett. 192, 109 -124.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Sr/Ca in corals as a proxy for sea surface temperature</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Sr/Ca in corals as a proxy for sea surface temperature</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Climate change, coral bleaching and the future of the world&apos;s coral reefs</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Hoegh-Guldberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mar. Freshwater Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="839" to="866" />
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Hoegh-Guldberg O. (1999) Climate change, coral bleaching and the future of the world&apos;s coral reefs. Mar. Freshwater Res. 50, 839 -866.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The response of coral growth rate and strontium content to light intensity and water temperature</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Houck</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Jokiel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 3rd International Coral Reef Symposium. Miami</title>
		<meeting>the 3rd International Coral Reef Symposium. Miami</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1977" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">425</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Houck J. E., Smith S. V., Jokiel P. L. (1977) The response of coral growth rate and strontium content to light intensity and water tem- perature. Proceedings of the 3rd International Coral Reef Sympo- sium. Miami, Vol. 2, p. 425.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Incorporation of strontium ( 90 Sr 2ϩ ) into the skeleton of the hermatypic coral Galaxea fascicularis</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Ip</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Krishnaveni</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Exp. Zool</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">258</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="273" to="276" />
			<date type="published" when="1991" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Ip Y. K. and Krishnaveni P. (1991) Incorporation of strontium ( 90 Sr 2ϩ ) into the skeleton of the hermatypic coral Galaxea fascicularis. J. Exp. Zool. 258, 273-276.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Are calcium and strontium transported by the same mechanism in the hermatypic coral Galaxea fascicularis?</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Ip</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">L L</forename><surname>Lim</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Exp. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">159</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="501" to="513" />
			<date type="published" when="1991" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Ip Y. K. and Lim A. L. L. (1991) Are calcium and strontium trans- ported by the same mechanism in the hermatypic coral Galaxea fascicularis? J. Exp. Biol. 159, 501-513.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The ultrastructure of skeletogenesis in hermatypic corals</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Johnston</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. Rev. Cytol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">67</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="171" to="214" />
			<date type="published" when="1980" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Johnston I. S. (1980) The ultrastructure of skeletogenesis in hermatypic corals. Int. Rev. Cytol. 67, 171-214.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Interpretation of Sr 2ϩ concentrations in carbonate minerals and rocks</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J J</forename><surname>Kinsman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Sedim. Petrol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="486" to="508" />
			<date type="published" when="1969" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Kinsman D. J. J. (1969) Interpretation of Sr 2ϩ concentrations in car- bonate minerals and rocks. J. Sedim. Petrol. 39, 486 -508.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The coprecipitation of cations with CaCO 3 . IV. The coprecipitation of Sr 2ϩ with aragonite between 16°and 96°C</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J J</forename><surname>Kinsman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Holland</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geochim. Cosmochim. Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="17" />
			<date type="published" when="1969" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Kinsman D. J. J. and Holland H. D. (1969) The coprecipitation of cations with CaCO 3 . IV. The coprecipitation of Sr 2ϩ with aragonite between 16°and 96°C. Geochim. Cosmochim. Acta 33, 1-17.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Deposition of calcium ( 45 Ca 2ϩ ) in the coral Galaxea fascicularis</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Krishnaveni</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Chou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Ip</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Compar. Biochem. Physiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">94</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="509" to="513" />
			<date type="published" when="1989" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Krishnaveni P., Chou L. M., and Ip Y. K. (1989) Deposition of calcium ( 45 Ca 2ϩ ) in the coral Galaxea fascicularis. Compar. Biochem. Physiol. 94A, 509 -513.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Climate variation and E1 Nino-Southern Oscillation events on the Great Barrier Reef: 1958 to</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Lough</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Coral Reefs</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="181" to="195" />
			<date type="published" when="1987" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Lough J. M. (1994) Climate variation and E1 Nino-Southern Oscilla- tion events on the Great Barrier Reef: 1958 to 1987. Coral Reefs 13, 181-195.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sea surface temperatures on the Great Barrier Reef: a contribution to the study of coral bleaching</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Lough</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">GBRMPA Res. Publ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">57</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">pp</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Lough J. M. (1999) Sea surface temperatures on the Great Barrier Reef: a contribution to the study of coral bleaching. GBRMPA Res. Publ. 57, 31 pp.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Calcification in hermatypic and ahermatypic corals</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Marshall</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">271</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="637" to="639" />
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Marshall A. T. (1996) Calcification in hermatypic and ahermatypic corals. Science 271, 637-639.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Decadal-scale, high resolution records of sea surface temperature in the eastern Indian and south western Pacific Oceans from proxy records of the Sr/Ca ratio of massive Porites corals</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Marshall</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Australian National University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note>Ph.D. thesis</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">Marshall J. F. (2000) Decadal-scale, high resolution records of sea surface temperature in the eastern Indian and south western Pacific Oceans from proxy records of the Sr/Ca ratio of massive Porites corals. Ph.D. thesis, Australian National University.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Evidence of mid-Holocene cooling of the tropical western Pacific Ocean from Sr/Ca-derived sea surface temperatures for Porites sp. corals from the central Great Barrier Reef</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Marshall</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Mcculloch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Burrows</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>submitted. Paleoceanography</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">Marshall J. F., McCulloch M. T., Burrows D. B. (submitted, 2002) Evidence of mid-Holocene cooling of the tropical western Pacific Ocean from Sr/Ca-derived sea surface temperatures for Porites sp. corals from the central Great Barrier Reef. Paleoceanography.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evidence of El Nino and the Indian Ocean Dipole from Sr/Ca derived SSTs for modern corals at Christmas Island, eastern Indian Ocean</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Marshall</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Mcculloch</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geophys. Res. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3453" to="3456" />
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Marshall J. F. and McCulloch M. T. (2001) Evidence of El Nino and the Indian Ocean Dipole from Sr/Ca derived SSTs for modern corals at Christmas Island, eastern Indian Ocean. Geophys. Res. Lett. 28, 3453-3456.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Variation of foraminiferal Sr/Ca over Quaternary glacialinterglacial cycles: Evidence for changes in mean ocean Sr/Ca</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Martin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Lea</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Mashiotta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Papenfuss</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sarnthein</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geochem. Geophys. Geosyst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Martin P. A., Lea D. W., Mashiotta T. A., Papenfuss T., and Sarnthein M. (1999) Variation of foraminiferal Sr/Ca over Quaternary glacial- interglacial cycles: Evidence for changes in mean ocean Sr/Ca. Geochem. Geophys. Geosyst. 1, .</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Calcification generates protons for nutrient and bicarbonate uptake</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Mcconnaughey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Whelen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Earth Sci. Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="95" to="117" />
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">McConnaughey T. A. and Whelen J. F. (1997) Calcification generates protons for nutrient and bicarbonate uptake. Earth Sci. Rev. 42, 95-117.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The coral record of last interglacial sea levels and sea surface temperatures</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Mcculloch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Esat</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Chem. Geol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">169</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="107" to="129" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">McCulloch M. T. and Esat T. (2000) The coral record of last intergla- cial sea levels and sea surface temperatures. Chem. Geol. 169, 107-129.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A high-resolution Sr/Ca and ␦ 18 O coral record from the Great Barrier Reef, Australia, and the 1982-1983 El Nino</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Mcculloch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Gagan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Mortimer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Chivas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Isdale</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geochim. Cosmochim. Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2747" to="2754" />
			<date type="published" when="1994" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">McCulloch M. T., Gagan M. K., Mortimer G. E., Chivas A. R., and Isdale P. J. (1994) A high-resolution Sr/Ca and ␦ 18 O coral record from the Great Barrier Reef, Australia, and the 1982-1983 El Nino. Geochim. Cosmochim. Acta 58, 2747-2754.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Coral record of equatorial sea-surface temperatures during the penultimate deglaciation at Huon Peninsula</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Mcculloch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Tudhope</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Esat</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Mortimer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Chappell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Pillans</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Chivas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Omura</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">283</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="202" to="204" />
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">McCulloch M. T., Tudhope A. W., Esat T. M., Mortimer G. E., Chappell J., Pillans B., Chivas A. R., and Omura A. (1999) Coral record of equatorial sea-surface temperatures during the penultimate deglaciation at Huon Peninsula. Science 283, 202-204.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Annual cycles of U/Ca in coral skeletons and U/Ca thermometry</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Min</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Edwards</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Taylor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Recy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Gallup</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Beck</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geochim. Cosmochim. Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">59</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2025" to="2042" />
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Min G. R., Edwards R. L., Taylor F. W., Recy J., Gallup C., and Beck J. W. (1995) Annual cycles of U/Ca in coral skeletons and U/Ca thermometry. Geochim. Cosmochim. Acta 59, 2025-2042.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mg/Ca thermometry in coral skeletons</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Mitsuguchi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Matsumato</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Abe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Uchida</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Isdale</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">274</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="961" to="963" />
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Mitsuguchi T., Matsumato E., Abe O., Uchida T., and Isdale P. J. (1996) Mg/Ca thermometry in coral skeletons. Science 274, 961- 963.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Petrogenic applications of the 40 K-40 Ca radiogenic decay scheme-A reconnaissance study</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Nelson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Mcculloch</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Chem. Geol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">79</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="275" to="293" />
			<date type="published" when="1989" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Nelson D. R. and McCulloch M. T. (1989) Petrogenic applications of the 40 K-40 Ca radiogenic decay scheme-A reconnaissance study. Chem. Geol. 79, 275-293.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ca isotope fractionation on the Earth and other solar system materials</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Russell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Papanastassiou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Tombrello</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geochim. Cosmochim. Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1075" to="1090" />
			<date type="published" when="1978" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Russell W. A., Papanastassiou D. A., and Tombrello T. A. (1978) Ca isotope fractionation on the Earth and other solar system materials. Geochim. Cosmochim. Acta 42, 1075-1090.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b53">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The calibration of D [Sr/Ca] versus sea surface temperature relationship for Porites corals</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C.-C</forename><surname>Shen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C.-Y</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C.-H</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C.-F</forename><surname>Dai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Li L.-A</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geochim. Cosmochim. Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">60</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3849" to="3858" />
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Shen C.-C., Lee T., Chen C.-Y., Wang C.-H., Dai C.-F., and Li L.-A. (1996) The calibration of D [Sr/Ca] versus sea surface temperature relationship for Porites corals. Geochim. Cosmochim. Acta 60, 3849 -3858.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b54">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Environmental controls on uranium in reef corals</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Shen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Dunbar</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geochim. Cosmochim. Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">59</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2009" to="2024" />
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Shen G. T. and Dunbar R. B. (1995) Environmental controls on uranium in reef corals. Geochim. Cosmochim. Acta 59, 2009 -2024.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b55">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rapid analysis of high-precision Sr/Ca ratios in corals and other marine carbonates</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Schrag</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Paleoceanography</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="97" to="102" />
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Schrag D. P. (1999) Rapid analysis of high-precision Sr/Ca ratios in corals and other marine carbonates. Paleoceanography 14, 97-102.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b56">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">High spatial-resolution analysis of trace elements in corals using laser ablation ICP-MS</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Sinclair</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Australian National University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">PhD thesis</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">Sinclair D. J. (1999) High spatial-resolution analysis of trace elements in corals using laser ablation ICP-MS. PhD thesis. Australian Na- tional University.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b57">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">High resolution analysis of trace elements in corals by laser ablation ICP-MS</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Sinclair</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Kinsley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Mcculloch</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geochim. Cosmochim. Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">62</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1899" to="1901" />
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Sinclair D. J., Kinsley L. P., and McCulloch M. T. (1998) High resolution analysis of trace elements in corals by laser ablation ICP-MS. Geochim. Cosmochim. Acta 62, 1899 -1901.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b58">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Strontium-calcium thermometry in coral skeletons</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Buddemeier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Redalje</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Houck</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">204</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="404" to="407" />
			<date type="published" when="1979" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Smith S. V., Buddemeier R. W., Redalje R. C., and Houck J. E. (1979) Strontium-calcium thermometry in coral skeletons. Science 204, 404 -407.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b59">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effects of Quaternary sea level cycles on strontium in seawater</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Stoll</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Schrag</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geochim. Cosmochim. Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">62</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1107" to="1118" />
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Stoll H. M. and Schrag D. P. (1998) Effects of Quaternary sea level cycles on strontium in seawater. Geochim. Cosmochim. Acta 62, 1107-1118.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b60">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Are seawater Sr/Ca variations preserved in Quaternary foraminifera?</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Stoll</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Schrag</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Clemens</forename><forename type="middle">S C</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geochim. Cosmochim. Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">63</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3535" to="3547" />
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Stoll H. M., Schrag D. P., and Clemens S. C. (1999) Are seawater Sr/Ca variations preserved in Quaternary foraminifera? Geochim. Cosmochim. Acta 63, 3535-3547.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b61">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Strontium and uranium concentrations in aragonite precipitated by some modern corals</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Thompson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Livingston</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Earth Planet. Sci. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="439" to="442" />
			<date type="published" when="1970" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Thompson G. and Livingston H. D. (1970) Strontium and uranium concentrations in aragonite precipitated by some modern corals. Earth Planet. Sci. Lett. 8, 439 -442.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b62">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The strontium-calcium atom ratio in carbonate-secreting marine organisms</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Thompson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Chow</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Deep Sea Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="20" to="39" />
			<date type="published" when="1955" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Suppl.)</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">Thompson T. G. and Chow T. J. (1955) The strontium-calcium atom ratio in carbonate-secreting marine organisms. Deep Sea Res. (Suppl.) 3, 20 -39.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b63">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Incorporation of strontium into reef coral skeletal carbonate</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Weber</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geochim. Cosmochim. Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2173" to="2190" />
			<date type="published" when="1973" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Weber J. N. (1973) Incorporation of strontium into reef coral skeletal carbonate. Geochim. Cosmochim. Acta 37, 2173-2190.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b64">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Scientific studies in the Cocos (Keeling) Islands: an introduction</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Woodroffe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Berry</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Atoll Res. Bull</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">399</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="16" />
			<date type="published" when="1994" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Woodroffe C. D. and Berry P. F. (1994) Scientific studies in the Cocos (Keeling) Islands: an introduction. Atoll Res. Bull. 399, 1-16.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b65">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Marshall</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Mcculloch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">J.F. Marshall and M.T. McCulloch</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
