<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /Users/grace/grobid-0.6.1/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">A Likely Ancient Genome Duplication in the Speciose Reef-Building Coral Genus, Acropora</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2019-03-29">March 29, 2019</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Yafei</forename><surname>Mao</surname></persName>
							<email>yafei.mao@oist.jp</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Okinawa Institute of Science and Technology Graduate University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>904-0495</postCode>
									<settlement>Onna</settlement>
									<region>Okinawa</region>
									<country key="JP">Japan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Noriyuki</forename><surname>Satoh</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Okinawa Institute of Science and Technology Graduate University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>904-0495</postCode>
									<settlement>Onna</settlement>
									<region>Okinawa</region>
									<country key="JP">Japan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Marine</forename><forename type="middle">Genomics</forename><surname>Unit</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Okinawa Institute of Science and Technology Graduate University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>904-0495</postCode>
									<settlement>Onna</settlement>
									<region>Okinawa</region>
									<country key="JP">Japan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">A Likely Ancient Genome Duplication in the Speciose Reef-Building Coral Genus, Acropora</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2019-03-29">March 29, 2019</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.isci</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received: July 10, 2018 Revised: January 28, 2019 Accepted: January 31, 2019</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.1" ident="GROBID" when="2021-09-14T02:41+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Whole-genome duplication (WGD) has been recognized as a significant evolutionary force in the origin and diversification of multiple organisms. Acropora, a speciose reef-building coral genus, is suspected to have originated by polyploidy. Yet, there is no genetic evidence to support this hypothesis. Using comprehensive phylogenomic and comparative genomic approaches, we analyzed six Acroporid genomes and found that a WGD event likely occurred $31 million years ago in the most recent common ancestor of Acropora, concurrent with a worldwide coral extinction. We found that duplicated genes were highly enriched in gene regulation functions, including those of stress responses. The functional clusters of duplicated genes are related to the divergence of gene expression patterns during development. Some proteinaceous toxins were generated by WGD in Acropora compared with other cnidarian species. Collectively, this study provides evidence for an ancient WGD event in corals, which helps explain the origin and diversification of Acropora.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>INTRODUCTION</head><p>Reef-building corals contribute to tropical marine ecosystems that support innumerable marine organisms, but reefs are increasingly threatened because of recent increases in seawater temperatures, pollution, and other stressors <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Ainsworth et al., 2016;</ref><ref type="bibr">Renema et al., 2016)</ref>. The Acroporidae is a family of reef-building corals within the phylum Cnidaria, one of the basal phyla of the animal clade <ref type="bibr">(Richards et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr">Wallace, 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr">Wallace and Rosen, 2006)</ref>. Astreopora (Anthozoa: Acroporidae) is the sister genus in the acroporid lineage according to fossil records and molecular phylogenetic evidence <ref type="bibr">(Fukami et al., 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr">Suzuki and Nomura, 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr">Wallace, 2012)</ref>. Importantly, Acropora (Anthozoa: Acroporidae), one of the most diverse genera of reef-building corals, including more than 150 species in the Indo-Pacific Ocean, is thought to have originated from Astreopora $60 mya with several species turnovers <ref type="bibr">(Edinger and Risk, 1994;</ref><ref type="bibr">Renema et al., 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr">Wallace, 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr">Wallace and Rosen, 2006)</ref>. Investigating the evolutionary history of this group importantly contributes to our understanding of coral reef biodiversity and conservation. Hybridization among Acropora species has been observed in the wild <ref type="bibr">(Vollmer and Palumbi, 2002)</ref>, and variable chromosome numbers have been determined in different Acropora lineages <ref type="bibr">(Kenyon, 1997)</ref>. In addition, gene duplications have been shown in several Acropora gene families <ref type="bibr">(Gacesa et al., 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr">Hamada et al., 2013)</ref>. Based on their unique lifestyle, variable chromosome numbers, and complicated reticular evolutionary history, Indo-Pacific Acropora likely originated via polyploidy <ref type="bibr">(Gacesa et al., 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr">Hamada et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr">Kenyon, 1997;</ref><ref type="bibr">Richards and Hobbs, 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr">Van Oppen et al., 2001;</ref><ref type="bibr">Vollmer and Palumbi, 2002;</ref><ref type="bibr">Willis et al., 2006)</ref>. However, there is no direct molecular and genetic evidence to support this hypothesis.</p><p>Ancient whole (large-scale)-gene/genome duplication (WGD), or paleopolyploidy, has shaped the genomes of vertebrates, green plants, and other organisms, and is usually regarded as an evolutionary landmark in the origin and diversification of organisms <ref type="bibr">(Soltis et al., 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr">Van de Peer et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr">Van De Peer et al., 2017</ref>) ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure S1</ref>). Two separate WGD events have been documented in the common ancestors of vertebrates (two rounds of WGD) (Dehal and Boore, 2005) and another major WGD has been reported in the last common ancestor of teleost fish <ref type="bibr">(Christoffels et al., 2004;</ref><ref type="bibr">Glasauer and Neuhauss, 2014)</ref>. Meanwhile, living angiosperms share an ancient WGD event <ref type="bibr">(Jiao et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr">Tiley et al., 2016)</ref>, and many other WGD events have been reported in major clades of angiosperms <ref type="bibr">(Soltis et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr">Vanneste et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr">Wang et al., 2018)</ref>. In addition, two rounds of WGDs in the vertebrates are suggested to have occurred during the Cambrian Period, and some WGDs in plants are believed to have occurred during Cretaceous-Tertiary (Smith et al., 2013; Van De Peer et al., 2017; Vanneste et al., 2014). Thus, WGD is regarded as an important evolutionary way to reduce the risk of extinction <ref type="bibr">(Van de Peer et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr">Van De Peer et al., 2017;</ref><ref type="bibr">Vanneste et al., 2014)</ref>. However, the study of WGD in Cnidaria has received less attention <ref type="bibr">(Kenny et al., 2016;</ref><ref type="bibr">Li et al., 2018;</ref><ref type="bibr">Schwager et al., 2017;</ref><ref type="bibr">Van de Peer et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr">Van De Peer et al., 2017)</ref>.</p><p>Duplicated genes created by WGD have complex fates during diploidization <ref type="bibr">(Sé mon and Wolfe, 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr">Van de Peer et al., 2009)</ref>. Usually, one of the duplicated genes is silenced or lost due to redundancy of gene functions, termed ''nonfunctionalization.'' However, retained duplicated genes provide important sources of biological complexity and evolutionary novelty due to subfunctionalization, neofunctionalization, and dosage effects <ref type="bibr">(Conant et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr">Jiao et al., 2011)</ref>. Duplicated genes may develop complementary gene functions via subfunctionalization, evolve new functions through neofunctionalization, or are retained in complicated regulatory networks with different gene expressions due to dosage effects. For instance, duplicated MADS-Box genes are crucial for flower development and the origin of phenotypic novelty in plants <ref type="bibr">(Van de Peer et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr">Veron et al., 2006)</ref>. Duplicated homeobox genes provide raw genetic material for vertebrate development <ref type="bibr">(Canestro et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr">Glasauer and Neuhauss, 2014)</ref>. In addition, toxin diversification following gene duplications has been recognized as a mechanism to enhance adaptation in animals <ref type="bibr">(Kondrashov, 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr">Kordi s and Guben sek, 2000)</ref>, especially in snake venoms <ref type="bibr">(Hargreaves et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr">Vonk et al., 2013)</ref>. Interestingly, toxic proteins are involved in various important processes in corals, including prey capture, protection from predators, wound healing, etc <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Armoza-Zvuloni et al., 2016;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Ben-Ari et al., 2018)</ref>, but it is still unclear how gene duplications of toxic proteins evolved in corals.</p><p>Isozyme electrophoresis and restriction fragment length polymorphism were used to identify gene duplications in polyploids a few decades ago <ref type="bibr">(Fü rthauer et al., 1999;</ref><ref type="bibr">Stuber and Goodman, 1983)</ref>. In the past 10 years, next-generation sequencing has generated a wealth of genomic data at vastly decreased cost and reduced efforts <ref type="bibr">(Goodwin et al., 2016;</ref><ref type="bibr">Hardwick et al., 2017)</ref>. Three main methods were developed to identify WGD, based on (1) analysis of the rate of synonymous substitutions per synonymous site (dS) of duplicated genes within a genome (dS-based method) <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(Blanc et al., 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr">Lynch and Conery, 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr">Vanneste et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Mao, 2019)</ref>, (2) phylogenetic analysis of gene families among multiple genomes (phylogenomic analysis) <ref type="bibr">(Blomme et al., 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr">Jiao et al., 2011)</ref>, and (3) synteny block identification compared with sister lineages without WGD (synteny analysis) <ref type="bibr">(Bowers et al., 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr">Dehal and Boore, 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr">Zhang et al., 2017)</ref>. The dS-based method and phylogenomic analysis only require gene family information, without genome assembly. However, too ancient WGD cannot be detected by the dS-based method, while gene tree uncertainty usually causes bias in the phylogenomic analysis. Both methods rely heavily on gene family estimation and clustering. Inaccurate gene predictions (gene models) and rough gene family cluster algorithms can easily fail to detect WGD using either method. In contrast, the synteny analysis relies heavily on genome assembly quality. Poor assembly quality can hide the WGD signals, and some genomes with huge rearrangements cannot be used to detect WGD using synteny block identification. Therefore, the most credible conclusions depend on complementary evidence from different methods <ref type="bibr">(Chen and Birchler, 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr">Soltis and Soltis, 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr">Tiley et al., 2016)</ref>.</p><p>Here, using all three methods, we analyzed a genome of Astreopora (Astreopora sp1) as an outgroup, and five Acropora genomes (Acropora digitifera, Acropora gemmifera, Acropora subglabra, Acropora echinata, and Acropora tenuis) to address the following questions: (1) whether and when WGD occurred in Acropora, (2) what is the fate of duplicated genes in Acropora after the event, (3) what are the gene expression patterns of duplicated genes across five developmental stages in A. digitifera, and <ref type="formula">4</ref>what is the role of WGD in diversification of toxic proteins in Acropora ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure S2</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Phylogenomic and Synteny Analysis of IAsa</head><p>If the proposed IAsa is deemed correct, the ohnologs of Acropora (paralogs created by IAsa) should form two clades from their orthologs in Astreopora sp1 by mapping IAsa onto phylogenetic trees (Jiao et al., 2011; Marcet-Houben and Gabaldó n, 2015). In other words, the phylogenetic topology would be A calibrated phylogenomic tree of six Acroporid species inferred from 3,461 single-copy orthologs using BEAST2. Horizontal bars on branches of the tree represent the timing of WGD in Acropora. The timing of IAsa was estimated at 35 mya (95% confidence interval: 31.18-35.7 mya) and 31 mya (95% confidence interval: 27.86-34.77 mya) by the dS-based method (horizontal purple bar) and phylogenomic analysis (horizontal orange bar), respectively. Gray shading represents the timing of one coral species turnover event, the Oligocene-Miocene transition (OMT), suggesting that IAsa is correlated with OMT. See also Figures S1, S3, and S4 <ref type="table">, Tables S5 and S6.</ref> (((Acropora clade1) bootstrap1, (Acropora clade2) bootstrap2), Astreopora sp1), defined as gene duplication topology ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 2B</ref>).</p><p>We performed a phylogenomic analysis to further evaluate the proposed IAsa. Firstly, we defined orthogroups as clusters of homologous genes in Acropora derived from a single gene in Astreopora sp1.  3) in dS distributions of the five Acropora lineages indicate that a WGD event occurred in Acropora. (Light red, A. digitifera; light yellow, A. echinata; light green, A. gemmifera; light blue, A. subglabra; light purple: A. tenuis; light cyan, Astreopora sp1). (B) Hypothetical tree topology of duplicated genes in the Acroporidae and the phylogeny of one duplicated gene (alphaprotein kinase 1-like). The phylogenetic tree shows gene retention, loss, and duplications following WGD. (C) Co-linear gene alignments of Astreopora sp1 and A. tenuis on scaffolds. The gray links show orthologs between Astreopora sp1 and A. tenuis. <ref type="table">Figures S5-S10 and Tables S1-S3.</ref> iScience 13, 20-32, March 29, 2019</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>See also</head><p>Each orthogroup contained at least seven homologous genes, including at least one gene copy in each Acropora species and only one gene copy in Astreopora sp1. We selected 883 orthogroups from 19,760 gene families, and reconstructed the phylogeny of 883 orthogroups using both maximum likelihood (ML) and Bayesian methods. We found that the phylogenetic topology of 205 orthogroups was consistent with gene duplication topology supporting IAsa. We further defined the 205 orthogroups as coreorthogroups <ref type="table">(Table S3</ref>, see Data S1).</p><p>In particular, we found differential gene loss, retention, and duplication in Acropora lineages. For instance, the phylogeny of orthogroup 1370 (alpha-protein kinase 1-like) showed gene retention in A. subglabra, A. digitifera, and A. echinata; gene loss in A. tenuis; and an extra gene duplication in A. subglabra. This implies that diversification of duplicated genes may contribute to species complexity and evolutionary innovation in Acropora (Glasauer and Neuhauss, 2014) ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 2B</ref>).</p><p>To estimate the split time of the two Acropora clades that could be regarded as the timing of IAsa, we selected 154 high-quality core-orthogroups, with bootstrap values in both Acropora clades &gt;70 in ML phylogeny, to reconstruct a time-calibrated phylogeny from the 205 core-orthogroups using BEAST2 <ref type="bibr">(Jiao et al., 2011)</ref>. However, we found that it was difficult for the parameters in MCMC to converge in 70 coreorthogroups, and we only successfully dated the phylogenetic trees of 135 high-quality core-orthogroups (see Data S1). Next, we estimated the distribution of inferred node ages between the two Acropora clades, and found that the peak value was estimated to be 31 Ma (95% confidence interval: 27.86-34.77 Ma), indicating that IAsa occurred at 31 Ma ( <ref type="figure">Figure S8</ref>). This result is in coincidence with the timing of the IAsa estimated by the dS-based method.</p><p>Intergenomic co-linearity is often used to directly identify ancient WGD and to reconstruct ancestral karyotypes in vertebrates <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Berthelot et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr">Nakatani et al., 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr">Zhang et al., 2017)</ref>. We performed intergenomic co-linearity and synteny analysis between Astreopora sp1 and A. tenuis to support IAsa. We found that synteny blocks of 21 scaffolds in Astreopora sp1 have at least two duplicated segments in A. tenuis ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_11">Figure S9</ref>). For example, two duplicated segments in scaffold 130 and scaffold 70 of A. tenuis corresponded to scaffold 323 in Astreopora sp1 ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 2C</ref>). In addition, we also observed that duplicated segments of the five Acropora species, which corresponded to the longest scaffold of Astreopora sp1, had good co-linearity ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure S10</ref>).</p><p>In summary, we found evidence to support IAsa with the dS-based method, and phylogenomic and synteny analyses. Moreover, we suggest that IAsa probably occurred between 28 and 36 mya ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>The Fate of Duplicated Genes Originating from IAsa</head><p>Duplicated genes provide substrates for diversification and evolutionary novelty, and most of them are regulators of gene networks in vertebrates and plants <ref type="bibr">(Jiao et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr">Kassahn et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr">Zhang et al., 2017)</ref>. We examined Gene Ontology (GO) for all genes among the 154 high-quality core-orthogroups to investigate their roles in IAsa and found that their molecular functions are enriched in specific categories: transporter, catalytic, binding, and receptor activity. Some of those are involved in gene regulation <ref type="table">(Table 1)</ref>.</p><p>Furthermore, we identified some duplicated genes under subfunctionalization and neofunctionalization, possibly contributing to stress responses of corals. dnaJ homolog subfamily B member 11-like (DNAJB) protein was shown to be involved in heat stress responses in marine organisms <ref type="bibr">(Fujikawa et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr">Wang et al., 2014)</ref>. Orthogroup 1247 (DNAJB) has two main domains (Ras and Dnaj domains) in Astreopora sp1 representing the ancient state. Each of the two domains was independently lost in the duplicated genes, resulting in complementary functions of the duplicated genes after IAsa ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figures 3A and  S11</ref>). In addition, excitatory amino acid transporters may be related to symbiotic interactions in Acropora <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(Bertucci et al., 2015)</ref>. Orthogroup 1244 (excitatory amino acid transporter 1-like) was predicted as a six transmembrane protein, and a high number of mutations have accumulated in both untransmembrane and transmembrane regions, suggesting that new functions would be generated <ref type="bibr">(Figures 3B and S12)</ref>. These examples suggest that IAsa might participate in stress responses and symbiotic interactions of Acropora. Together, these results agree with previous patterns of the fate of duplicated genes in vertebrates and plants <ref type="bibr">(Jiao et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr">Soltis et al., 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr">Van De Peer et al., 2017;</ref><ref type="bibr">Zhang et al., 2017)</ref>, indicating that the IAsa possibly contributes to the species complexity and diversification in Acropora.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Gene Expression Patterns of Duplicated Genes across Five Developmental Stages in A. digitifera</head><p>To better understand the evolution of duplicated genes, gene expression analysis across five developmental stages in A. digitifera (blastula, gastrula, postgastrula, planula, and adult polyps) was carried out <ref type="bibr">(Reyes-Bermudez et al., 2016)</ref>. We identified 236 ohnologous pairs in A. digitifera from 883 ML phylogeny (see Methods) and found that these ohnologous pairs presented an interesting gene expression profiling.  <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure 4A</ref>). Ohnologous pairs in the HC cluster are enriched in protein kinase, whereas ohnologous pairs in the NC cluster are enriched in membrane transporter and ion-binding proteins ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure 4B</ref>). This result indicates that the two clusters of ohnologous pairs potentially evolved into different gene functions. In addition, we compared dN/dS values to investigate selective pressure on HC and NC clusters ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure 4C</ref>), but there is no significant difference between the two clusters (Mann-Whitney-Wilcoxon test, p = 0.51).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Evolution of Toxic Proteins in Cnidaria</head><p>Next, we investigated the role of IAsa in the diversification of toxins in Acropora. We identified $200 putative toxic proteins in each of the five Acropora species, and we clustered them with the putative toxic proteins of Astreopora sp1 and other six Cnidarian species (Hydra magnipapillata, Nematostella vectensis, Montastraea cavernosa, Porites australiensis, Porites astreoides, and Porites lobata) into 24 gene families <ref type="table">(Table S4</ref>, See Methods). Based on the gene family phylogeny, each of which contains at least 15 genes (See Data S1), we found that toxic proteins have undergone widespread gene duplications in Cnidaria, and most of the gene duplications occurred in individual species lineages, except for Acropora (Figures 5 and S13-S20). Gene duplications occurred in the most recent common ancestor of Acropora in 9 of 15 gene families, potentially caused by WGD (IAsa). For example, in gene family 1 (coagulation factor X), each species contains $50 genes, except H. magnipapillata and P. astreoides. Gene duplications occurred frequently in individual species lineages: Astreopora sp1, M. cavernosa, N. vectensis, and P. australiensis. Yet, five gene duplications are inferrred to have occurred in the most recent common ancestor of Acropora by WGD ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figure 5</ref>). These results indicated that IAsa potentially contributed to the diversification of proteinaceous toxins in Acropora.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>DISCUSSION</head><p>Ancient WGD is considered as a significant evolutionary factor in the origin and diversification of evolutionary lineages <ref type="bibr">(Soltis et al., 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr">Van De Peer et al., 2017)</ref>, but much work remains to be done to definitively identify WGD and to understand its consequences in different evolutionary lineages. Staghorn corals of the genus Acropora, which constitute the foundation of modern coral reef ecosystems, are hypothesized to have originated through polyploidization <ref type="bibr">(Kenyon, 1997;</ref><ref type="bibr">Renema et al., 2016;</ref><ref type="bibr">Willis et al., 2006)</ref>. However, there is no genetic evidence to support this assertion. To that end, we analyzed the genomes of one Astreopora and five Acropora species to address the possibility of WGD in Acropora and the functional fate of duplicated genes from that event.</p><p>To the best of our knowledge, this is the first study to report genomic-scale evidence of WGD in corals (IAsa). We find that large numbers of ohnologs are retained in Acropora species and hundreds of gene families display phylogenetic duplication topology among the five Acropora species. Meanwhile, our synteny analysis between Astreopora sp1 and A. tenuis directly supports IAsa. However, reconstruction of the  Ancient WGD is usually inferred using the dS-based method, but artificial signals in dS distributions have been reported in previous studies, because of dS saturation (dS value &gt;1) or using poorly annotated genomes or allelic variations or low retention rates <ref type="bibr">(Rabier et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr">Tiley et al., 2016;</ref><ref type="bibr">Vanneste et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Mao, 2019)</ref>. There is an extra peak in the dS distribution of anchor gene pairs in A. digitifera and A. tenuis ( <ref type="figure">Figure S6</ref>). One possible explanation is that the extra peak is artifactual because few anchor gene pairs were used in the analysis. However, this could also indicate a second WGD event in Acropora.</p><p>We found few orthogroups with topologies that fit the two proposed WGD events ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure S21</ref>). In addition, a new ML phylogeny modeling approach was recently developed to overcome shortcomings of the dS-based method <ref type="bibr">(Rabier et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr">Tiley et al., 2016)</ref>. We used it to test whether a second WGD occurred in Acropora. The result showed that one WGD event is the best model in Acropora and that it occurred 30.69-34.69 mya <ref type="table">(Tables S5 and S6</ref>; see Methods). Moreover, we applied the dS-based method on two recently released genomes by other groups (Acropora tenuis and Acropora millepora) (see Methods). We found similar peaks on these two dS distributions of paralogous gene pairs ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure S22</ref>). Together, we have genome-scale evidence to support IAsa, yet, there is no conclusive evidence to support a second WGD in Acropora.</p><p>It is crucial to accurately estimate the timing of a WGD event to understand its evolutionary consequences <ref type="bibr">(Jiao et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr">Vanneste et al., 2014)</ref>. Our study has clearly estimated the timing of IAsa using both phylogenomic analysis and the dS-based method. We suggest that IAsa probably occurred between 28 and 36 mya ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref>). Interestingly, species turnover events usually occurred with extinctions (Jackson and Sax, 2010), and one species turnover event in corals (Oligocene-Miocene transition [OMT]) was suggested to have occurred between 15.97 and 33.7 mya <ref type="bibr">(Edinger and Risk, 1994)</ref>. The timing of IAsa may correspond to a massive extinction of corals created by OMT. This finding supports the hypothesis that WGD may enable organisms to escape extinction during drastic environmental changes (Van De Peer et al., 2017) ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref>).</p><p>The occurrence of IAsa raises the question of what impact it may have had upon coral evolution <ref type="bibr">(Conant et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr">Willis et al., 2006)</ref>. We performed GO analysis on duplicated genes and examined duplicated gene families, showing that duplicated genes following IAsa indeed provided raw genetic material for Acropora to diversify and are potentially crucial for stress responses. In particular, toxin diversification in Acropora was mainly generated by WGD. In addition, we focused on expression patterns of duplicated genes in A. digitifera, showing that expressions of duplicated protein kinases are likely to be correlated during development. A possible explanation may be that protein kinases are probably retained in complex signal transduction pathways via subfunctionalization or dosage effects <ref type="bibr">(Conant et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr">Glasauer and Neuhauss, 2014)</ref>. However, expressions of duplicated membrane proteins are likely uncorrelated because these proteins may have developed different functions via neofunctionalization, such as excitatory amino acid transporters (orthogroup 1244). However, more work is needed to be done to investigate molecular mechanisms of duplicated genes in order to examine these hypotheses in the diversification of Acropora (Yasuoka et al., 2016). For instance, previous gene functional studies have demonstrated that voltagegated sodium channel gene paralogs, duplicated in teleosts, contributed to the acquisition of new electric organs via neofunctionalization in both mormyroid and gymnotiform electric fishes <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Arnegard et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr">Zakon et al., 2006)</ref>.</p><p>Our previous study proposed that adaptive radiation in Acropora was probably driven by introgression <ref type="bibr">(Mao et al., 2018)</ref>; thus Acropora is the first invertebrate lineage reported to have undergone both WGD and introgression. Meanwhile, both introgression and WGD have also been reported in cichlid fish lineages <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Berner and Salzburger, 2015</ref>), a famous model of adaptive radiation in vertebrates <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Berner and Salzburger, 2015</ref>; Seehausen et al., 2014). Both WGD and introgression are regarded as significant forces in adaptive radiation of organisms <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Berner and Salzburger, 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr">Van De Peer et al., 2017</ref>), but we still do not understand the relationship between WGD and introgression in adaptive radiations (Soltis and Soltis, 2009).</p><p>In conclusion, this study identified an ancient WGD shared by Acropora species (IAsa) that not only provides new insights into the evolution of reef-building corals but also expands a new model of WGD in animals.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Limitation of the Study</head><p>Small-scale gene duplication continually occurs within the evolution of organisms <ref type="bibr">(Maere et al., 2005)</ref>, but large-scale gene/genome duplication or entire genome duplication was regarded as a rare evolutionary event in the animals. With advanced increase of genomic data, we observed more and more WGD in animals <ref type="bibr">(Van De Peer et al., 2017)</ref>, such as vertebrates <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Berthelot et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr">Dehal and Boore, 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr">Kenny et al., 2016)</ref>, insects <ref type="bibr">(Li et al., 2018)</ref>, and corals (this study). Yet, it is hard to distinguish large-scale gene/ genome duplication from entire genome duplication using the dS-based method and phylogenomic and synteny analyses without precise genomic data. For example, the second-round WGD has been argued to be large-scale genome duplication rather than entire genome duplication (Smith and Keinath, 2015). Hence, in this study, we defined WGD as large-scale gene/genome duplication. Our evidence from different analyses supports the fact that WGD occurred in the common ancestor of Acropora, but there is still lack of sufficient evidence to support the fact that the WGD is generated by entire genome duplication. In addition, the distribution of inferred age nodes ( <ref type="figure">Figure S8</ref>) was not shown as a standard normal distribution, one possible reason for which is that there is a lack of data in the phylogenomic approach.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>METHODS</head><p>All methods can be found in the accompanying Transparent Methods supplemental file.            <ref type="table">318  119  366  323  306  364  8  8  8  8  8   S K C T</ref>  <ref type="table">501  302  549  430  401  547  13  13  13</ref> 13 13 <ref type="table">681   686  567  538  684  19  19   19</ref> 19                <ref type="table">9  5  7  12  11  13  0  2  5  2  2  0   Gene  family_9   Venom  phosphodiest  erase 2   5  6  6  6   7  1  7  9  3  5  5   Gene  family_1  0   DELTAactitoxin-Aas1a   3  4  5  5  4  3  0  1   1  5  4   Gene family_11    5  2  3  2  2  1  1  1  1  2  1   Gene  family_1  2   Phospholipa  se-B 81   4  2  2  2  3  4  0  3   3  1  1   Gene  family_1  3   Venom  dipeptidyl  peptidase 4   5  2  1  2  2  3  2  4  3  0  0  1   Gene  family_1  4   Hyaluronida  se-1   3  2  2  2  2  2  1  2  2  1  2</ref>  </p><formula xml:id="formula_0">M S ---------------------------GA Q F L V L --------------GK G L F G N F E K SK L N P I P K K K D D V D -R DG SWG V M S E R I S F G S V D F V V S Y HH L R T R R K V L G ------NN L E DC L P DA MM E M F DM E F D F P P R A H C L S R WY G L K E F L V I T P A E D A D T V Y S E S K C H L L L S S I G I A A T N --------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------- M A D G D D E V D E V F E I T D F T T S S EW E R F A A R L EQ L L I E WK L D G T NK K K S T S K G K E L F N N F E K S K L NP I P HK K V E V D E R EG SWG V I S E R I S F G N A N F I V S Y HH L R T R K K SH G K K S K Q T E D L E D C L P H AM M E M F DM E F D F P P R A H C L S R WY G L K E F V V I S P A E D A E A V I T E S K C Q L L L S S I G I A A T N M A D G D D E -------------------------------------------GK E L F N N F E K SK L N P I P H K K V E V D E R EG SWG V I S E R I S F G N A N F I V S Y HH L R T R K K SH G K K S K Q T E D L E D C L P H AM M E M F DM E F D F P P R A H C L S R WY G L K E F V V I S P A E D A E A V I T E S K C Q L L L S S I G I A A T N M A D G D D E -------------------------------------------GK E L F N N F E K SK L N P I P H K K V E V D E R EG SWG V I S E R I S F G N A N F I V S Y HH L R T R K K SH G K K P K Q T ED L E DC L P HA MM E M F DM E F D F P P R A H C L S R WY G L K E F V V I S P A E D A E A V I T E S K C Q L L L S S I G I A A T N M A D G D E G -DE V F E I T D F T T S S EW E R F A A R L EQ L L I E WK L D G T N-KK SA S K GK E L F N N F E K SK L N P I P H K K V E E D E R EG SWG V M S E R I S F G N A N F I V S Y HH L R A R K K SH G K K S K Q T E D L E D C L P H AM M E M F DM E F D F P P R A H C L S R WY G L K E F V V I S P A E D A E A V I T E S K C Q L L L S S I G I A A T N M A ------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------- M A ------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------- M A ------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------- M A ------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------- M A -------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------</formula><formula xml:id="formula_1">V P M F V H T L GQ WR R V Y Y G L C I G G G F R T T F Q I SH L H H I P S H Y GH L A G L L E I FK DK L A C P I S P M H P V T L T V R F T Y V L D E WT DY AWP Q E P P D L S S C L E C T V G V K N L E S L P F G A CQ DP L R E L H L S T T W P C L S E E V I V DN S V Y S D L DP C H A P QW S V R A K M S E N P Q C L L G E Y L G G Y MT LC H R Q E S T ----------------------------------------------------------------M P P V T LT V R F T Y V L N EWA D Y S WP Q E P P DP S S C L E C K V G V S N L K T L P F G A CQ DP L R E L H L S T T W P C L S E E V I V DN S V Y S D L DP C H A P QW S L R A K M S E N P Q C L L G E Y</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>L R GY MT LC H R Q E S T S K C A V P I FA H I LQ Q WR R I Y H G L C I G G G F R T T F HM S Q L R H I P SQ Y G H L A G L L D I FK DK L A C P I S P M P P</head><formula xml:id="formula_2">V T LT V R F T Y V L N EWA D Y S WP Q E P P DP S S C L E C K V G V S N L K T L P F G A CQ DP L R E L H L S T T W P C L S E E V I V DN S V Y S D L DP C H A P QW S L R A K M S E N P Q C L L G E Y</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>L R GY MT LC H R Q E S T S K C A I P I FA H I LQ Q WR R I Y H G L C I G G G F R T T F HM S Q L R H I P SQ Y G H L A G L L D I FK DK L A C P I S P M P P</head><formula xml:id="formula_3">V T LT V R F T Y V L N EWA D Y S WP Q E P P DP S S C L E C K V G V S N L K T L P F G A CQ DP L R E L H L S T T W P C L S E E V I V DN S V Y S D L DP C H A P QW S L R A K M S E N P Q C L L G E Y</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>L R GY MT LC H R Q E S T S K C A I P I FA H I LQ Q WR R I Y H G L C I G G G F R T T F HM S Q L R H I P SQ Y G H L A G L L D I FK DK L A C P I S P M P P</head><formula xml:id="formula_4">V T LT V R F T Y V L N EWA D Y S WP Q E P P DP S S C L E C K V G V S N L K T L P F G A CQ DP L R E L H L S T T W P C L S E E V I V DN S V Y S D L DP C H A P QW S L R A K M S E N P Q C L L ----------------- S K C A I P I FA H V LQ Q WR R I Y H G L C I G G G F R T T F LM S Q L R H I P SQ Y G H L A G L L D I FK DK L A C P I S P M P P V T LT V R F T Y V L N EWT D Y S WP Q E P P DP S S C L E C K V G V S N L K T L P F G A CQ DP L R E L H L S T T W P C L S E E V I V DN S V Y S D L DP C H A P HW S L R A K M S E N P Q C L L G E Y L R GY I T LC H R Q E S T -----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------E M H V ---------------------------------------------Y L ------------- -----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------Q M H V ---------------------------------------------C L ------------- -----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------E M H V ---------------------------------------------Y F ------------- -----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------E M H V ---------------------------------------------Y L ------------- -----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------E M H V ---------------------------------------------Y L -------------</formula><formula xml:id="formula_5">M Q L L NM T AM D D D H N L A D I T H A L Q R L T EA P P V A S L S T A V S R A T SR I S AM G E R S S N E F P I P A N L L S E I L K H L F P D A DQ D L E D L E I AQ Q E L S F D K A E N R K E A K E C N A P Q E K F R S L K SA P E D S L T F F L A V C V C I V Y HN Y G G L R A V A H L WQ E F V L EM R Y R W E N D I F I P R L K L Q A P N L G S C L V HQ K L Q M M Q L L K N T L MD D D H N L A D I T H A L Q R L T EA P P V A S L S S A V S R A T SR I S A I GD S S L D E Y P I P G K L L S E I L Q H L F P D A DQ N L E D L E T VQ Q E L L F A K M E S E N D A K E E N I QQ DK F R S L K S A P ED S L T F F L A V G I C I V Y H S Y G G L K A V A H L WQ E F V L EM R F R W E N D I F I P R L K L Q A P N L G S C L L HQ K L Q M M Q L L K N T V MD D D H N L A D I T H A L Q R L T EA P P V A S L S S A V S R A T SR I S A I GD S S L D E Y P I P G K L L S E I L Q H L F P D A DQ D L E D L E T AQ Q E L L F A K M E S E N D A K E E N I QQ DK F R S L K S A P ED S L T F F L A V G I C I V Y H S Y G G L K A V A H L WQ E F V L EM R F R W E N D I F I P R L K L Q A P S L G S C L L HQ K L Q M M Q L L K N T L MD D D H N L A D I T H A L Q R L T EA P P V A S L S S A V S R A T SR I S AM G D S S L D E Y P I P G K L L S E I L Q H L F P D A DQ D L E D L E T VQ Q E L L F A K M E S E N D A K E E T I Q ----------------------------------------------------------------------------Q M ------------DN L A D I T H A L Q R L T EA P P V A S L S S A V S R A T SR I S A I GD S S L D E Y P I P G K L L S E I L Q H L F P D A DQ D L E D L E T VQ Q E L L F A K M E S E N D A K E E N I Q ----------------------------------------------------------------------------Q M M Q L L K N T L V D D D H N L A D I T H A L Q R L T EA P P V A S L S S A V S R A T SR I S A L G D S S S D E Y P I P G K L L S E I L Q H L F P D A DQ D L E D L E T AQ Q E L L F A K M E S E N E A K E E N I QQ DK F R S L K S A P ED S L T F F L A V G I C I V Y H S Y G G L K A V A H L WQ E F V L EM R Y R W E N D I F I P R L K L Q A P N L G S C L L HQ K L Q M --------------------------------------------V S A L --------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------V --------------------------------------------V S A L --------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------V --------------------------------------------V S A L --------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------V --------------------------------------------V S A L --------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------V --------------------------------------------V S A L --------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------V</formula><formula xml:id="formula_6">L NC C I ER K R L S K I R T A S LQ F A T N L S K T ---RT E S N V T N A E K V R R N S S N T R L G S T D S Q S S V S D D E E F F E A V E SQ E E S E T E S G N N T E N F K N I R GT D S DY NM D N S C S G N N T I FC K R EG G K E P F G D L K L L V S G E P L I V P I TQ E P A P MT EDM L E E Q A E I LT Q L G T SV E G A R V R AQ MQ C A S L L S DM E A F L NC C I ER K R L S K I R T A S LQ F S T N V N K N S G T R I P N N T S NM E S S R K SD S N T R L E S T G S Q S S I SD D E E F F E A L E NQ D E S E K E T R NY F E N F N I EG K T N S D S D I EN S N E N N A S M Y -K R E G G K E L F G D L K L L V S G E P L V V P I TQ --------------------------------------------- L NC C I ER K R L S K I R T A S LQ F S T N V N K N S G T R I P N N T S NM E S S R K SD S N T R L E S T G S Q S S I SD D E E F F E A L E NQ D E N E K E T R K Y F E N F N I K G K T N S D S D I EN S N D N N A S M Y -K R E G G K E L F G D L K L L V S G E P L V V P I TQ --------------------------------------------- L NC C I ER K R L S K I R T A S LQ F S T N I N K N S G R R I P N N T S NM E S S R K SD S N K R L E S T G S Q S S I SD D E E F F E A L E NQ D E S E K E A R NY F E N F N I EG K T K S D S D I EN S N D N N A S M Y -K R E G G K E L F G D L K L L V S G E P L V V P I TQ --------------------------------------------- L NC C I ER K R L S K I R T A S LQ F S T N I N K N S G R R I P N N T S NM E S S R K SD S N T R L E S T G S Q S S I SD D E E F F E A L E NQ D E S E K E T R NY F E N F N I EG K T N S D S D I EN S N D N N A S M Y -K R E G G K E L F G D L K L L V S G E P L V V P I TQ --------------------------------------------- L NC C I ER K R L S K I R T A S LQ F S T N V N K N S G T R I P N N T S NM E S C R K SD S N T R L E S T G S Q S S I SD D E E F F E A L E NQ D E N E K E T R NY F E N F N I EG K T N S D S D I EN S N D N N A S M S -K R E G G R E L F G D L K L L V S G E P L V V P I TQ --------------------------------------------- L S C C L Q --------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------- L S C C L Q --------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------- L S C C L Q --------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------- L S C C L Q --------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------- L S C C L Q --------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------- 864 475 722 603 574 720 K A A N P GC L L E D F V R WY S P F DW I L G P ET E E E I E E L K K L K T SH E K D S K E S S T P V T A A T S E V S L D E GWD T E E I E I P D E D F T T SD A K S L MA K A K A G N V E E LQ V P I K WR E E G H L S V R MR I P GNMWA E V WQ S A R P V P V R R Q K R L F D E T K E A E K E P A P M T EDM L E E Q A E I LT Q L G T SV E G A R V R AQ MQ C A ---------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------E P A P M T EDM L E E Q A E I LT Q L G T SV E G A R V</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>S L L S DM E A F K A A N P GC L L E D F V R WY S P F DW I L G P ET E E E I E E L E K L K T SH E K D S K E S S T P V T A A T S E V S L D E GWD T E E I E I P D E D F T T SD A K S L MA K A K A G N V E E LQ V P I K WR E E G H L S I R MR I P GN M WA E V WQ S A R P</head><formula xml:id="formula_7">V P V R R Q K R L F D E T K E A E K V L H F L A G L K P A E V A F Q L F P V L L H A A V L S L L S DM E A F K A A N P GC L L E D F V R WY S P F DW I L G P ET Q E E I E E L E R L K N N A E K A S E E P ST P V A A T V S E A S F G E GWD T E E I E I A D E D L V S K D A K S L MN E A K A G N L DQ L Q A P A K WR E E G H L S L R M R I P GN M WV E V WQ S A R P V P V R R Q K R L F D E T K E A E K V L H F L A GM K P A E V A F Q L F P V L L R A A V L S L L S DM E A F K A A N P GC L L E D F V R WY S P F DW I L G P ET Q E E I E E L E R L K N N A E K A S E E P ST R V A A T V S E A S F G E GWD T E E I E I A D E D L V S K D A K S L MN E A K A G N L DQ L Q A P A K WR E E G H L S L R M R I P GN M WV E V WQ S A R P V P V R R Q K R L F D E T K E A E K V L H F L A GM K P A E V A F Q L F P V L L R A A V L S L L S DM E A F K A A N P GC L L E D F V R WY S P F DW I L G P ET Q E E I E E L E R L K N N A E K A S E E P SR P V A A T V S E A S F G E GWD T E E I E I A D E D L V S K D A K S L MN E A K A G N L DQ L Q A P A K WR E E G H L S L R M R I P GN M WV E V WQ S A R P V P V R R Q K R L F D E T K E A E K V L H F L A GM K P A E V A F Q L F P V L L R A A V L S L L S DM E A F K A A N P GC L L E D F V R WY S P F DW I L G P ET Q E V I E E L E R L K N N A E K A S E E P SR P V A A T V S E A S F G E GWD T E E I E I A D E D L V S K D A K S L MN E A K A G N L DQ L Q A P A K WR E E G H L S L R M R I P GN M WV E V WQ S A R P V P V R R Q K R L F D E T K E A E K V L H F L A GM K P A E V A F Q L F P V L L R A A V L S L L S DM E A F K A A N P GC L L E D F V R WY S P F DW I L G P ET Q E E I E E L E R L K N N A E K G S E E P SR P V E A T V S E V S F G E GWD T E E I E I A D E D L V S K D A K S L MN E A K A G N L DQ L Q A P A K WR E E G H L S H R M R I P GN T WV E V WQ S A R P V P V R RQ K R L F D E T K E A E K V L H F L A GM K P A E V A F Q L F P V L L R A A V</formula><formula xml:id="formula_8">R I E E A G A R D I P A V A S L L DK V L E K A S K L SWA M P Q D L L L C E E F V K Q LQ L C E L V V A R A H S L R F K F Q D A L S D K E T G T D K D V E H F L S A L M E K P EV A V I G A G R G P A G R V L H G L F A K Q E S A R M Q F T V D E S S -PN Q A V ---A F R E Q P I A H P SM S K E Q V G N K I T R R D F Y A I L G V P R DA N K NQ I K R A Y R K L AM R I E E A G A R D I P A V A F L L DK V L DK A S K L SW EM P Q D L T Q C E E F V K Q LQ L C E L V V A R A N S L R Y K F Q D A L V -KG T E T D K D V E H F L S A L M E K P EV T V I G A G R G P A G R V L H S L F V</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>K Q E S A R M Q F G G D E S P F P NQ Q Q R H S A T LP Q D F P SP ---------T G R E Y I LR T T I P R P R P S S R P C P Q R MY SV L T -R I E E A G A R D I</head><formula xml:id="formula_9">P A V A F L L DK V L DK A S K L SW EM P Q D L T Q C E E F V K Q LQ L C E L V V A R A N S L R Y K F Q D A L L -KG T E T D K D V E H F L S A L M E K P EV T V I G A G R G P A G R V L H S L F V</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>K Q E S A R M Q F G G D E S P F R NQ Q Q R H S A T LP Q D F P SP ---------T G R E Y I LR T T I P R P R P S S R P C P Q R MY C V L T -R I E E A G A R D I</head><formula xml:id="formula_10">P A V A F L L DK V L DK A S K L SW EM P Q D L T Q C E E F V K Q LQ L C E L V V A R A N S L R Y K F Q D A L L -KG T E T D K D V</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>E H F L S A L M E K P EV T V I G A G R G P A G R ----------S A R MQ F G G D E S P F P NQ Q Q R H S A T LP Q D F P SP ---------T G R E Y I LR T T I P R P R P S S R P C P Q R MY C V L T -R I E E A G A R D I</head><formula xml:id="formula_11">P A V A F L L DK V L DK A S K L SW EM P Q D L T Q C E E F V K Q LQ L C E L V V A R A N S L R Y K F Q D A L L -KG T E T D K D V E H F L S A L M E K P EV T V I G A G R G P A G R V L H S L F V K Q E S A R M Q F G G D E T P F P NQ Q V --SW F R SC F F A L L V Y L I R ND D A T V K E N D Y R I V I SA I T GN S H P P I P P C L R A L N I R I E E A G A R D I P A V A F L L DK V L DK A S K L SW EM P Q D L T Q C E E F V K Q LQ L C E L V V A R A H S L R Y K F H D A L V -KG T E T D K D V E H F L S A L M E K P EV T V I G A G R G P A G R V L H G L F V K Q E S A R M Q F G G D E S P F P NQ Q Q R H S A T LP Q D F P SP ---------T G R E Y I LR T T I P R P R P S S R P C P Q R MY C V L T - --------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------I LA G R D F Y A I L G V P R DA N K NQ I K R A Y R K L AM --------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------I LA G R D F Y A I L G V P R DA N K NQ I K R A Y R K L AM --------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------I LA G R D F Y A I L G V P R DA N K NQ I K R A Y R K L AM --------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------I LA G R D F Y A I L G V P R DA N K NQ I K R A Y R K L AM --------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------I LA G R D F Y A I L G V P R DA N K NQ I K R A Y R K L</formula><formula xml:id="formula_12">K WH P D K N K E DP K A Q E R F Q D L S A A Y E V L T D E E K R R T Y D S H G E E G L K NM N S G G G D P F D P F S --------------------S F F G G F G F H F E G S Q H S HQ R EV P R G S D I HM D L E V T L E E L Y NG N F I E V L R F K P V T ET V P GT RQ C N C R Q E M R T T Q L G P GR FQ M S P V D I C D E C P A V T Y V T K E K L L E V E -----------------------------------------------N-------DE F R ---L A G --------------A F T D D V I FQ ----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------- -----------------------------------------------N-------DE F R ---L A G --------------A F T D D V I FQ ----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------- -----------------------------------------------N-------DE F R ---L A G --------------A F T D D V I FQ ----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------- I S F P --------------F L S A ---------------------------------A S F S -Y A T P G ----------L P I -P YW S G V Y F E -----N N H ---------------------------------------------------------------------PQ T P A ------------- -----------------------------------------------N-------DE F R ---L A G --------------A F T D D V I FQ ----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------- K WH P D K N K D D P K AQ E R FQ D L S A A Y E V L T D E E K R R T Y DT HG E E G L K NM N S G G G D P F D P F S --------------------S F F G G F G F H F E G A Q H S HQ R EV P R G S D I NM D L E V T L E E L Y NG N F I E V S R F K P V K E T I S G T R K C N C R Q E M R T T Q L G P GR FQ M S P V D I C D E C P A V T Y V T K E K L L E V E K WH P D K N K E DP K A Q E R F Q D L S A A Y E V L T D E E K R R T Y DT HG E E G L K NM N S G G G D P F D P F S R F V F S G F L T K I A E G S R L E L C T F F G G F G F H F E G A Q H S HQ R EV P R G S D I NM D L E V T L E E L Y NG N F I E V S R F K P V K E T I S G T R K C N C R Q E M R T T Q L G P GR FQ M S P V D I C D E C P A V T Y V T K E K L L E V E K WH P D K N K E DP K A Q E R F Q D L S A A Y E V L T D E E K R R T Y DT HG E E G L K NM N S G G G D P F D P F S --------------------S F F G G F G F H F E G A Q H S HQ R EV P R G S D I NM D L E V T L E E L Y NG N F I E V S R F K P V K E T I S G T R K C N C R Q E M R T T Q L G P GR FQ M S P V D I C D E C P A V T Y V T K E K L L E V E K WH P D K N K E DP K A Q E R F Q D L S A A Y E V L T D E E K R R T Y DT HG E E G L K NM N S G G G D P F D P F S --------------------S F F G G F G F H F E G A Q H S HQ R EV P R G S D I NM D L E V T L E E L Y NG N F I E V S R F K P V K E T I S G T R K C N C R Q E M R T T Q L G P GR FQ M S P V D I C D E C P A V T Y V T K E K L L E V E K WH P D K N K E DP K A Q E R F Q D L S A A Y E V L T D E E K R R T Y DT HG E E G L K NM N S G G G D P F D P F S --------------------S F F G G F G F H F E G A Q H S HQ R EV P R G S D I NM D L E V T L E E L Y NG N F I E V S R F K P V K E T I S G T R K C N C R Q E M R T T Q L G P GR FQ M S P V D I C D E C P A V T Y V T K E K L L E V</formula><formula xml:id="formula_13">I EP GM H D GQ E Y P F I A E G E P H I D G E P G D L K F M I R E L R H E R F Q R K G D D L Y T N V T I T LV DA L N G F EM D I L H L DG H K V H V V R E K I TWP G A R I K K K E E GM P NY EN N N V K GD L Y I T FD V E F P R G G L E D S E K E A L K S I L K Q D S Q Q K A Y N G L ------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------ ------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------ ------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------ ------------------------------------------------------L I S P L S S -------------------------------------------------------------------KN V L C A DQ R ------- ------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------ I EP GM H D GQ E Y P F V A E G E P H V D G E P G D L K F I I K E L R HD R F Q R K G D D L Y T N V T V T L L DA L N G F EM D I L H L DG H K V H V V</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>R E K I TWP G A K I K K K E E GM P NY EN N N I K G D L Y I T F D I A F P R GG L E DN D K E A L K N I L K Q S P NQ K A Y N G L I EP GM H D GQ E Y P F V A E G E P H</head><formula xml:id="formula_14">V D G E P G D L K F I I K E L R HD R F Q R K G D D L Y T N V T V T L L DA L N G F EM D I L H L DG H K V H V V</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>R E K I TWP G A K I K K K E E GM P NY EN N N I K G D L Y I T F D I A F P R GG L E DN D K E A L K N I L K Q S P NQ K A Y N G L I EP GM H D GQ E Y P F V A E G E P H</head><formula xml:id="formula_15">V D G E P G D L K F I I K E L R HD R F Q R K G D D L Y T N V T V T L L DA L N G F EM D I L H L DG H K V H V V</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>R E K I TWP G A R I K K K E E GM P NY EN N N I K G D L Y I T F D I E F P R GG L E DN D K E A L K D I L K Q S P NQ K A Y N G L I EP GM H D GQ E Y P F V A E G E P H</head><formula xml:id="formula_16">V D G E P G D L K F I I K E L R HD R F Q R K G D D L Y T N V T V T L L DA L N G F EM D I L H L DG H K V H V V</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>R E K I TWP G A R I K K K E E GM P NY EN N N I K G D L Y I T F D I E F P R GG L E DN D K E G W ---YK S S I S -------I EP GM H D GQ E Y P F V A E G E P H I D G E P G D L K F I I K E L R HD</head><formula xml:id="formula_17">R F Q R K G D D L Y T N V T V T L L DA L N G F EM D I L H L DG H K V H V V</formula></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Ancient WGD in the Reef-Building Coral Acropora (IAsa)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Ancient WGD Identification (IAsa) and Timing of the Event in Acropora (A) Frequency distribution of dS values for paralogous gene pairs in five Acropora and one Astreopora species showing that a WGD event occurred in Acropora. Similar peaks (dS value: 0.1-0.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Duplicated Genes under Subfunctionalization or Neofunctionalization are shown with phylogenetic trees. (A) The phylogeny of orthogroup 1247 (dnaJ homolog subfamily B member 11-like) reconstructed with MrBayes shows a duplicated gene under subfunctionalization. Bayesian posterior probabilities are shown at each node. The bottom right panel shows that two domains are in Astreopora sp1, but each domain was independently lost in duplicated genes under subfunctionalization in orthogroup 1247.ancestral karyotype will necessitate the assemblage of genomes to the chromosome level to fully understand gene fractionation and chromosome rearrangements in Acropora under IAsa(Smith and Keinath,  2015; Smith et al., 2013).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Continued (B) The phylogeny of orthogroup 1244 (excitatory amino acid transporter 1-like) reconstructed with MrBayes shows a duplicated gene under neofunctionalization. Bayesian posterior probabilities are shown at each node. Six transmembrane helices prediction is shown at the bottom right. See alsoFigures S11 and S12.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Gene Expression Profiling Reveals Evolution of Duplicated Genes in A. digitifera (A) Gene expression profiling across five developmental stages (blastula, PC; gastrula, G; postgastrula, S; planula, P; and adult polyps, A) in A. digitifera. Two clusters of gene expression of ohnologous gene pairs: HC, high correlation: p &lt; 0.05; NC, no correlation: p R 0.05 (Pearson's correlation test). Pearson's correlation coefficients between two ohnologous gene pairs are presented in the right panel, and lines represent average values of correlation coefficients in each cluster. (B) Significant functional enrichments of two clusters of ohnolog gene pairs (p &lt; 0.05, Fisher's exact test) indicate that divergence of gene expression is associated with gene functions. Colors of the bar represent fold change values in enrichments. (C) Boxplot of dN/dS values of ohnologous gene pairs shows no significant difference between the two clusters (p = 0.51, Mann-Whitney test).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Diversification of Toxic Proteins via Gene Duplications in CnidariaPhylogenetic analysis of Coagulation factor X in 12 cnidarian species shows wide gene duplications. Gene duplication occurred in individual species lineages (red arrows), and gene duplications by WGD in Acropora are indicated with blue arches. Outer color strips represent 12 cnidarian species, and black strip represents non-cnidarian species. Bootstrap values greater than 50 are shown with black dots at nodes. See also Figures S13-S20 andTable S4. Blomme, T.,Vandepoele, K., De Bodt, S.,  Simillion, C., Maere, S., and Van de Peer, Y. (2006). The gain and loss of genes during 600 million years of vertebrate evolution. Genome Biol. 7, R43.Bowers, J.E.,Chapman, B.A., Rong, J., and  Paterson, A.H. (2003). Unravelling angiosperm genome evolution by phylogenetic analysis of chromosomal duplication events.Nature 422,  433-438.   Canestro, C., Albalat, R., Irimia, M., and Garcia- Fernà ndez, J. (2013). Impact of gene gains, losses and duplication modes on the origin and diversification of vertebrates. Semin. Cell Dev. Biol. 24, 83-94.Chen, Z.J., and Birchler, J.A. (2013). Polyploid and Hybrid Genomics (John Wiley &amp; Sons). Christoffels, A.,Koh, E.G.L., Chia, J.M., Brenner,  S., Aparicio, S., and Venkatesh, B. (2004). Fugu genome analysis provides evidence for a wholegenome duplication early during the evolution of ray-finned fishes.Mol. Biol. Evol. 21, 1146-1151.   Conant, G.C., Birchler, J.A., and Pires, J.C. (2014. Dosage, duplication, and diploidization: clarifying the interplay of multiple models for duplicate gene evolution over time.Curr. Opin.  Plant Biol. 19, 91-98.   Dehal, P., and Boore, J.L. (2005). Two rounds of whole genome duplication in the ancestral vertebrate. PLoS Biol. 3, 1700-1708.Edinger, E.N., and Risk, M.J. (1994). Oligocene miocene extinction and geographic restriction of caribbean corals -roles of turbidity, temperature, and nutrients. Palaios 9, 576-598. Fujikawa, T., Munakata, T.,Kondo, S., Satoh, N.,  and Wada, S. (2010). Stress response in the ascidian Ciona intestinalis: transcriptional profiling of genes for the heat shock protein 70 chaperone system under heat stress and endoplasmic reticulum stress. Cell StressChaperon 15, 193-204.   Fukami, H., Omori, M., and Hatta, M. (2000). Phylogenetic relationships in the coral family Acroporidae, reassessed by inference from mitochondrial genes. Zoolog. Sci. 17, 689-696.Fü rthauer, M.,Thisse, B., and Thisse, C. (1999). Three different noggin genes antagonize the activity of bone morphogenetic proteins in the zebrafish embryo. Dev.Biol. 214,[181][182][183][184][185][186][187][188][189][190][191][192][193][194][195][196] Gacesa, R., Chung, R., Dunn, S.R., Weston, A.J., Jaimes-Becerra, A., Marques, A.C., Morandini, A.C., Hranueli, D.,Starcevic, A., Ward, M., et al.  (2015). Gene duplications are extensive and contribute significantly to the toxic proteome of nematocysts isolated from Acropora digitifera (Cnidaria: Anthozoa: Scleractinia). BMC Genomics 16, 774.Glasauer, S.M.K., and Neuhauss, S.C.F. (2014). Whole-genome duplication in teleost fishes and its evolutionary consequences. Mol. Genet. Genomics 289, 1045-1060. Goodwin, S., McPherson, J.D., and McCombie, W.R. (2016). Coming of age: ten years of nextgeneration sequencing technologies. Nat. Rev. Genet. 17, 333-351. Hamada, M., Shoguchi, E., Shinzato, C., Kawashima, T., Miller, D.J., and Satoh, N. (2013). The complex NOD-like receptor repertoire of the coral Acropora digitifera includes novel domain combinations. Mol. Biol. Evol. 30, 167-176. Hardwick, S.A., Deveson, I.W., and Mercer, T.R. (2017). Reference standards for next-generation sequencing. Nat. Rev. Genet. 18, 473. Hargreaves, A.D., Swain, M.T., Hegarty, M.J., Logan, D.W., and Mulley, J.F. (2014). Restriction and recruitment-gene duplication and the origin and evolution of snake venom toxins. Genome Biol. Evol. 6, 2088-2095. Jackson, S.T., and Sax, D.F. (2010). Balancing biodiversity in a changing environment: extinction debt, immigration credit and species turnover. Trends Ecol. Evol. 25, 153-160. Jiao, Y.N., Wickett, N.J., Ayyampalayam, S., Chanderbali, A.S., Landherr, L., Ralph, P.E., Tomsho, L.P., Hu, Y., Liang, H.Y., Soltis, P.S., et al. (2011). Ancestral polyploidy in seed plants and angiosperms. Nature 473, 97-U113. Kassahn, K.S., Dang, V.T., Wilkins, S.J., Perkins, A.C., and Ragan, M.A. (2009). Evolution of gene function and regulatory control after wholegenome duplication: comparative analyses in vertebrates. Genome Res. 19, 1404-1418. Kenny, N.J., Chan, K.W., Nong, W., Qu, Z., Maeso, I., Yip, H.Y., Chan, T.F., Kwan, H.S., Holland, P.W.H., Chu, K.H., et al. (2016). Ancestral whole-genome duplication in the marine chelicerate horseshoe crabs. Heredity 119, 388. Kenyon, J.C. (1997). Models of reticulate evolution in the coral genus Acropora based on chromosome numbers: parallels with plants. Evolution 51, 756-767. Kondrashov, F.A. (2012). Gene duplication as a mechanism of genomic adaptation to a changing environment. Proc. Biol. Sci. 279, 5048-5057. Kordi s, D., and Guben sek, F. (2000). Adaptive evolution of animal toxin multigene families. Gene 261, 43-52. Li, Z., Tiley, G.P., Galuska, S.R., Reardon, C.R., Kidder, T.I., Rundell, R.J., and Barker, M.S. (2018). Multiple large-scale gene and genome duplications during the evolution of hexapods. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U S A 115, 4713-4718. Lynch, M., and Conery, J.S. (2000). The evolutionary fate and consequences of duplicate genes. Science 290, 1151-1155. Mao, Y. (2019). GenoDup Pipeline: a tool to detect genome duplication using the dS-based method. PeerJ 7, e6303. Mao, Y., Economo, E.P., and Satoh, N. (2018). The roles of introgression and climate change in the rise to dominance of Acropora Corals. Curr. Biol. 28, 3373-3382. Maere, S., De Bodt, S., Raes, J., Casneuf, T., Van Montagu, M., Kuiper, M., and Van de Peer, Y. (2005). Modeling gene and genome duplications in eukaryotes. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U S A 102, 5454-5459. Marcet-Houben, M., and Gabaldó n, T. (2015). Beyond the whole-genome duplication: phylogenetic evidence for an ancient interspecies hybridization in the baker's yeast lineage. PLoS Biol. 13, e1002220.Nakatani, Y.,Takeda, H., Kohara, Y., and  Morishita, S. (2007). Reconstruction of the vertebrate ancestral genome reveals dynamic genome reorganization in early vertebrates. GenomeRes. 17, 1254-1265.   Rabier, C.E., Ta, T., and Ane, C. (2014. Detecting and locating whole genome duplications on a phylogeny: a probabilistic approach. Mol.Biol.  Evol. 31, 750-762.   Renema, W., Bellwood, D.R., Braga, J.C.,  Bromfield, K., Hall, R., Johnson, K.G., Lunt, P.,  Meyer, C.P., McMonagle, L.B., Morley, R.J., et al.  (2008). Hopping hotspots: global shifts in marine biodiversity. Science 321, 654-657.Renema, W., Pandolfi, J.M.,Kiessling, W.,  Bosellini, F.R., Klaus, J.S., Korpanty, C., Rosen,  B.R., Santodomingo, N., Wallace, C.C., and  Webster, J.M. (2016). Are coral reefs victims of their own past success? Sci. Adv. 2, e1500850.Reyes-Bermudez, A., Villar-Briones, A.,Ramirez- Portilla, C., Hidaka, M., and Mikheyev, A.S. (2016). Developmental progression in the coral Acropora digitifera is controlled by differential expression of distinct regulatory gene networks.Genome Biol. Evol. 8, 851-870. Richards, Z.T., and Hobbs, J.P.A. (2015). Hybridisation on coral reefs and the conservation of evolutionary novelty. Curr. Zool. 61, 132-145. Richards, Z.T., Miller, D.J., and Wallace, C.C. (2013). Molecular phylogenetics of geographically restricted Acropora species: implications for threatened species conservation. Mol. Phylogenet. Evol. 69, 837-851.Schwager, E.E., Sharma, P.P., Clarke, T.,Leite,  D.J., Wierschin, T., Pechmann, M., Akiyama-Oda,  Y., Esposito, L., Bechsgaard, J., Bilde, T., et al.  (2017). The house spider genome reveals an ancient whole-genome duplication during arachnid evolution. BMC Biol. 15, 62.Seehausen, O., Butlin, R.K., Keller, I., Wagner, C.E., Boughman, J.W., Hohenlohe, P.A., Peichel, C.L., Saetre, G.P., Bank, C.,Brannstrom, A., et al.  (2014). Genomics and the origin of species. Nat.Rev. Genet. 15, 176-192.   Sé mon, M., and Wolfe, K.H. (2007). Consequences of genome duplication. Curr. Opin. Genet. Dev. 17, 505-512. Smith, J.J., and Keinath, M.C. (2015). The sea lamprey meiotic map improves resolution of ancient vertebrate genome duplications. GenomeRes. 25, 1081-1090.   Smith, J.J., Kuraku, S., Holt, C., Sauka-Spengler,  T., Jiang, N., Campbell, M.S., Yandell, M.D.,  Manousaki, T., Meyer, A., Bloom, O.E., et al.  (2013. Sequencing of the sea lamprey(Petromyzon marinus) genome provides insights into vertebrate evolution. Nat. Genet. 45, 415-421. Soltis, D.E., Albert, V.A., Leebens-Mack, J., Bell, C.D., Paterson, A.H., Zheng, C., Sankoff, D., Pamphilis, C.W., Wall, P.K., and Soltis, P.S. (2009). Polyploidy and angiosperm diversification. Am. J. Bot. 96, 336-348. Soltis, P.S., Marchant, D.B., Van de Peer, Y., and Soltis, D.E. (2015). Polyploidy and genome evolution in plants. Curr. Opin. Genet. Dev. 35, 119-125. Soltis, P.S., and Soltis, D.E. (2009). The role of hybridization in plant speciation. Annu. Rev. Plant Biol. 60, 561-588. Soltis, P.S., and Soltis, D.E. (2012). Polyploidy and Genome Evolution (Springer).Stuber, C.W., andGoodman, M.M. (1983). Inheritance, intracellular localization, and genetic variation of phosphoglucomutase isozymes in maize (Zea mays L.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Figure S2 .</head><label>S2</label><figDesc>events in evolution of the animal clade. Related to Figure 1. The backbone and divergence time of the tree are based on various sources (e.g., Satoh, 2016). The shaded grey oval represents the uncertain position of two rounds of WGD and colored triangles represent the corresponding divergent groups. Grey triangles represent WGDs and the red star represents invertebrate WGD specific to Acropora (IAsα) reported in this study. Flowchart of study design. Related to Figures 2-5. The flowchart illustrates methods used to test the main questions in this study.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Figure S3 .</head><label>S3</label><figDesc>Venn diagrams of gene families in six Acroporid species. Related to Figure 1. (A). Venn diagram of shared and unique gene families in six Acroporid species. (B). Venn diagram of shared and unique gene families between Astreopora sp1 and A. tenuis. (C). The table of the number of unique gene family in six Acroporid species.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Figure S4 .</head><label>S4</label><figDesc>Phylogeny of the Family Acroporidae. Related to Figure 1. Timecalibrated phylogenetic tree reconstructed based on fossil calibration and concatenated coding sequences (7,467,066 bp in total) from 3,461 single-copy orthologous genes with BEAST2. Branch lengths are scaled to estimated-divergence time. Posterior 95% CIs of node ages are represented with blue horizontal bars as well as ML bootstrap values and Bayesian posterior probabilities are shown at each node.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Figure S5 .</head><label>S5</label><figDesc>Frequency distributions of dS values for paralogous gene pairs in five Acropora and one Astreopora species. Related to Figure 2. The distributions of dS values of paralogs, estimating neutral evolutionary divergence since the two paralogs diverged, are plotted with a bin size of 0.005, showing the similar peaks (dS value: 0-0.3) in Acropora.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Figure S6 .Figure S7 .Figure S8 .</head><label>S6S7S8</label><figDesc>Frequency distributions of dS values for anchor-gene pairs in five Acropora and one Astreopora species. Related to Figure 2. Distributions of dS values of anchor paralogs, estimating the neutral evolutionary divergence times since the paralogs diverged, are plotted with a bin size of 0.01, showing the similar peaks (dS value: 0-0.3, red boxes) in Acropora and extra peaks in A. digitifera and A. tenuis (dS value: 0.3-0.5, blue boxes). Frequency distributions of dS values for paralogous genes in Acropora and for orthologous genes. Related to Figure 2. (A) Frequency distribution of dS values for paralogous genes in Acropora and for orthologous genes showing that a WGD event occurred in the most recent common ancestor of Acropora. Distributions are plotted with a bin size of 0.01. (B) Frequency distribution of log dS values for paralogous genes in Acropora and for orthologous genes. Distributions are plotted with a bin size of 0.05. Node age distribution of IAsα. Related to Figure 2. Inferred node ages from 135 phylogenies were analyzed with KDE toolbox to show the peak at 30.78 My, represented by the black solid line. The grey lines represent density estimations from 1000 bootstraps and the black dotted line represents the corresponding 95% confidence interval (27.86 -34.77 My) from 100 bootstraps.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head>Figure S9 .</head><label>S9</label><figDesc>Synteny blocks between Astreopora sp1 and A. tenuis. Related to Figure 2. Only co-linear segments with at least 8 anchor pairs are shown in between the top length 100 scaffolds of Astreopora sp1 (Left side) and the top length 200 scaffolds of A. tenuis (Bottom). Only the scaffolds of Astreopora sp1 representing duplicated segments with A. tenuis are shown. The duplicated segments on different scaffolds are covered with red boxes. The duplicated segments on the same scaffolds are marked with red arrows.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head>Figure S10 .</head><label>S10</label><figDesc>An example of synteny blocks between Astreopora sp1 and the five Acropora species. Related to Figure 2. Only co-linear segments with at least 8 anchor pairs are shown in between the longest scaffolds of Astreopora sp1 (Left side) and scaffolds of other five Acropora species (Bottom). The red box represents the retained the duplicated segments.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_13"><head>Figure S11 .</head><label>S11</label><figDesc>Alignment of orthogroup 1247 (dnaJ homolog subfamily B member 11-like) showing the independent loss of the domain in duplicates. Related to Figure 3.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_14"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>R AQ MQ S A ---------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------E P A P M T EDM L E E Q A E I LT Q L G T SV E G A R V R AQ MQ S A ---------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------E P A P M T EDM L E E Q A E I LT Q L G T SV E G A R V R AQ MQ S A ---------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------E P A P M T EDM L E E Q A E I LT Q L G T SV E G A R V R AQ MQ S A ---------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------E P A P M T EDM L E E Q A E I LT Q L G T SV E G A R VR AQ MQ S A ------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_15"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>L ------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_16"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>R E K I TWP G A R I K K K E E GM P NY EN NN I K G D L Y I T F D I E F P R GG L E DN D K E A L K N I L K Q S P NQ K T Y N G LFigure S12. Alignment of orthogroup 1244 (excitatory amino acid transporter 1like) showing mutations on transmembrane and exposed regions, suggesting that new functions would be generated. Related toFigure 3. Exposed regions are shown in yellow.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_17"><head>Figure S13 .</head><label>S13</label><figDesc>Phylogeny of the toxic protein, Ryncolin-4. Related to Figure 5. The phylogeny was reconstructed using ExaML and bootstrap values are shown at each node. Gene duplications caused by WGD in Acropora are shown in cyan.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_18"><head>Figure S14 .</head><label>S14</label><figDesc>Phylogeny of the toxic Astacin-like metalloprotease. Related to Figure 5. The phylogeny was reconstructed using ExaML and bootstrap values are shown at each node. Gene duplication caused by WGD in Acropora is shown in cyan.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_19"><head>Figure S15 .</head><label>S15</label><figDesc>Phylogeny of a toxic protein (Putative lysosomal acid lipase/ cholesteryl ester hydrolase). Related to Figure 5. The phylogeny was reconstructed using RAxML and bootstrap values are shown at each node. Gene duplications caused by WGD in Acropora are shown in cyan shadows.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_20"><head>Figure S16 .</head><label>S16</label><figDesc>Phylogeny of the toxic putative endothelial lipase. Related to Figure 5. The phylogeny was reconstructed using RAxML and bootstrap values are shown at each node. Gene duplications caused by WGD in Acropora is shown in cyan.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_21"><head>Figure S17 .</head><label>S17</label><figDesc>Phylogeny of the toxin protein (DELTA-thalatoxin-Avl2a/DELTAalicitoxin-Pse2a). Related to Figure 5. The phylogeny was reconstructed using RAxML and bootstrap values are shown at each node. Gene duplication by WGD in Acropora is shown in cyan.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_22"><head>Figure S18 .</head><label>S18</label><figDesc>Phylogeny of the toxic protein (DELTA-actitoxin-Aas1a). Related to Figure 5. The phylogeny was reconstructed using RAxML and bootstrap values are shown at each node. Gene duplication by WGD in Acropora is shown in cyan.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_23"><head>Figure S19 .</head><label>S19</label><figDesc>Phylogeny of the toxic protein (Phospholipase-B 81). Related to Figure 5. The phylogeny was reconstructed using RAxML and bootstrap values are shown at each node. Gene duplication by WGD in Acropora is shown in cyan.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_24"><head>Figure S20 .</head><label>S20</label><figDesc>Phylogeny of the toxic snake venom 5'-nucleotidase. Related to Figure 5. The phylogeny was reconstructed using RAxML and bootstrap values are shown at each node. Gene duplication by WGD in Acropora is shown in cyan.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_25"><head>Figure S21 .Figure S22 .</head><label>S21S22</label><figDesc>Phylogeny of orthogroup 434 (somatostatin receptor type 5-like) shows duplicates are under two WGD topology. Related to Figure 1. The phylogeny was reconstructed using MrBayes, and Bayesian posterior probabilities are shown at each node. Frequency distributions of dS values for paralogous gene pairs in two new released genomes: (A) Acropora millepora and (B) Acropora tenuis. Related to Figure 2. The distributions of dS values of paralogs, estimating neutral evolutionary divergence since the two paralogs diverged, are plotted with a bin size of 0.005, showing the similar peaks (dS value: 0-0.3) in Acropora.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>of modern diversity patterns of reef corals.Proc. Biol. Sci. 273,[975][976][977][978][979][980][981][982] </figDesc><table><row><cell>ISCI, Volume 13</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">of genes responsive to thermal stress and development of genetic markers for population studies. Mar. Biotechnol. (NY) 16, 547-559. Supplemental Information evolution Wang, J.-P., Yu, J.-G., Li, J., Sun, P.-C., Wang, L.,</cell><cell>the coral Acropora digitifera. Curr. Biol. 26, 2885-2892. Zakon, H.H., Lu, Y., Zwickl, D.J., and Hillis, D.M.</cell></row><row><cell>Yuan, J.-Q., Meng, F.-B., Sun, S.-R., Li, Y.-X., and</cell><cell></cell><cell>(2006). Sodium channel genes and the evolution</cell></row><row><cell>Lei, T.-Y. (2018). Two likely auto-tetraploidization</cell><cell>Willis, B.L., van Oppen, M.J.H., Miller, D.J.,</cell><cell>of diversity in communication signals of electric</cell></row><row><cell>events shaped kiwifruit genome and contributed</cell><cell>Vollmer, S.V., and Ayre, D.J. (2006). The role of</cell><cell>fishes: convergent molecular evolution. Proc.</cell></row><row><cell>to establishment of the actinidiaceae family.</cell><cell>hybridization in the evolution of reef corals. Annu.</cell><cell>Natl. Acad. Sci. U S A 103, 3675-3680.</cell></row><row><cell>iScience 7, 230-240.</cell><cell>Rev. Ecol. Evol. Syst. 37, 489-517.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Wang, W., Hui, J.H.L., Chan, T.F., and Chu, K.H. (2014). De novo transcriptome sequencing of the A Likely Ancient Genome Duplication Yasuoka, Y., Shinzato, C., and Satoh, N. (2016). The mesoderm-forming gene brachyury snail echinolittorina malaccana: identification regulates ectoderm-endoderm demarcation in in the Speciose Reef-Building</cell><cell>Zhang, G.Q., Liu, K.W., Li, Z., Lohaus, R., Hsiao, Y.Y., Niu, S.C., Wang, J.Y., Lin, Y.C., Xu, Q., Chen, L.J., et al. (2017). The Apostasia genome and the ). Biochem. Genet. 21, evolution of orchids. Nature 549, 379-383. 667-689.</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Suzuki, G., and Nomura, K. (2013). Species</cell></row><row><cell>Coral Genus, Acropora</cell><cell></cell><cell>boundaries of Astreopora corals (Scleractinia, Acroporidae) inferred by mitochondrial and nuclear molecular markers. Zoolog. Sci. 30,</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>626-632.</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>of the</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>coral genus Acropora (Scleractinia, Cnidaria)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>based on a mitochondrial and a nuclear marker:</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>reticulation, incomplete lineage sorting, or</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>morphological convergence? Mol. Biol. Evol. 18,</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>1315-1329.</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Vanneste, K., Baele, G., Maere, S., and Van de</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Peer, Y. (2014). Analysis of 41 plant genomes</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>supports a wave of successful genome</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>duplications in association with the Cretaceous-</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Paleogene boundary. Genome Res. 24, 1334-</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>1347.</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Vanneste, K., Van de Peer, Y., and Maere, S.</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(2012). Inference of genome duplications from</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>age distributions revisited. Mol. Biol. Evol. 30,</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>177-190.</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Veron, A.S., Kaufmann, K., and Bornberg-Bauer,</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>E. (2006). Evidence of interaction network</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>evolution by whole-genome duplications: a case</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>study in MADS-box proteins. Mol. Biol. Evol. 24,</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>670-678.</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Vollmer, S.V., and Palumbi, S.R. (2002).</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Hybridization and the evolution of reef coral</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>diversity. Science 296, 2023-2025.</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Vonk, F.J., Casewell, N.R., Henkel, C.V.,</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Heimberg, A.M., Jansen, H.J., McCleary, R.J.R.,</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Kerkkamp, H.M.E., Vos, R.A., Guerreiro, I., and</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Calvete, J.J. (2013). The king cobra genome</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>reveals dynamic gene evolution and adaptation</cell></row></table><note>Tiley, G.P., Ane, C., and Burleigh, J.G. (2016). Evaluating and characterizing ancient whole- genome duplications in plants with gene count data. Genome Biol. Evol. 8, 1023-1037. Van de Peer, Y., Maere, S., and Meyer, A. (2009). The evolutionary significance of ancient genome duplications. Nat. Rev. Genet. 10, 725-732. Van De Peer, Y., Mizrachi, E., and Marchal, K. (2017). The evolutionary significance of polyploidy. Nat. Rev. Genet. 18, 411-424. Van Oppen, M.J., McDonald, B.J., Willis, B., and Miller, D.J. (2001). The evolutionary historyin the snake venom system. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U S A 110, 20651-20656. Wallace, C.C. (2012). Acroporidae of the Caribbean. Geologica Belgica 15, 388-393. Wallace, C.C., and Rosen, B.R. (2006). Diverse staghorn corals (Acropora) in high-latitude Eocene assemblages: implications for the iScience 13, 20-32, March 29, 2019Yafei Mao and Noriyuki Satoh</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_8"><head>Table S5 . Likelihood of multiple WGDs hypotheses in Acropora using WGDgc method with gene counts data. Related to Figure 1.Table S6 . Likelihood of different times of WGD under one WGD event in Acropora using WGDgc. Related to Figure 1.</head><label>S5S6</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>1</cell></row><row><cell>Gene</cell><cell>Snake</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>family_1</cell><cell>venom 5'-</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>5</cell><cell>nucleotidase</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>WGD event(s)</cell><cell></cell><cell>Likelihood</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="3">Likelihood Ratio Test</cell><cell></cell><cell>P_value</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0</cell><cell></cell><cell>-38731.86</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0 VS 1</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">7.66E-05</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>1</cell><cell></cell><cell>-38724.04</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>1 VS 2</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">0.01248965</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>2</cell><cell></cell><cell>-38720.92</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>2 VS 3</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">0.05990546</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>3</cell><cell></cell><cell>-38719.15</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Time of WGD</cell><cell></cell><cell>Likelihood</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>18.697005</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>-38724.14</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>22.697005</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>-38724.09</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>26.697005</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>-38724.06</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>30.697005</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>-38724.04</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>34.697005</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>-38724.04</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>38.697005</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>-38724.06</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>42.697005</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>-38724.11</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>46.697005</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>-38724.2</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>50.697005</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>-38724.35</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">iScience 13, 20-32, March 29, 2019</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Supplemental</head> <ref type="table">Tables   Table S1.</ref>  <ref type="table">Table S3</ref><p>. Numbers of gene family in orthogroups, core-orthogroups and highquality core-orthogroups. Related to <ref type="figure">Figure 2</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Numbers Orthogroups 883</head><p>Core-orthogroups 205</p><p>High-quality core-orthogroups 154 </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Transparent Methods</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Species information, genomic data and gene families cluster</head><p>Data can be accessed at: http://marinegenomics.oist.jp, https://przeworskilab.com/data/ and http://comparative.reefgenomics.org/datasets.html <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(Bhattacharya et al., 2016)</ref>. The Acropora species information in this study was described in our previous paper <ref type="bibr">(Mao et al., 2018)</ref>. Information about Astreopora sp1 was described previously <ref type="bibr">(Suzuki and Nomura, 2013)</ref>. Astreopora sp1 was sampled, sequenced, and assembled in the same way of Acropora species <ref type="bibr">(Shinzato et al., in preparation)</ref>. Transcriptome data of A. digitifera across five development stages was described previously <ref type="bibr">(Reyes-Bermudez et al., 2016)</ref>. Protein sequences of the six species were combined to perform allagainst-all BLASTP approach to find all orthologs and paralogs among six species. Then, OrthoMCL was used with default settings to cluster homologs into 19,760 gene families according to sequence similarity <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(Li et al., 2003)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Single-copy orthologs and reconstruction of a calibrated phylogenomic tree</head><p>A custom python script was used to select 3,461 single-copy orthologs with only one gene copy in each species. For each sequence alignment of single-copy orthologs, coding sequences were aligned with MAFFT <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(Katoh et al., 2002)</ref> as described previously <ref type="bibr">(Mao et al., 2018)</ref>. Then, the concatenated sequences of 3,461 single-copy orthologs were used to reconstruct the phylogenomic tree (species tree) with BEAST2 <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Bouckaert et al., 2014)</ref>. First, we partitioned the concatenated coding sequences by codon position. Molecular clock and trees, except substitution model, were linked together. Then, divergence time was estimated using the HKY substitution model, relaxed lognormal clock model, and calibrated Yule prior with the divergence time estimated in our previous study. We ran BEAST2 three times independently, 50 million Markov chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) generations for each run, then we used Tracer to check the log files and we found that ESS of each of parameters exceeded 200.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Orthogroup selection and detection of a WGD event with dS analysis (a) dS distributions of paralogous gene pairs</head><p>Paralogous gene pairs of each species were identified by all-against-all BLASTP approach and then OrthoMCL was used to cluster paralogs into gene families for each species <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(Li et al., 2003)</ref>. Gene families with fewer than 20 genes were used to calculate dS values. Each gene pair within a given gene family was aligned with MAFFT <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(Katoh et al., 2002)</ref> and aligned sequences were used to calculate dS values with Codeml package in PAML with parameters: noisy = 9, verbose = 1, runmode = -2, seqtype = 1, CodonFreq = 2, model = 0, NSsites = 0, icode = 0, fix_kappa = 0, kappa = 1, fix_omega = 0, and omega = 0.5 <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(Yang, 2007)</ref>. The dS distribution of each species was plotted in R <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(Team, 2013)</ref>. All processes were run in the GenoDup <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(Mao, 2019)</ref>. In addition, in order to avoid bias of genomic data, GenoDup <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(Mao, 2019)</ref> was applied to the two recently released genomes (Acropora tenuis and Acropora millepora).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>(b) dS distributions of anchor gene pairs</head><p>We used MCScanX with default settings (except for match_size=3) to find anchor gene pairs based on synteny information for each species <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(Wang et al., 2012)</ref>. Each anchor gene pair was aligned with MAFFT <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(Katoh et al., 2002)</ref> and aligned sequences were used to calculate dS values with Codeml package in PAML with parameters: noisy = 9, verbose = 1, runmode = -2, seqtype = 1, CodonFreq = 2, model = 0, NSsites = 0, icode = 0, fix_kappa = 0, kappa = 1, fix_omega = 0, and omega = 0.5 <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(Yang, 2007)</ref>. The dS distribution of each species was plotted in R <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(Team, 2013)</ref>. All processes were run in the GenoDup <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(Mao, 2019)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>(c) dS distributions of orthologous gene pairs</head><p>We used MCScanX with default settings (except for match_size=3) to find orthologous gene pairs based on synteny information between Astreopora sp1 and A. tenuis, and between A. tenuis and A. digitifera <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(Wang et al., 2012)</ref>. Each orthologous gene pair was aligned with MAFFT <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(Katoh et al., 2002)</ref> and aligned sequences were used to calculate dS values with Codeml package in PAML with parameters: noisy = 9, verbose = 1, runmode = -2, seqtype = 1, CodonFreq = 2, model = 0, NSsites = 0, icode = 0, fix_kappa = 0, kappa = 1, fix_omega = 0, and omega = 0.5 <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(Yang, 2007)</ref>. dS distributions of all species were plotted in R <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(Team, 2013)</ref>. All processes were run in GenoDup <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(Mao, 2019)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Detection of a WGD event using phylogenetic analysis</head><p>A custom python script was used to select the 883 gene families, including one gene copy in Astreopora, one gene copy in each of the five species and at least two ohnologs in one of five Acropora species, as orthogroups. Ohnologs are defined as paralogs originating from WGD.</p><p>For each of the 883 gene tree reconstructions, we used MAFFT <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(Katoh et al., 2002)</ref> to align amino acid sequences of each single-copy ortholog. We aligned coding sequences with TranslatorX <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(Abascal et al., 2010)</ref> based on amino acid alignments and we excluded the single-copy orthologous genes containing ambiguous 'N'. PartitionFinder <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(Lanfear et al., 2012)</ref> was used to find the best substitution model for RAxML (Version 8.2.2) <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(Stamatakis, 2014)</ref> and MrBayes (Version 3.2.3) <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(Ronquist et al., 2012)</ref>, respectively.</p><p>Then, 205 orthogroups, for which phylogeny matched the duplication topology (Astreaopora, (Acropora, Acropora)), were selected as core-orthogroups by eyes. The 154 high quality core-orthogroups, for which clades' bootstrap values in ML phylogeny exceeded 70, were used to perform molecular dating with BEAST2 based on the calibrated phylogenomic tree <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Bouckaert et al., 2014)</ref>. Molecular clock and trees, except substitution model, were linked together. Then, divergence time was estimated using the HKY substitution model, relaxed lognormal clock model, and calibrated Yule prior with the divergence time from our previous study. We ran BEAST2 three times independently, 30 million Markov chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) generations for each run. Then we used Tracer to check the log files. 135 timecalibrated phylogenies with ESS values exceeded 200 were selected.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Estimating peak values in dS distributions and inferred node ages' distribution with KDE toolbox</head><p>Each distribution was estimated using KDE toolbox in MATLAB, as described previously <ref type="bibr">(Zhang et al., 2017)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>(a). Estimating peak values in distributions</head><p>To estimate the age of WGD within dS distributions, we assumed the peak value in orthologous gene pair dS distributions as the split time between two species: the split time between Astreopora sp1 and A. tenuis is 53.6 My, whereas the split time between A. tenuis and A. digitifera is 14.69 My. Before we used the kde() function in KDE toolbox, we first truncated dS distributions to avoid estimation bias due to extreme values: the dS distribution of orthologous gene pairs between Astreopora sp1 and A. tenuis was truncated with a range from -1 to1 while the dS distribution of orthologous gene pairs between A. tenuis and A. digitifera was truncated with a range from -5 to -2. Then, we used the kde() function in KDE toolbox to estimate the peak values of these two dS distributions as -0.314 and -3.4596, respectively. Moreover, the distribution of Acropora paralogous gene pairs was truncated with a range from -4 to 0 and we estimated the peak value of this distribution as -1.8165. We also used bootstrapping to estimate 95% confidence intervals (CIs) of Acropora paralogous gene pairs distribution as -1.7606 to -2.1261 (31.18 to 35.71 My). For bootstrapping, we generated 100 bootstrap samples for each distribution by sampling with replacement from the original data distribution (49,002 samples in the original distribution) with the sample() function. We estimated maximum peak values for each bootstrap samples. Then we sorted maximum peak values and values of 6 th and 95 th rank were used to define the 95% CI.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>(b). Estimating peak values in distributions of inferred node age</head><p>To estimate the age of WGD in the distribution of inferred node ages, we used the kde() function in KDE toolbox to estimate the peak value as 30.78 My, and we used bootstrapping to estimate the 95% CIs as 27.86 to 34.77 My. For bootstrapping, we generated 100 bootstrap samples from the distribution by sampling with replacement from the original data distribution (135 samples in the original distribution) with the sample() function. We estimated maximum peak values for each of 100 bootstrap samples. Then, we sorted maximum peak values and values of 6 th and 95 th rank defined the 95% CI.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Maximum likelihood approach to detect WGD with gene family count data</head><p>First, we filtered gene family cluster data generated by OrthoMCL described above <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(Li et al., 2003)</ref>. The gene family, including only one Astreopora sp1 gene and at least one gene in each of the five Acropora species, was counted. Then, we used the WGDgc package in R to estimate log likelihood for parameters (0, 1, 2, 3) of WGD event(s) with setting (dirac=1,conditioning="twoOrMore") <ref type="bibr">(Rabier et al., 2014)</ref>. Then, we performed likelihood ratio test (pchisq(2*(Likelihood_1-Likelihood_2), df=1, lower.tail=FALSE)) to find the best model and found that one WGD event was the best model to fit the gene family count data. We estimated the age of WGD on 4 My intervals between 18.69 and 38.69 My under a one WGD event model. The lowest log likelihood was shown at the age of WGD: 30.69 and 34.69 My.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Gene expression profiling analysis and dN/dS calculation</head><p>We selected 236 gene pairs of A. digitifera (ohnologous gene pairs) from 883 orthogroups. We BLASTed these ohnologous gene pairs against the gene expression data across five developmental stages <ref type="bibr">(Reyes-Bermudez et al., 2016)</ref> and these data were normalized for each developmental stage. Correlations between two ohnologous genes were performed using Pearson's correlation in R <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(Team, 2013)</ref>. Hierarchical clustering was performed using Pheatmap for HC cluster genes and NC cluster genes, respectively. Pairwise dN/dS ratios were calculated with PAML using codeml based on the coding sequence alignment of ohnologous gene pairs with parameters: noisy = 9, verbose = 1, runmode = -2, seqtype = 1, CodonFreq = 2, model = 0, NSsites = 0, icode = 0, fix_kappa = 0, kappa = 1, fix_omega = 0, and omega = 0.5 <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(Yang, 2007)</ref>. The dN/dS distribution was plotted with ggplot2 in R and significance tests of differences between dN/dS distributions were evaluated by a Mann-Whitney test in R <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(Team, 2013)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Evolution analysis of toxic proteins in corals</head><p>The 55 toxic proteins of A. digitifera identified in the previous study were downloaded from http://www.uniprot.org/ as queries. The protein sequences of Porites astreoides, Porites australiensis, Porites lobata, Montastraea cavernosa, Hydra magnipapillata and Nematostella vectensis were downloaded from http://comparative.reefgenomics.org/datasets.html <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(Bhattacharya et al., 2016)</ref>, and combined them with protein sequences of six Acroporid species to create a search database.</p><p>We identified candidates of toxic proteins by BLASTing the 55 toxins against the combined protein sequences with settings: e-value &lt; 1e -20 and identity &gt; 30%. Then, we used OrthoMCL to cluster candidates of toxins into 24 gene families and reconstructed their ML gene trees with ExaML <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(Kozlov et al., 2015)</ref> and RAxML. Each gene tree was rooted at a branch or clade of query sequences.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Gene ontology enrichment for duplicated genes of core-orthogroups and protein domains and transmembrane helices prediction</head><p>We BLASTed the sequences of 154 high quality core-orthogroups of Acropora against the UNIPROT database to find best hits. Identical hits in each ohonlogs group were removed and the remaining hits were used to perform gene enrichment in David <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(Huang et al., 2009)</ref>. We also used InterProScan <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(Zdobnov and Apweiler, 2001)</ref> to predict protein domains and used the TMHMM Server (v. 2.0) <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(Krogh et al., 2001)</ref> to predict transmembrane helices from protein sequences.</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Climate change disables coral bleaching protection on the Great Barrier Reef</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Ainsworth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Heron</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Ortiz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Mumby</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Grech</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Ogawa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Eakin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Leggat</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">352</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="338" to="342" />
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Ainsworth, T.D., Heron, S.F., Ortiz, J.C., Mumby, P.J., Grech, A., Ogawa, D., Eakin, C.M., and Leggat, W. (2016). Climate change disables coral bleaching protection on the Great Barrier Reef. Science 352, 338-342.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rapid Hydrogen Peroxide release from the coral Stylophora pistillata during feeding and in response to chemical and physical stimuli</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Armoza-Zvuloni</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Schneider</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Sher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Shaked</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sci. Rep</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">21000</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Armoza-Zvuloni, R., Schneider, A., Sher, D., and Shaked, Y. (2016). Rapid Hydrogen Peroxide release from the coral Stylophora pistillata during feeding and in response to chemical and physical stimuli. Sci. Rep. 6, 21000.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Old gene duplication facilitates origin and diversification of an innovative communication system-twice</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Arnegard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Zwickl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Lu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Zakon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U S A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">107</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="22172" to="22177" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Arnegard, M.E., Zwickl, D.J., Lu, Y., and Zakon, H.H. (2010). Old gene duplication facilitates origin and diversification of an innovative communication system-twice. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U S A 107, 22172-22177.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The chemical armament of reef-building corals: interand intra-specific variation and the identification of an unusual actinoporin in Stylophora pistilata</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Ben-Ari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Paz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Sher</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sci. Rep</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">251</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2018" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Ben-Ari, H., Paz, M., and Sher, D. (2018). The chemical armament of reef-building corals: inter- and intra-specific variation and the identification of an unusual actinoporin in Stylophora pistilata. Sci. Rep. 8, 251.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Berner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Salzburger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Berner, D., and Salzburger, W. (2015).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Berthelot</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Brunet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Chalopin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Juanchich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Bernard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Noë L</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Bento</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Da Silva</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Labadie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Alberti</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Berthelot, C., Brunet, F., Chalopin, D., Juanchich, A., Bernard, M., Noë l, B., Bento, P., Da Silva, C., Labadie, K., and Alberti, A. (2014).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Transcriptomic differences between day and night in Acropora millepora provide new insights into metabolite exchange and lightenhanced calcification in corals</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Bertucci</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Foret</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Ball</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Miller</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Ecol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4489" to="4504" />
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Bertucci, A., Foret, S., Ball, E.E., and Miller, D.J. (2015). Transcriptomic differences between day and night in Acropora millepora provide new insights into metabolite exchange and light- enhanced calcification in corals. Mol. Ecol. 24, 4489-4504.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">A recent polyploidy superimposed on older largescale duplications in the Arabidopsis genome</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Blanc</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Hokamp</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Wolfe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Blanc, G., Hokamp, K., and Wolfe, K.H. (2003). A recent polyploidy superimposed on older large- scale duplications in the Arabidopsis genome.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="137" to="144" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Genome Res. 13, 137-144.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">TranslatorX: multiple alignment of nucleotide sequences guided by amino acid translations</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Abascal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Zardoya</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Telford</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic acids research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="7" to="13" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Abascal, F., Zardoya, R., and Telford, M.J. (2010). TranslatorX: multiple alignment of nucleotide sequences guided by amino acid translations. Nucleic acids research 38, W7-13.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Comparative genomics explains the evolutionary success of reef-forming corals</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Bhattacharya</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Agrawal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Aranda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Baumgarten</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Belcaid</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Drake</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Erwin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Foret</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Gates</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Gruber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Elife 5</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">Bhattacharya, D., Agrawal, S., Aranda, M., Baumgarten, S., Belcaid, M., Drake, J.L., Erwin, D., Foret, S., Gates, R.D., Gruber, D.F., et al. (2016). Comparative genomics explains the evolutionary success of reef-forming corals. Elife 5.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">BEAST 2: a software platform for Bayesian evolutionary analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Bouckaert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Heled</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Kuhnert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Vaughan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Xie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Suchard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Rambaut</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Drummond</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS computational biology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Bouckaert, R., Heled, J., Kuhnert, D., Vaughan, T., Wu, C.H., Xie, D., Suchard, M.A., Rambaut, A., and Drummond, A.J. (2014). BEAST 2: a software platform for Bayesian evolutionary analysis. PLoS computational biology 10, e1003537.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Systematic and integrative analysis of large gene lists using DAVID bioinformatics resources</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Sherman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Lempicki</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature Protocols</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="44" to="57" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Huang, D.W., Sherman, B.T., and Lempicki, R.A. (2009). Systematic and integrative analysis of large gene lists using DAVID bioinformatics resources. Nature Protocols 4, 44-57.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Efficient de novo assembly of highly heterozygous genomes from whole-genome shotgun short reads</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Kajitani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Toshimoto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Noguchi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Toyoda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Ogura</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Okuno</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Yabana</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Harada</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Nagayasu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Maruyama</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1384" to="1395" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Kajitani, R., Toshimoto, K., Noguchi, H., Toyoda, A., Ogura, Y., Okuno, M., Yabana, M., Harada, M., Nagayasu, E., Maruyama, H., et al. (2014). Efficient de novo assembly of highly heterozygous genomes from whole-genome shotgun short reads. Genome research 24, 1384-1395.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">MAFFT: a novel method for rapid multiple sequence alignment based on fast Fourier transform</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Katoh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Misawa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Kuma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Miyata</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic acids research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3059" to="3066" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Katoh, K., Misawa, K., Kuma, K., and Miyata, T. (2002). MAFFT: a novel method for rapid multiple sequence alignment based on fast Fourier transform. Nucleic acids research 30, 3059-3066.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">ExaML version 3: a tool for phylogenomic analyses on supercomputers</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Kozlov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Aberer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Stamatakis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2577" to="2579" />
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Kozlov, A.M., Aberer, A.J., and Stamatakis, A. (2015). ExaML version 3: a tool for phylogenomic analyses on supercomputers. Bioinformatics 31, 2577-2579.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Predicting transmembrane protein topology with a hidden Markov model: Application to complete genomes</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Krogh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Larsson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Von Heijne</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">L L</forename><surname>Sonnhammer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Molecular Biology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">305</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="567" to="580" />
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Krogh, A., Larsson, B., von Heijne, G., and Sonnhammer, E.L.L. (2001). Predicting transmembrane protein topology with a hidden Markov model: Application to complete genomes. Journal of Molecular Biology 305, 567-580.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">PartitionFinder: combined selection of partitioning schemes and substitution models for phylogenetic analyses</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Lanfear</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Calcott</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">Y W</forename><surname>Ho</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Guindon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Molecular biology and evolution</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1695" to="1701" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Lanfear, R., Calcott, B., Ho, S.Y.W., and Guindon, S. (2012). PartitionFinder: combined selection of partitioning schemes and substitution models for phylogenetic analyses. Molecular biology and evolution 29, 1695-1701.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">OrthoMCL: identification of ortholog groups for eukaryotic genomes</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Stoeckert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Jr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Roos</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2178" to="2189" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Li, L., Stoeckert, C.J., Jr., and Roos, D.S. (2003). OrthoMCL: identification of ortholog groups for eukaryotic genomes. Genome research 13, 2178-2189.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">GenoDup Pipeline: a tool to detect genome duplication using the dSbased method</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Mao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PeerJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">6303</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2019" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Mao, Y., 2019. GenoDup Pipeline: a tool to detect genome duplication using the dS- based method. PeerJ, 7, p.e6303.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A phylogenomic assessment of ancient polyploidy and genome evolution across the Poales</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Mckain</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Tang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Mcneal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ayyampalayam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Davis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Depamphilis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Givnish</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Pires</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Stevenson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Leebens-Mack</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome biology and evolution</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1150" to="1164" />
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">McKain, M.R., Tang, H., McNeal, J.R., Ayyampalayam, S., Davis, J.I., dePamphilis, C.W., Givnish, T.J., Pires, J.C., Stevenson, D.W. and Leebens-Mack, J.H., (2016). A phylogenomic assessment of ancient polyploidy and genome evolution across the Poales. Genome biology and evolution, 8(4), pp.1150- 1164.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">MrBayes 3.2: efficient Bayesian phylogenetic inference and model choice across a large model space</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Ronquist</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Teslenko</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Van Der Mark</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Ayres</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Darling</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Hohna</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Larget</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Suchard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Huelsenbeck</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Systematic biology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">61</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="539" to="542" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Ronquist, F., Teslenko, M., van der Mark, P., Ayres, D.L., Darling, A., Hohna, S., Larget, B., Liu, L., Suchard, M.A., and Huelsenbeck, J.P. (2012). MrBayes 3.2: efficient Bayesian phylogenetic inference and model choice across a large model space. Systematic biology 61, 539-542.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">RAxML version 8: a tool for phylogenetic analysis and postanalysis of large phylogenies</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Stamatakis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1312" to="1313" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Stamatakis, A. (2014). RAxML version 8: a tool for phylogenetic analysis and post- analysis of large phylogenies. Bioinformatics 30, 1312-1313.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">R: A language and environment for statistical computing</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Team</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Team, R.C. (2013). R: A language and environment for statistical computing.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">MCScanX: a toolkit for detection and evolutionary analysis of gene synteny and collinearity</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Tang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Debarry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Tan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">X</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">Z</forename><surname>Jin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Marler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Guo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
			<biblScope unit="page">40</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Wang, Y.P., Tang, H.B., DeBarry, J.D., Tan, X., Li, J.P., Wang, X.Y., Lee, T.H., Jin, H.Z., Marler, B., Guo, H., et al. (2012). MCScanX: a toolkit for detection and evolutionary analysis of gene synteny and collinearity. Nucleic acids research 40.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">PAML 4: phylogenetic analysis by maximum likelihood</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Molecular biology and evolution</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1586" to="1591" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Yang, Z. (2007). PAML 4: phylogenetic analysis by maximum likelihood. Molecular biology and evolution 24, 1586-1591.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">InterProScan-an integration platform for the signature-recognition methods in InterPro</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Zdobnov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Apweiler</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="847" to="848" />
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Zdobnov, E.M., and Apweiler, R. (2001). InterProScan-an integration platform for the signature-recognition methods in InterPro. Bioinformatics 17, 847-848.</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
