<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /Users/grace/grobid-0.6.1/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Toxic effects of alcyonacean diterpenes on scleractinian corals</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Aceret</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Sammarcob</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Cell</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">School of Molecular Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">James Cook University of North Queensland</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>Q4811</postCode>
									<settlement>Townsville</settlement>
									<country key="AU">Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">&apos; Chancellery</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">bLouisiana Universities Marine Consortium (LUMCON)</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>8124 Hiway 56</addrLine>
									<postCode>70344</postCode>
									<settlement>Chauvin</settlement>
									<region>LA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">Central Queensland University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Rockhampton. Q4702</addrLine>
									<country key="AU">Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Aquatic and Invertebrate Zoology Laboratory, Institute of Biological Sciences, Univer-sity of the Philippines at Los Bafios, College</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>4031</postCode>
									<region>Laguna</region>
									<country key="PH">Philippines</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Toxic effects of alcyonacean diterpenes on scleractinian corals</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<note type="submission">Received 3 June 1994; revision received 11 October 1994; accepted 7 November 1994</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.1" ident="GROBID" when="2021-09-14T05:04+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Coral</term>
					<term>Cell expulsion</term>
					<term>Diterpenoid</term>
					<term>Nematocyst</term>
					<term>Toxicity</term>
					<term>Zooxanthellae</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>Soft corals like Sinularia~exibilis (Quoy &amp; Gaimard) and Lobophytum hedleyi (Ehrenberg) inhibit growth and produce tissue necrosis in neighbouring scleractinian corals. Chemical analysis has shown that these soft corals exude terpenes, toxic allelomones which can kill certain hard corals in the vicinity. This study investigates the stepwise process by which soft coral diterpenes induce cytological damage in scleractinian corals. Small branchlets of Acropora formosa (Dana) and Porites cylindrica (Dana) were exposed to concentrations between 5 and 20 ppm of diterpenes derived from S. Jlexibilis and L. hedleyi. Concentrations higher than 5 ppm caused the initial expulsion of zooxanthellae which was followed by release of nematocysts. These processes were accompanied by inhibition of polyp activity, necrosis and ultimate death of coral polyps. The expelled cells were viable supporting the suggestion that the diterpenes act as membrane active, lipolytic agents. The loss of nematocysts and zooxanthellae from a heterotrophic scleractinian coral essentially removes its ability to procure food from the environment in the form of phyto and zooplankton, to defend itself against competitors for space and predators, and to obtain carbohydrates and other organic molecules fixed by photosynthetic symbionts.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p>Sinularia~exibilis <ref type="bibr">(Quoy &amp; Gaimard, 1833</ref>) is a fleshy, soft coral whose apparent vulnerability to predation is a contradiction to its successful colonization of available space on reefs. Initial interest was based on field observations that this soft coral inhibited the growth of Pavona cactus in its vicinity, possibly by exuding allelochemicals towards the hard coral (see <ref type="bibr">Coll, 1992)</ref>. Field experiments proved that relocated Sinularian colonies can indeed kill neighbouring scleractinian corals and the hypothesis that they do so by releasing chemicals into the water became more compelling <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Sammarco et al., 1983)</ref>. This was confirmed by the findings of soft coral derived terpenes in the seawater surrounding the soft coral <ref type="bibr">(Co11 et al., 1982)</ref>. These allomones <ref type="bibr">(Whittaker &amp; Feeney,</ref><ref type="bibr">197 1)</ref> were identified as flexibilide, dihydroflexibilide and traces of sinulariolide, cembranolide diterpenes which were suspected to be the toxic agents. Although structurally similar, subsequent laboratory experiments showed that they differ in their bioactivities.</p><p>Thus, flexibilide interfered with coral photosynthesis and respiration <ref type="bibr">(Webb &amp; Coll, 1983)</ref>. Sinulariolide has been reported to be an algicide <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(Tursch et al., 1978)</ref>, and the same chemicals caused tissue necrosis and death of corals in the laboratory <ref type="bibr">(Co11 &amp; Sammarco, 1983)</ref>. Lobophytum spp. <ref type="bibr">(Ehrenberg, 1834)</ref> are common soft corals which dominate the intertidal regions of reefs and coastal islands. These corals have fleshy, lobed bodies exposed to predators and like S. Jlexibilis, are rarely preyed upon <ref type="bibr">(Griffiths, 1995)</ref>. Many species have been shown to be ichthyotoxic <ref type="bibr">(Co11 &amp; Sammarco, 1983</ref>), and we have isolated various compounds from Lobophytum species <ref type="bibr">(Co11 et al., 1977</ref><ref type="bibr">(Co11 et al., , 1986</ref>. Specific Lobophytum ichthyotoxins have been identified including denticulatolide from L. denticulutum <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Uchio et al., 1985)</ref>, and lobolide and crassolide from L. crassurn <ref type="bibr">(Bowden et al., 1977;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Kashman &amp; Groweiss, 1977;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Tursch et al., 1978)</ref>. Epiphyte-free colonies of Lobophytum contained cembranolides which have antifouling properties <ref type="bibr">(Bowden et al., 1987)</ref>, while L. pauciflorum possesses cytotoxic cembranolides <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(Yamada et al., 1980)</ref>. A eudesmanoid diterpene isolated from L. hedleyi <ref type="bibr">(Bowden et al., 1978a,b)</ref> and flexibilide from S. Jlexibilis <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Kazlauskas et al., 1978)</ref>, caused mortality in scleractinian coral polyps exposed to more than 10 ppm concentrations of the compounds <ref type="bibr">(Co11 &amp; Sammarco, 1983</ref>). The main objective of these experiments was to compare the toxic responses generated by flexibilide from S. JIexibilis and the eudesmanoid diterpene from Loboph_vtum hedleyi, on polyps ofAcroporaformosa <ref type="bibr">(Dana, 1846)</ref> and Porites cylindrica <ref type="bibr">(Dana, 1846)</ref>. Variations in the effects of flexibilide, dihydroflexibilide and sinulariolide from S. jexibilk on A. formosa were also compared ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref> ).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Methods</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">I. Collection and maintenance of corals</head><p>Colonies of A. formosa and P. cylindrica were collected from Geoffrey Bay, Magnetic <ref type="bibr">Island (146" 49'E,</ref><ref type="bibr">19" 8' S)</ref> and Pioneer Bay, Orpheus Island (146" 28' E, 18" 32' S)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Flexibilide</head><p>Eudesmanoid diterpene by scuba, placed in 50 1 Nally bins filled with seawater during transport to the laboratory and kept in flowing sea water raceways thereafter. Branchlets were cut into 3-4 cm lengths with bolt cutters and placed in running sea water for at least 12 h prior to experimentation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Dihydroflexibilide Sinulariolide</head><p>During the treatments, they were placed in 200 ml glass jars containing 100 ml seawater and immersed in flowing sea water raceway to maintain constant temperature.</p><p>Under these static conditions, the small branchlets were found to be relatively unstressed, even beyond 24 h as shown by the control data.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.">Isolation of terpenes</head><p>The isolation and characterisation of the eudesmanoid diterpene from Lobophytum hedleyi <ref type="bibr">(Bowden et al., 1978a)</ref>, and the three cembranoid diterpenes (flexibilide, dihydroflexibilide and sinulariolide) from S. Jlexibilis were based on reported procedures <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(Tursch et al., 1975;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Kazlauskas et al., 1978)</ref>  <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">(Fig. 1</ref>). Freeze-dried soft corals were cut into small pieces, placed in a sealed flask and extracted with dichloromethane by leaving the coral tissue overnight.</p><p>The solution was filtered, and the solvent dried in vacua to yield a crude extract which was dissolved in dichloromethane and examined by silica-gel tic against standard samples. The crude extract was adsorbed onto a silica gel chromatography column and eluted with combinations of light petroleum, diethyl ether, and dichloromethane from the chromatography column, to yield relatively pure compounds <ref type="bibr">(Co11 &amp; Bowden, 1986)</ref>, which were further purified by hplc or recrystallisation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.">Experimental treatments</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.1.">Stock solutions</head><p>Stock solutions of flexibilide, dihydroflexibilide and sinulariolide from S. jfexibilis, and the eudesmanoid diterpene from L. hedle_yi were prepared by dissolving appropriate weights of the pure diterpenes in 1 ml of ethanol. Aliquots of these stock solutions were added to jars containing the coral branchlets in 100 ml seawater, to produce the concentrations desired in each treatment. Controls consisted of coral branches in (1) seawater and (2) seawater with the same amount of ethanol used in the preparation of the relevant treatments.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.2.">Toxicity assay</head><p>Branchlets of A. formosa and P. cylindrica were treated with 5, 10, 15 and 20 ppm concentrations of flexibilide or the eudesmanoid diterpene in seawater for 24 h. They were examined after 0, 2, 8, 32, 256, 720 and 1440 min to determine the effects of the diterpenes on the corals. The corals were visually assessed using a stereo-dissecting microscope, and ranked following the scheme of attributes used by <ref type="bibr">Co11 &amp; Sammarco (1983)</ref>. Conditions of the corals at the time of examination were coded as follows: 1 = 75-100% of colony exhibiting normal polypal activity, with extended tentacles, no change in pigmentation, no mortality 2 = 50-75% as above 3 = less than 50% as above 4 = tissue still evident, obvious loss of pigmentation, decreased water clarity, no visible signs of life 5 = little or no tissue evident, complete loss of pigmentation, mortality.</p><p>Using a compound microscope, the state of the cells released from the polyps were observed, and cell counts were made. The mean count from 10 x 1 ml seawater samples was used to calculate the number of cells using the modified Fuchs-Rosenthal technique <ref type="bibr">(Spherling &amp; Arakelian, 1990)</ref>. Viability of the cells were tested using Trypan Blue exclusion technique <ref type="bibr">(Andersson et al., 1990;</ref><ref type="bibr">Combrier et al., 1990;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Gurhan &amp; Ozdural, 1990)</ref>. Cells which turned blue by absorbing the dye were dead, while colorless cells were still alive and viable.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.3.">Comparative toxicity of soft coral diterpenes on scleructinian coruls</head><p>Flexibilide, dihydroflexibilide and sinulariolide, diterpenes derived from S. jlexibilis, were used to assess the relative efficacy of the individual terpenes in causing deleterious effects on A. formosa. The experimental protocol was the same as in the previous experiment. Treatments were at concentrations of 5 and 10 ppm only, to avoid the significant levels of mortality generated by higher levels of flexibilide, i.e. at sublethal concentrations for the scleractinian coral. Deleterious effects were determined for A. formosa on a scale of l-5 as above. Seawater alone and seawater with ethanol were used as controls.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4.">Statistical analysis</head><p>The effects of diterpenes on polyp activity were analysed using Friedman's analysis of variance by ranks. Cell counts were transformed</p><p>into log values then backtransformed before linear regression was performed to describe the relationship between time and number of cells released. Graphs were drawn using polynomial regression lines to show the effects of diterpenes over time. Differences among cell count means were analysed using one-way analyses of variance <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Sokal and Rohlf, 1981;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Zar, 1984)</ref>. test shows significant differences in toxic effects between 5 and 10 ppm (p &lt; 0.005) but not among 10, 15, and 20 ppm (p &gt; 0.05). Treatments using concentrations 10 ppm or greater resulted in cessation of polypal activity and ultimately death. Polynomial regression lines drawn for comparative purposes only. Variance in the behavioral data did not exceed k 1.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Results</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">I. Polypal activity</head><p>After 4.5 h treatment with different concentrations of flexibilide, polypal activity of A. formosa branchlets decreased markedly relative to the controls (Chi,squared = 13.154, p&lt; 0.005, Friedman's test) ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 2a)</ref>. At 5 ppm flexibilide concentration, polypal activity was reduced to 50%, while at ppm the result was significantly different with only 25 y0 of the polyps remaining active (pc 0.005, Friedman's test). When any concentration higher than 10 ppm flexibilide was used, polyp activity ceased completely, bleaching of tissues was apparent, and death ultimately followed within 24 h or longer.</p><p>A similar pattern was seen in the activity of P. cylindvica polyps treated with flexibilide relative to controls. Polypal activity at the 5 ppm concentration was significantly greater into log (time+ l), back-transformed before converted into h. Friedman's test shows significant differences in toxic effects between 5 and 10 ppm (p~O.005) but not among 10, 15, and 20 ppm (p&gt;O.O5). Treatments using concentrations 10 ppm or greater resulted in cessation of polypal activity and ultimately death. Polynomial regression lines drawn for comparative purposes only. Variance in the behavioral data did not exceed + 1. than at 10 ppm levels of flexibilide (Chi,-squared = 12.857, p&lt; 0.005, Friedman's test). Any increases beyond 10 ppm arrested polyp activity completely, although statistically they were not significantly different to the result with 10 ppm flexibilide (p &gt; 0.005, Friedman's test). Neither control showed any significant deleterious effects <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">(Fig. 2b)</ref>.</p><p>Coral polyps treated with the eudesmanoid diterpene from L. hedleyi at 5 ppm were significantly affected relative to the controls only after 4.5 h exposure. Only 50% of the polyps were active at the end of 24 h (Chi,-squared = 12.857, p&lt; 0.005, Friedman's test). At 10 ppm, polyp activity in both A. formosa and P. cylindrica was reduced to 25 % at 4.5 h, and all activity stopped within the next hour (Friedman's test, p&lt; 0.005; <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. 3)</ref>. Although the effects of flexibilide were noticeable earlier, the eudesmanoid diterpene was more toxic, causing death in polyps at shorter times of exposure (oneway ANOVA, pc 0.05). Neither control, seawater alone or seawater with ethanol, showed any ill effects. Corals which had been exposed to low concentrations (i.e. 5 ppm or less) for 24 h recovered after flushing the container with seawater. back-transformed before converted into h; zooxanthellae counts transformed into sqrt (count + 0.5). Oneway ANOVA shows significant differences between 5 and 10 ppm (p&lt;O.Ol), but not among 10, 15, and 20 ppm (p&gt; 0.05). Treatments using concentrations 10 ppm or higher resulted into similar numbers of zooxanthellae released. Polynomial regression lines drawn for comparative purposes only. mpora formosa 1</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.">Zooxanthellae release</head><p>Under the compound microscope, the affected polyps were seen to secrete a slimy matrix. Examination of this matrix revealed that endoplasmic cells were being expelled in an organized manner. The first cells that were released were zooxanthellae. These are round cells with thick cell walls and granular interior. The number of zooxanthellae released by the corals upon treatment with terpenes increased at first and then after a threshold had been reached, decreased <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">(Fig. 4)</ref>.</p><p>At a concentration of 5 ppm flexibilide, the number of zooxanthellae released from either scleractinian, was significantly lower than in the corals exposed to 10 ppm (one-way ANOVA, p &lt; 0.0 1). The number of zooxanthellae expelled at 15 and 20 ppm of toxin, however did not vary significantly from those released at 10 ppm (one-way ANOVA, p&gt; 0.05). Fewer zooxanthellae were released from P. cylindrica than from A. into log (time + l), back-transformed before converted into h; zooxanthellae counts transformed into sqrt count+0.5).</p><p>One-way ANOVA shows significant differences between 5 and 10 ppm (p&lt;O.Ol), but not among 10, 15, and 20 ppm (p&gt; 0.05). Treatments using concentrations 10 ppm or higher resulted into similar numbers of zooxanthellae released. Polynomial regression lines drawn for comparative purposes only.</p><p>formosa in the initial stages. This expulsion was slower, and the threshold was between 4.5 and 12 h exposure. After 24 h, more zooxanthellae were being released from P. cylindrica than from A. formosa. The differences in the number of cells released was not significant (one-way ANOVA, p&gt; 0.05).</p><p>At a concentration of 5 ppm of the eudesmanoid diterpene, release of zooxanthellae peaked between 0.5 and 4.5 h. The number of zooxanthellae steadily increased with concentration, and was not significantly different in A. formosa or P. cylindrica (oneway ANOVA, p &gt; 0.0 1). The zooxanthellae numbers released at 5 ppm toxin were markedly less than values released from polyps treated with 10 ppm terpene (ANOVA,</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>~~0.05).</head><p>Again, the total number of zooxanthellae released at 15 and 20 ppm toxin were not significantly different from those found at the 10 ppm concentration ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Fig. 5</ref>; ANOVA, p &gt; 0.05). All zooxanthellae released from terpene-treated coral polyps were viable as indicated by the absence of take-up of the Trypan Blue dye. into log (time + l), back-transformed before converted into h. Cell counts transformed into sqrt (count + 0.05). One-way ANOVA shows significant differences between 5 and 10 ppm (ptO.Ol), but not among 10, 15, and 20 ppm (p&gt;O.O5). Treatments using concentrations of 10 ppm or more yielded similar number of expelled nematocysts. Polynomial regression lines drawn for comparative purposes only.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3.">Nematocyst release</head><p>Nematocysts were expelled from the polyps of A. formosa and P. cylindrica following loss of the zooxanthellae.</p><p>Some nematocysts were still encapsulated in their bulbs while others exhibited a clearly discharged appearance.</p><p>Unlike the zooxanthellae, the number of nematocysts released increased significantly relative to the controls with time of exposure to flexibilide and to the eudesmanoid diterpene ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figs. 6 and 7)</ref>. The number of nematocysts released from A. formosa and P. cylindrica upon exposure to 5 ppm flexibilide were significantly less than that from branchlets treated with 10 ppm which showed almost the same results as the 15 and the 20 ppm treatments (one-way ANOVA, p &lt; 0.05).</p><p>The number of nematocysts released from A. formosa and P. cylindrica in the eudesmanoid diterpene treatments increased as a function of concentration and exposure time, even beyond 24 h <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">(Fig. 7)</ref>. The viability of nematocysts back-transformed before converted into h. Cell counts transformed into sqrt (count + 0.05). One-way ANOVA shows significant differences between 5 and 10 ppm (p &lt; 0.0 l), but not among 10, 15, and 20 ppm (p &gt; 0.05). Treatments using concentrations of 10 ppm or more yielded similar number of expelled nematocysts. Polynomial regression lines drawn for comparative purposes only. time <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">(Figs. 8 and 9</ref>). This mortality however was independent of terpene concentration. Controls did not exhibit significant expulsion of nematocysts.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.4.">Comparative toxicity</head><p>The differences of the effects of S. flexibilis diterpenes on polyp activity in A. formosa are shown on <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 10</ref>. Sinulariolide has a negligible effect on the polyp activity of A. formosa. The coral polyps were normal and still alive even after the 24 h study period. In the case of flexibilide and dihydroflexibilide, the toxic effects were noted after 30 min, and evident not only in the physical appearance of the branchlets, but also in the number of polyps which were no longer active after 24 h. Dihydroflexibilide showed weaker effects than flexibilide, in that only 75% of the polyps ceased activity after 24 h. This difference was highly significant ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 10a; Friedman's test, p&lt; 0.01)</ref>.</p><p>Fewer zooxanthellae were released from A. formosa treated with dihydroflexibilide than flexibilide. Again this difference was highly significant ( <ref type="figure">Fig. lob;</ref> one-way ANOVA, p&lt;O.Ol, ). The release of zooxanthellae peaked 4 h after treatment, and flexibilide induced the release of almost twice as many cells as dihydroflexibilide (R = 0.362, P-C 0.001). Sinulariolide did not cause release of zooxanthellae. Following the release of zooxanthellae from A. formosa under the diterpene treatments, nematocysts were expelled. Again, no nematocysts were expelled from sinulariolide-treated corals ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 10~</ref>; one-way ANOVA, p&gt; 0.05). Only flexibilide and dihydroflexibilide elicited the release of nematocysts. Fewer nematocysts appeared to be released by dihydroflexibilide treatment than by flexibilide, although these differences were not significant ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 10~</ref>; one-way ANOVA, p&gt; 0.05).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Discussion</head><p>A range of soft coral derived diterpenes exhibited toxic effects on the polyps of A. formosa and P. cylindrica. They also caused the release of symbiotic zooxanthellae which are responsible for carbon fixation in the coral polyps via photosynthesis. This results in the depletion of energy supplies to coral cells and a reduction in the supply of carbohydrates to the corals. The zooxanthellae are also critically important to the calcification process in scleractinian corals <ref type="bibr">(Goreau, 1961;</ref><ref type="bibr">Pear-se &amp; Muscatine, 1971</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">, 1973</ref>. Thus, by causing the expulsion of zooxanthellae, a scleractinian coral is severely limited in its ability to grow and calcify. This reduction of photosynthetic activity was noted by <ref type="bibr">Webb &amp; Co11 (1983)</ref> and these experiments provide an explanation for that observation.</p><p>The terpenes also initiated the release of nematocysts, which seemed to be initiated once the rate of zooxanthellae expulsion decreased. The soft coral terpenes caused the expulsion of nematocysts, severely inhibiting the scleractinian coral in its ability to capture prey and defend itself. With the release of most of the zooxanthellae and nearly all the nematocysts, the diterpenes have thus effectively broken down the major processes used by scleractinian corals to obtain food and defend their living space. This ultimately leads to death of the corals.</p><p>The finding that A. formosa is more sensitive to soft coral derived diterpenes than P. cylindrica may be due to the fact that each species has a different structural morphology. Acropora formosa has large calices with interconnected axial corallites. P. cylindrica on the other hand, has minute concave calices, its corallites are compacted with few or no coenosteums, although their walls and septa are porous <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(Veron, 1986)</ref>. A. formosa therefore possesses a higher surface/volume ratio and a larger number of interconnections, which may enhance the transport of terpenes through the larger colony surface and interconnections, and make it easy for terpenes to get from one part of the coral to another. In P. cylindrica the surface for contact is smaller and the terpenes have to be absorbed through the porous walls to be distributed throughout the coral.</p><p>Of the three terpenes derived from S. jexibilis, sinulariolide did not exert toxic effects on hard corals polyps, while flexibilide and dihydroflexibilide were quite lethal to the corals. Flexibilide was more potent than dihydroflexibilide under the bioassay conditions.</p><p>Variations in toxicity might imply that the diterpenes have different ecological roles in the coral (i.e. play diverse functions; <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Sammarco &amp; Coll, 1990)</ref>. In fact, while flexibilide is a major inhibitor of coral growth, dihydroflexbilide is not as potent, and sinulariolide does not possess any toxicity towards A. formosa. From other studies, sinulariolide plays an antifouling role <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(Tursch et al., 1978;</ref><ref type="bibr">Coll, 1992)</ref>, while dihydroflexibilide is a potent olfactory feeding deterrent <ref type="bibr">(Aceret, 1994)</ref>, and the variations in the levels of the three diterpenes within colonies of S. jlexibilis appear to be a response to ecological factors <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Maida et al., 1993)</ref>.</p><p>The release of different cells under the influence of terpenes indicates that the terpenes induce dissociation of the individual cells from the coral tissues. More interestingly, the viability of zooxanthellae released seem to point to the fact that this release is due to the dysfunction of membrane junctions, not to zooxanthellae mortality. Viability of the cells after exposure to the terpenes means that the terpenes are not toxic to the zooxanthellae but that they initiate release of the cells from the parent tissue. It implies that these terpenes apparently influence the cell-to-cell junctions so crucial for the organization and integrity of the tissues. This same theory has been proposed by <ref type="bibr">Gates et al. (1992)</ref> to explain the detachment of zooxanthellae from the host tissues as the main effect of temperature stress on coral cells. <ref type="bibr">Gates &amp; Muscatine (1992)</ref> have also shown that the expelled zooxanthellae are really algal cells with coral protoplasm collapsed around them. Thus, it is not only the zooxanthellae which are still viable, the coral cells released are also still viable. This finding sheds a different light on the results of this experiment, and further reinforces the theory that the diterpenes dissociate cells by destroying cell adhesion molecules. As such, the diterpenes may have some medical value in the treatment of blood clots and thromboses, especially if their cytotoxicity could be modified.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Structures of diterpenes (flexibilide, dihydroflexibilide and sinulariolide derived from S. jlexibilis, and the eudesmanoid diterpene from Lobophytum sp.) used in coral toxicity assays.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Effects of various concentrations of flexibilide on coral polyp activity. (a) A. formosa; (b) P. cylindrica. Values are the means ofthree replicates. Time in min transformed into log (time + l), back-transformed before converted into h. Friedman's</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Effects ofvarious concentrations of the eudesmanoid diterpene on coral polyp activity. (a)A.,formo.m; (b) P. cylindrica. Values are the means of three replicates. Time in min transformed</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig. 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Number of zooxanthellae per ml of seawater released from corals treated with flexibilide. (a) A. formosa; (b) P. cylindrica. Values are the means of three replicates. Time in mitt transformed into log (time + l),</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig. 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Number of zooxanthellae per ml of seawater released from corals treated with eudesmanoid diterpene. (a) Acropora formosa; (b) P. cylindrica. Values are the means of three replicates, Time in min transformed</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Fig. 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Number of nematocysts per ml of seawater released from corals treated with flexibilide. (a) Acropora formosa; (b) P. cylindrica. Values are means of three replicates. Time in min transformed</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Fig. 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc>released, as indicated by Trypan Blue dye, revealed an increasing percentage of dead nematocysts with longer Number of nematocysts released from corals treated with eudesmanoid diterpene. (a) Acropora formosa; (b) P. cylindrica. Values are means of three replicates. Time in min transformed into log (time + l),</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Fig. 8 .</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Viability of nematocysts released from corals treated with flexibilide. (a) Acropora formom; (b) I'. cylindrica. Values are means of three replicates. Time in min transformed into log (time + l), back-transformed before converted into h. Cell counts transformed into sqrt (count + 0.05). Proportion of dead cells arcsinetransformed to fit regression assumptions. One-way ANOVA shows mortality of cells independent of terpene concentration, but dependent on time (p&gt; 0.05). Polynomial regression lines drawn for comparative purposes only.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Fig. 9 .</head><label>9</label><figDesc>Viability of nematocysts released from corals treated with eudesmanoid diterpene. (a) Acropora formosa; (b) P. cylindrica. Values are means of three replicates. Time in min transformed into log (time + l), back-transformed before converted into h. Cell counts transformed into sqrt (count + 0.05). Proportion of dead cells arcsine-transformed to fit regression assumptions. One way ANOVA shows mortality of cells independent of terpene concentration, but dependent on time (p&gt; 0.05). Polynomial regression lines drawn for comparative purposes only.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Fig. 10 .</head><label>10</label><figDesc>Variation in effects of S. flexibilis diterpenoids on A. formosa. Values are means of six replicates. Number of cells released transformed into sqrt (counts + 0.05). Time in min transformed into log (time + 1), back-transformed before converted into h. (a) Flexibilide inhibited polyp activity more strongly than dihydroflexibilide (Friedman's test, p&lt; 0.01); sinulariolide was not significantly different from controls (Friedman's test p&gt; 0.005). (b) One-way ANOVA shows significant differences in release of zooxanthellae between flexibilide and dihydroflexibilide (p&lt;O.Ol), but not between sinulariolide and the controls (p&gt;O.O5). (c) Differences in the number of nematocysts released by flexibilide and dihydroflexibilide were not significant (one-way ANOVA, p&gt;O.O5). Sinulariolide did not trigger the release of zooxanthellae or nematocysts. Polynomial regression lines drawn for comparative purposes only.</figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>Thanks to B. Bowden and D. Yellowlees for providing valuable advice during the course of this study. This work was funded by the Australian Research Council. An IDP (International Development Programme of Australian Colleges and Universities Programme) Ph.D. Fellowship is acknowledged to TLA, and James Cook University and Central Queensland University provided additional support for the project.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>References</head><p>Aceret, T.L., 1994. Screening of biomedical substances derivedfrom marine organisms. Ph.D. Thesis, James</p><p>Cook University of North Queensland, Townsville, Australia, 180 pp. <ref type="bibr">Andersson, B.S., M. Rundgreen, S.D. Nelson &amp; S. Harder, 1990. N-Acetyl-p-benzoquinone</ref> imine-induced changes in the energy metabolism in hepatocytes. <ref type="bibr">Chem. Biol. Interact., Vol. 75, pp. 201-212. Bowden B.F., J.A. Brittle, J.C. Coil, N. Liyanage, S.J. Mitchell, &amp; G.J. Stokie, 1977</ref> </p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">13 cells in serum-induced and serum-free medium supplemented with various membrane protective agents</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">I. &amp; N</forename><surname>Gurhan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Ozdural</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cytotechnology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="89" to="93" />
			<date type="published" when="1990" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Serial cultivation of suspended BHK 21</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">Gurhan, S.I. &amp; N. Ozdural, 1990. Serial cultivation of suspended BHK 21,&apos;13 cells in serum-induced and serum-free medium supplemented with various membrane protective agents. Cytotechnology, Vol. 3, pp. 89- 93.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cembranoid constituents from an Australian collection of the soft coral Sinulariu,flexibilis</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">&amp; A</forename><surname>Kashman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Groweiss ; Kazlauskas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Murphy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Wells</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">&amp; J C</forename><surname>Schonlholzer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Coil</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Tetrahed. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1817" to="1824" />
			<date type="published" when="1977" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Aust. J. Chem.</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">Kashman, Y. &amp; A. Groweiss, 1977. Lobolide: a new epoxycembranolide from marine origin. Tetrahed. Lett., Vol. 13, pp. 1159-l 160. Kazlauskas, R., P.T. Murphy, R.J. Wells, P. Schonlholzer &amp; J.C. Coil, 1978. Cembranoid constituents from an Australian collection of the soft coral Sinulariu,flexibilis. Aust. J. Chem., Vol. 3 1, pp. 1817-1824.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Variability of terpene content in the soft coral Sinularia,flexibilis (Coelenterata: Octocorallia), and its ecological implications</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Maida</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Carroll</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">&amp; J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Coil</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Chem. Ecol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2285" to="2296" />
			<date type="published" when="1993" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Maida, M., A.R. Carroll &amp; J.C. Coil, 1993. Variability of terpene content in the soft coral Sinularia,flexibilis (Coelenterata: Octocorallia), and its ecological implications. J. Chem. Ecol., Vol. 19, pp. 2285-2296.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Nutrition of corals</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Muscatinc</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biology and geology qfcorul</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1973" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Muscatinc, L., 1973. Nutrition of corals. In, Biology and geology qfcorul reef;</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Competitive strategies of soft corals (Coelenterata: Octocorallia): Allelopathic effects on selected scleractinian corals</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">B. &amp; L</forename><surname>Pearse</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Muscatinc</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">W &amp; J C</forename><surname>Sammarco</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Coll</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Chem. Ecol</title>
		<editor>Sammarco, P.W., J.C. Coll, S.C. La Barre &amp; B. Willis</editor>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">141</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="173" to="178" />
			<date type="published" when="1971" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Cwul Reejk</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">Pearse, V.B. &amp; L. Muscatinc, 1971. Role of symbiotic algae (zooxantheilae) in coral calcification. Biol. Bull., Vol. 141, pp. 350-63. Sammarco, P.W &amp; J.C. Coll, 1990. Lack of predictability in terpenoid function. J. Chem. Ecol., Vol. 16, pp. 273-289. Sammarco, P.W., J.C. Coll, S.C. La Barre &amp; B. Willis, 1983. Competitive strategies of soft corals (Co- elenterata: Octocorallia): Allelopathic effects on selected scleractinian corals. Cwul Reejk, Vol. 1, pp. 173- 178.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The number and some other characteristics of isolated human ventricular cardiomyocytes under pathological conditions</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">R F J</forename><surname>Sokal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Rohlf</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="middle">W H</forename><surname>Biometry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Freeman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Co</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Francisco</forename><surname>San</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Car Vasa</title>
		<editor>Spherhng, I.D. &amp; L.A. Arakelian</editor>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">859</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="327" to="334" />
			<date type="published" when="1981" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Sokal, R.R. &amp; F.J. Rohlf, 1981. Biometry. W.H. Freeman and Co., San Francisco, 859 pp. Spherhng, I.D. &amp; L.A. Arakelian, 1990. The number and some other characteristics of isolated human ventricular cardiomyocytes under pathological conditions. Car Vasa, Vol. 32, pp. 327-334.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Chemical studies of marine invertebrates. XI. Sinulariolide, a new cembranolide diterpene from the soft coral Sinulariajkxibilis</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Tursch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Braekman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Daloze</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Herin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Karlsson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">&amp; D</forename><surname>Losman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Te/rahedron</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="129" to="133" />
			<date type="published" when="1975" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Tursch, B., J.C. Braekman, D. Daloze, M. Herin, R. Karlsson &amp; D. Losman, 1975. Chemical studies of marine invertebrates. XI. Sinulariolide, a new cembranolide diterpene from the soft coral Sinulariajkxibilis. Te/rahedron, Vol. 31, pp. 129-133.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Terpenoids from coelenterates</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Tursch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Braekman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Daloze</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">&amp; M</forename><surname>Kaisin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Marine rmtural products: chemical and biological per.~pectives</title>
		<editor>P.J. Scheuer</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Academic Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1978" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="247" to="296" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Tursch, B., J.C. Braekman, D. Daloze &amp; M. Kaisin, 1978. Terpenoids from coelenterates. In, Marine rmtural products: chemical and biological per.~pectives, Vol. 2, edited by P.J. Scheuer, Academic Press, New York, pp. 247-296.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dcnticulatolidc, an ichthyotoxic peroxide-containing cembranolide from soft coral Lobophytum denticuloturn</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Uchio</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Eguchi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kuramoto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Nakayama</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">&amp; T</forename><surname>Hase</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Tetruhed. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4487" to="4490" />
			<date type="published" when="1985" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Uchio, Y., S. Eguchi, J. Kuramoto, M. Nakayama &amp; T. Hase, 1985. Dcnticulatolidc, an ichthyotoxic peroxide-containing cembranolide from soft coral Lobophytum denticuloturn. Tetruhed. Lett., Vol. 26, pp. 4487-4490.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Corals of Australicr and the Indo-Pocifzc</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E N</forename><surname>Veron</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1986" />
			<publisher>Angus and Robertson Publishers</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">644</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">pp</biblScope>
			<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Veron, J.E.N., 1986. Corals of Australicr and the Indo-Pocifzc. Angus and Robertson Publishers, London, 644 pp.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effects of alcyonarian coral terpenes on scleractinian coral photosynthesis and respiration</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">J C</forename><surname>Webb</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Coil</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Toxicon</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="485" to="533" />
			<date type="published" when="1983" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Suppl.</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">Webb, L. &amp; J.C. Coil, 1983. Effects of alcyonarian coral terpenes on scleractinian coral photosynthesis and respiration. Toxicon, Suppl., Vol. 3, pp. 485-48X.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">H P P</forename><surname>Whittaker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Feeney</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Allelochemics: Chemical interactions between species. Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">171</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="757" to="770" />
			<date type="published" when="1971" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Whittaker, R.H. &amp; P.P. Feeney, 1971. Allelochemics: Chemical interactions between species. Science, Vol. 171, pp. 757-770.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Studies in marine natural products. III. Two new cembranolides from the soft coral Lobophyturn pauciJIontrn (Ehrenberg)</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Yamada</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Susuki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Iguchi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Kukuchi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Tsukitani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">&amp; H</forename><surname>Horiai</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Chem. Pharm. Bull</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2035" to="2038" />
			<date type="published" when="1980" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Yamada, Y., S. Susuki, K. Iguchi, H. Kukuchi, Y. Tsukitani &amp; H. Horiai, 1980. Studies in marine natural products. III. Two new cembranolides from the soft coral Lobophyturn pauciJIontrn (Ehrenberg). Chem. Pharm. Bull., Vol. 28, pp. 2035-2038.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Biostatistical analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Zar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1984" />
			<publisher>Prentice-Hall International</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">718</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">pp</biblScope>
			<pubPlace>New Jersey</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>2nd edition</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">Zar, J.H., 1984. Biostatistical analysis, Prentice-Hall International, New Jersey, 2nd edition, 718 pp.</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
