<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /Users/grace/grobid-0.6.1/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Adaptations to Endosymbiosis in a Cnidarian-Dinoflagellate Association: Differential Gene Expression and Specific Gene Duplications</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2011-07-21">July 21, 2011</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Philippe</forename><surname>Ganot</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Université de Nice-Sophia-Antipolis</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Nice</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Université Pierre et Marie Curie</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Paris</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">Centre National de la Recherche Scientifique</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Roscoff</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="laboratory">UMR7138 Systématique</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Adaptation, Nice</settlement>
									<region>Evolution</region>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Virginie</forename><forename type="middle">¤</forename><surname>Magnone</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Université de Nice-Sophia-Antipolis</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Nice</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Université Pierre et Marie Curie</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Paris</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">Centre National de la Recherche Scientifique</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Roscoff</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="laboratory">UMR7138 Systématique</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Adaptation, Nice</settlement>
									<region>Evolution</region>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="laboratory" key="lab1">Institut de Pharmacologie Moléculaire et Cellulaire</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory" key="lab2">UMR 6097</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Centre Scientifique de Monaco</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Sophia Antipolis, Monaco</settlement>
									<country>France, Monaco</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Denis</forename><surname>Allemand</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Université de Nice-Sophia-Antipolis</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Nice</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">Centre National de la Recherche Scientifique</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Roscoff</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Paola</forename><surname>Furla</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Université de Nice-Sophia-Antipolis</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Nice</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Université Pierre et Marie Curie</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Paris</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">Centre National de la Recherche Scientifique</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Roscoff</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="laboratory">UMR7138 Systématique</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Adaptation, Nice</settlement>
									<region>Evolution</region>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Cé</forename><surname>Cile Sabourault</surname></persName>
							<email>cecile.sabourault@unice.fr</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Université de Nice-Sophia-Antipolis</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Nice</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Université Pierre et Marie Curie</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Paris</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">Centre National de la Recherche Scientifique</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Roscoff</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="laboratory">UMR7138 Systématique</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Adaptation, Nice</settlement>
									<region>Evolution</region>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="institution">University of California</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>San Francisco</addrLine>
									<country>United States of America</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff6">
								<orgName type="laboratory">ARC Centre of Excellence for Coral Reef Studies</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">James Cook University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Townsville</settlement>
									<country key="AU">Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Adaptations to Endosymbiosis in a Cnidarian-Dinoflagellate Association: Differential Gene Expression and Specific Gene Duplications</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2011-07-21">July 21, 2011</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1371/journal.pgen.1002187</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received December 29, 2010; Accepted June 1, 2011;</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.1" ident="GROBID" when="2021-09-14T02:44+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Trophic endosymbiosis between anthozoans and photosynthetic dinoflagellates forms the key foundation of reef ecosystems. Dysfunction and collapse of symbiosis lead to bleaching (symbiont expulsion), which is responsible for the severe worldwide decline of coral reefs. Molecular signals are central to the stability of this partnership and are therefore closely related to coral health. To decipher inter-partner signaling, we developed genomic resources (cDNA library and microarrays) from the symbiotic sea anemone Anemonia viridis. Here we describe differential expression between symbiotic (also called zooxanthellate anemones) or aposymbiotic (also called bleached) A. viridis specimens, using microarray hybridizations and qPCR experiments. We mapped, for the first time, transcript abundance separately in the epidermal cell layer and the gastrodermal cells that host photosynthetic symbionts. Transcriptomic profiles showed large inter-individual variability, indicating that aposymbiosis could be induced by different pathways. We defined a restricted subset of 39 common genes that are characteristic of the symbiotic or aposymbiotic states. We demonstrated that transcription of many genes belonging to this set is specifically enhanced in the symbiotic cells (gastroderm). A model is proposed where the aposymbiotic and therefore heterotrophic state triggers vesicular trafficking, whereas the symbiotic and therefore autotrophic state favors metabolic exchanges between host and symbiont. Several genetic pathways were investigated in more detail: i) a key vitamin K-dependant process involved in the dinoflagellate-cnidarian recognition; ii) two cnidarian tissue-specific carbonic anhydrases involved in the carbon transfer from the environment to the intracellular symbionts; iii) host collagen synthesis, mostly supported by the symbiotic tissue. Further, we identified specific gene duplications and showed that the cnidarian-specific isoform was also up-regulated both in the symbiotic state and in the gastroderm. Our results thus offer new insight into the inter-partner signaling required for the physiological mechanisms of the symbiosis that is crucial for coral health.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Introduction</head><p>The mutualistic symbiosis of anthozoans (Cnidaria), such as corals and sea anemones, with their intracellular dinoflagellate symbionts, mostly of the genus Symbiodinium, forms both trophic and structural foundation of coral reef ecosystems. Anthozoans have a very simple body plan and are composed of two tissue layers, the epidermis and the gastroderm (also called ectoderm and endoderm, respectively <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>, <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure S1A</ref>). They host their unicellular symbionts, also called zooxanthellae, inside vacuoles (symbiosomes) within the gastrodermal cell layer. Safely localized inside the animal host cells, the photosynthetic symbionts fix large quantities of carbon dioxide. Most of the reduced organic carbon produced is then translocated to the host as mobile compounds, such as glycerol, lipids and amino acids <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>. In return, the host provides suitable conditions for symbiont photosynthesis: inorganic nitrogen, phosphorus and inorganic carbon, as well as a favorable high light environment <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>.</p><p>This partnership generates many constraints, however, resulting in physiological and cellular adaptations (for review, <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4]</ref>). For example, the presence of photosynthetic zooxanthellae within the gastrodermal cells requires the host to transport inorganic carbon from the surrounding seawater to the symbionts, a process in which carbonic anhydrases (CAs) are central <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6]</ref>. To prevent possible cellular damage resulting from photosynthesis-induced hyperoxia, both partners also express a high diversity of antioxidant enzymes, including catalases, peroxidases and superoxide dismutases (SODs), <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>. SOD and CA isoforms specific to symbiotic anthozoans have been demonstrated <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10]</ref>.</p><p>Environmental perturbations such as an increase in seawater temperature may induce dysfunction and collapse of the symbiosis, leading to zooxanthellae loss or so-called ''bleaching'', and this phenomenon has led to severe worldwide decline of coral reefs <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>. The establishment and maintenance of this partnership must therefore be dependent on intimate molecular communications between the partners, including recognition and tolerance of symbionts, as well as adaptations for mutual transport and exchange of nutritional resources. A small number of candidate genes for this molecular dialogue has been proposed, including CAs and the cell adhesion protein Sym32 <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">12,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13]</ref>. These have so far been examined by targeted protein analyses (for review, see <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>). Large-scale gene expression studies have tended to highlight a modulation of the host transcriptome, in particular genes involved in cell adhesion, lipid metabolism, cell cycle regulation, or cell death <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref>. While most transcriptomic approaches have been performed in symbiotic cnidarians under thermal stress, imposed in order to understand the molecular and cellular basis of the early events leading to bleaching <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">19]</ref>, we rather focused our present experimental approach on two stable states: symbiotic and aposymbiotic individuals.</p><p>How do anthozoans maintain a stable partnership with their photosynthetic dinoflagellate symbionts? To decipher the molecular dialogue inferred by the presence of the dinoflagellate symbionts (Symbiodinium clade temperate A) within the sea anemone Anemonia viridis, we compared transcriptomes of symbiotic and aposymbiotic specimens using a symbiosis-dedicated microarray. This oligonucleotide microarray (2,000 features) was developed from the A. viridis 40,000 EST collection <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref> and is dedicated to genes potentially involved in symbiosis regulatory pathways.</p><p>Our two main goals were to identify gene expression patterns characteristic of: i) the symbiotic and aposymbiotic conditions, ii) the epidermis and gastroderm tissue layers. The main advantage of our model, A. viridis, is it allows efficient separation of the two tissue layers of the animal (epidermis and gastroderm) with minimal cross contamination <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>. Concerted DNA microarrays and quantitative RT-PCR (qPCR) analyses outlined characteristic gene expression signatures for the symbiotic and aposymbiotic states. Among newly identified genes, some appeared to result from anthozoan-specific gene duplications. Analyses of tissuespecific expression demonstrated that most of the host genes involved in symbiotic interactions are preferentially expressed in the gastroderm (i.e. the zooxanthellate tissue layer). We detailed several genetic regulatory pathways involved in dinoflagellatecnidarian recognition, carbon transfer to the intracellular symbionts and mesoglea constitution. Finally, we propose a model where the aposymbiotic state triggers vesicular trafficking whereas the symbiotic state favors metabolic exchanges between host and symbionts.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Molecular quantification of dinoflagellates</head><p>The ''bleached'' phenotype is shared by many stressed symbiotic cnidarians and is the consequence of a massive upstream loss of symbionts and hence their photosynthetic pigments. Most approaches to quantify symbiont loss use manual zooxanthellae counts. Here, we developed a fast and accurate approach using real-time quantitative PCR on total genomic DNA extracts to quantify the relative number of nuclei and hence cells.</p><p>Symbiodinium (temperate A clade) nuclear Elongation Factor 2 (EF2), Sucrose Phosphate Synthase (SPS) and Ascorbate Peroxidase (APX) and the A. viridis nuclear Coatomer subunit gamma (COP-c Regulator of Chromosome Condensation protein 2 (RCC2) and Niemann-Pick disease type C1 (NPC1) gene copy numbers were assessed for total genomic DNA extracts from 5 symbiotic anemones (Sy1-Sy5) and 6 aposymbiotic anemones (AS1-AS6) collected along the Mediterranean coasts around Nice, France ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure S2</ref>) and kept in laboratory culture, as well as in vitro cultured Symbiodinium (CZ) and epidermal tissue fraction (Ep). Although gene locus number per nucleus is assumed to remain constant for a given species, dinoflagellates have been shown to undergo gene specific amplifications <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">22]</ref>. In Amphidinium carterae, the EF2 gene is present in tandem repeat contrary to APX <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref>. Whilst the 3 A. viridis gene loci were present in a nearly 1:1 ratio in all specimens, in Symbiodinium the number of genes was relatively variable from one specimen to another despite the proximity of collection sites to one another. The SPS:APX ratio was around 1:1 in all specimens except for AS2 and AS6. EF2:APX and EF2:SPS ratios displayed strong polymorphism, likely due to EF2 variable gene amplification ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure S3A</ref>). Gene copy numbers between A.viridis and its symbiont were also measured. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref> shows the relative symbiont to host nucleus ratio for APX/COP-c SPS/COP-c and EF2/COP-c (similar results were obtained with RCC2 and NPC1, <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure S3B</ref>). Whatever gene locus used, the pattern of symbiont to host cell ratio was reproducibly similar with ratios between aposymbiotic and symbiotic specimens ranging from 8.2610 22 (AS4 versus Sy1) to over 10 24 fold (AS6 versus Sy5).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Inter-individual variability in symbiotic and aposymbiotic expression profiles</head><p>In order to identify gene expression patterns characteristic of symbiosis, the gene expression profiles of symbiotic and aposymbiotic anemones were compared using a symbiosis-dedicated oligoarray. 60-mer oligonucleotides were designed from 2,000 sequences putatively involved in symbiosis selected from the large clustered and annotated A. viridis EST collection <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref>. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure S1</ref> gives an overview of the Gene Ontology (GO) functional annotations of the selected sequences.</p><p>Microarray experiments were performed between symbiotic and aposymbiotic anemones, using a dual-dye protocol, one condition being labeled with Cy3, and the second by Cy5. The experimental design of hybridizations is shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure S4</ref>. Microarray results were analyzed according to two methods. First, in order to have an overall estimate of the genes differentially expressed between the two states, we treated the 11 individual</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Author Summary</head><p>The global decline of reef-building corals is of particular concern: they are among the most threatened marine ecosystems. Coral reefs have been decimated over the last several decades, leading to a rapid loss of reef biodiversity and the loss of the resources that humans derive from them. Coral health depends mainly on the trophic intimate association between the animal host and the photosynthetic symbionts (dinoflagellates) residing within its cells. Insights into the physiological mechanisms that underlie healthy as well as stressed (or bleached) corals are thus critical to predict whether they will be able to adapt to and survive climate change. We used a transcriptomic approach to decipher the molecular dialogues between a cnidarian host and its dinoflagellate symbionts. We identified in the host new key pathways that contribute to the symbiotic interaction, as well as specific genetic adaptations.</p><p>specimens as two batch categories: symbiotic anemones (Sy1-Sy5) and aposymbiotic anemones (AS1-AS6). Statistical analysis was performed with the limmaGUI package <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref> that defined for each gene in each experiment an average fold change (M, corresponding to a log2 ratio between the 2 experimental conditions) and a statistical value (called B, with positive values for the more significant variations). 58 and 78 genes were significantly upregulated (|M|.0.59 and B.0) in the symbiotic (hereafter called ''SY gene set'') and aposymbiotic states (hereafter called ''APO gene set''), respectively <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">(Figure 2A</ref>, Tables S1 and S2). Functional annotation of these 136 genes using GO terms and statistical analysis by Gossip (Fisher's exact test, p,0.05) showed that the terms ''plastid'', ''calcium ion binding'', and ''protein modification process'' were over-represented in the SY gene set, in contrast to ''cytosol'', ''cytoplasmic membrane-bounded vesicle'' and ''transcription'', which were over-represented in the APO gene set ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure S1C</ref>).</p><p>Second, in order to gain insights about inter-individual variation in gene expression, we compared each individual symbiotic anemone (Sy1 to Sy5) with the batch of 6 aposymbiotic anemones (Apo), and inversely, compared each aposymbiotic anemone (AS1 to AS6) with the batch of 5 symbiotic anemones (Sy). This analysis ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 2A</ref>) showed unexpectedly high inter-individual variability of differential gene expression patterns within these 136 genes. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 2B</ref> shows the number of individual anemones for which a given gene is significantly differentially expressed between the SY and APO gene sets. For instance, only 8 SY genes were differentially expressed in all 11 anemones. Conversely, one APO gene (M = 20.63; B = 1.15) encoding for Interferon Regulatory Factor 1 was significantly differentially expressed in only 3 out of 11 anemones. To obtain an indication of the source of variability, we clustered the different anemones according to their expression. Different clustering parameters were tested and showed similar cluster trees; the most representative is shown underneath the heatmap <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">(Figure 2A</ref>). Whatever the parameters used, specimens Sy4 and Sy5, AS1 and AS2, and AS4 and AS5 always paired together. Remarkably, even if the anemones were maintained in the same culture conditions at least 3 months before sampling, such co-clustering seemed to correlate with their previous life history: different collection dates/areas for symbiotic specimens, and different bleaching causes for aposymbiotic sea anemones (see Material and Methods and <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure S2</ref>). Nonetheless, these variable transcriptomic profiles define the same stable symbiotic or aposymbiotic phenotype.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Definition of the Kern gene subset</head><p>The ''Kern'' gene subset (named after the German word for nucleus) was where the remainder of the analysis was focused, and is defined as those genes of cnidarians origin only (excludes genes of unicellular or prokaryotic origin) found in the SY or APO gene set, and differentially expressed in at least 8 out of the 11 specimens. <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">Table 1 lists the representative 19 and 20</ref> Kern genes found in the SY and APO gene sets respectively. A blast homology search against the Nematostella vectensis genome database and the Uniprot generalist database, and searches for specific protein signatures (signal peptide, trans-membrane domains or others domains) allowed the genes to be named and functions and cellular localizations assigned <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">(Table 1)</ref>. Among the different functional categories found, cell adhesion proteins (8/39) were the most represented, a process indeed expected to play a key role in signaling events between partners. A total of 7 other genes were involved in metabolism (4 SY and 3 APO). The four SY genes were specifically involved in fatty acid metabolism, indicating that fatty acid metabolism is likely a preponderant metabolic pathway of the symbiotic condition. Although all genes listed in <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">Table 1</ref> would merit further investigation, only several selectively targeted genes are detailed in this study (see below).</p><p>In order to obtain support for the functional implication of some of the Kern genes, we monitored the expression of genes of interest directly after thermal stress, which is known to disrupt symbiosis. Anemones Sy3-5 were subjected to an 8uC temperature increase, and the expression of CA2-c, CA2-m and NPC2-D dropped by around 3 fold after 24 h and 48 h ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 3</ref>). This result is interesting, considering their up-regulation in symbiotic individuals. This immediate response to environmental stress precedes symbiosis breakdown and thus strengthens support for the possible role of these 3 genes in endosymbiosis in A. viridis. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Gastroderm-specific gene expression</head><p>As the two tissue layers can be separated in A. viridis, it is a powerful biological model for studying tissue-specific gene expression. We used two experimental designs to compare gastrodermal versus epidermal gene expression profiles ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure  S4</ref>). Firstly we directly hybridized the cDNAs of the two tissues against each other on the same array, and secondly we compared each tissue sample to the aposymbiotic AS6 reference and thus defined tissue expression profiles by transitivity. Only the genes with at least 1.50 fold increase in transcript abundance (M.0.59) in one tissue in both experiments were assigned as differentially expressed <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">(Table 2, Tables S1 and S2</ref>). As expected, the expression of most Symbiodinium genes was restricted to the gastroderm. The Venn diagram in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure 4</ref> summarizes distribution of the 1,715 cnidarian-specific genes (prokaryote and zooxanthellae genes were excluded from the analysis) according to their gastrodermal (Ga), epidermal (Ep), and preferential symbiotic (SY) versus aposymbiotic (APO) expression. We further confirmed preferential expression of several genes in the different tissues using real-time quantitative PCR ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figure 5</ref>). Taken together, microarray and qPCR results showed that many more A. viridis genes were preferentially expressed in the gastroderm (71%) than in the epidermis (29%). More interestingly, among the 17 genes which were both preferentially expressed in a given tissue and differentially regulated under symbiotic/aposymbiotic status, the large majority <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(12)</ref> were in fact up-regulated within the gastroderm of symbiotic anemones (i.e. the zooxanthellate tissue). This suggests that the presence of symbionts directly modulates the gene expression of their hosting gastrodermal cells. In addition, out of these 12 genes, 9 belong to the Kern subset of genes, supporting the importance of this gene set in inter-partner communication and regulation ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figure 5</ref> and <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">Table 2</ref>). Hence, we have identified different categories of genes potentially involved in sequential aspects of symbiosis, and showed for the first time that the animal tissue-specific molecular response to the presence/absence of zooxanthellae was restricted almost entirely to preferential expression of genes within the compart-  ment hosting the symbionts. These results support the crucial role of the gastroderm in this symbiotic interaction. The gastroderm-specific gene expression disclosed interesting hallmarks. Carbonic anhydrases are primordial enzymes necessary for the transport of inorganic carbon through biological membranes. Two isoforms were identified in our library and had increased transcript abundance in zooxanthellate anemones. Based on their respective protein signatures and blast homology, one isoform (Av_CA2-c, Kern # 3) is cytoplasmic whereas the other isoform (Av_CA2-m, Kern # 5) probably localizes to the outer plasma membrane, since it contains a signal peptide sequence as well as a trans-membrane and GPI anchor domains at its NH 2 and COOH termini, respectively. The cytoplasmic CA2 was equally distributed in the two compartments, but the membrane-anchored CA2 was principally expressed in the gastroderm ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figure 5</ref>). Another interesting finding on the tissue distribution of gene expression was that collagen biosynthesis was broadly under the control of the gastroderm. In cnidarians, fibrillar collagen genes were recently shown to be much more represented than first expected from bilaterian evolutionary comparisons, with 8 different genes present in the genome of N. vectensis <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref>. In A. viridis, we found 13 different cDNAs corresponding to portions of the N. vectensis homologs. Additionally, we monitored the expression of 5 genes regulating the post-translational processing of collagen synthesis. Interestingly, 14 of these cDNAs showed increased transcript abundance in the gastroderm ( <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">Table 2</ref>). The mesoglea, the acellular layer between epidermis and gastroderm, which mostly consists of collagen, may partly originate from the gastroderm in A. viridis. However, none of these genes showed differential expression between aposymbiotic and symbiotic states, except for Prolyl-4hydroxylase alpha. This enzyme is a key chaperone for the biosynthesis of collagen, catalyzing the hydroxylation of proline residues of procollagen chains necessary for their correct three dimensional folding <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref>. Two different isoforms were identified in our sequence library and the expression of one of them (Kern # 14) was specifically enhanced in zooxanthellate anemones. Thus, in addition to showing that the gastroderm synthesized much of collagen fibers, our results infer that Symbiodinium may exert, directly or indirectly, post-translational control on collagen synthesis and modulate the formation of the mesoglea in A. viridis.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Cnidarian-specific gene duplication of symbiosis-related genes</head><p>During the course of our analysis, we noticed that some of the genes involved in symbiosis (Kern genes) had multiple paralogs in our dataset. Such was the case with the previously described MERP gene family <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref>, but the same held true for other Kern genes including Niemann Pick type C2 (NPC2), Calumenin, Sym32 and C3 Complement (C3) families ( <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">Table 2)</ref>. We conducted phylogenetic analyses on the NPC2, Calumenin and Sym32 gene families in order to assign an evolutionary origin for each member. A. viridis isoforms present in our dataset were compared to their homologs in N.vectensis and other representative eukaryotes with a complete genome sequence. Both maximum likelihood ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">Figure 6</ref> and <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Figure 7A</ref>) and Bayesian ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figures S5, S6</ref>, S7) methods gave very similar trees.    In vertebrates, Calumenin belongs to the CREC gene family, which encompasses 5 members (CAB45, ERC-55, Reticulocalbin 1 and 3, and Calumenin) <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref>. From phylogenetic analysis across metazoans ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">Figure 6A</ref>), 3 groups of homologs can be defined; the CAB45 homologs, the ERC55 homologs and the CALU (Calumenin, Reticulocalbin 1 and 3) homologs. Cnidarian homologs are found within these 3 groups, however additional cnidarian homologs (NvCALUa,c,f-h, AvCALUa,c) are also present outside the CALU and ERC55 groups, representing cnidarian specific CALU gene duplications.</p><p>NPC2 ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">Figure 6B</ref>) is a single copy gene in human, nematode, sea urchin, Placozoa and yeast and is independently duplicated in ascidian and fish. Two copies of the NPC2 gene were found in sea anemones. Phylogenetic analysis supports a gene duplication in Anthozoans, with NvNPC2a and AvNPC2a representing the orthologs of the chordate NPC2, and NvNPC2b and AvNPC2-D defining an anthozoan specific duplication.</p><p>In the symbiotic sea anemones A. viridis and Anthopleura elegantissima, Sym32 is composed of two adjacent FasI domains ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Figure 7A</ref>). In A. viridis, we identified two FasI-containing proteins: Sym 32 and the related periostin gene (PN), which is conserved across metazoans (only cnidarians and human are shown). AvSym32 and AvPN are composed of 2 and 4 FasI domains, respectively. In N. Nematostella, there are also two comparable FasI-containing proteins; both are composed of 4 FasI domains. One corresponds to the PN homolog (NvPN) and the second, which we named Nv2Sym, is similar to a tandem duplication of the AvSym32 sequence with 262 FasI domains. In human, two related FasIcontaining proteins are characterized: the cognate Periostin (HsPN) and the ''Transforming growth factor-beta-induced protein ig-h3'' precursor (HsBGH3), both with 4 FasI domains. As proteins did not have the same number of FasI domains, we conducted a phylogenetic analysis on the alignment of all single FasI domains in order to gain insight into the domain evolution of this protein family ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Figure 7A</ref> and <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Figure S7B</ref>). Human and cnidarian PN genes likely evolved from a common ancestor while Hs_PN and Hs_BGH3 would have duplicated after the Cnidaria -Bilateria separation. Consequently, AvSym32 and Nv2Sym are cnidarianspecific genes. Whether a Sym32 version containing only 2 FasI domains is specific to symbiotic anthozoans remains to be clarified.</p><p>Comparison of the expression of the A. viridis CALU, NPC2 and sym32 homologs showed that the isoform which was more highly expressed in the symbiotic state was also preferentially expressed in the gastroderm, whereas the other members were ubiquitously expressed ( <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">Table 2)</ref>. For instance, AvCalu-a (Kern # 1) was the most up regulated gene in the symbiotic condition and localized in the    gastroderm, whereas expression of both the other isoforms (AvCalu-b and AvCalu-c) was neither different between symbiotic versus aposymbiotic conditions nor between the tissue layers ( <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">Table 2)</ref>. The same held true for the two isoforms of NPC2 (AvNPC2-D (Kern # 2) versus AvNPC2-a) and for Sym32 (Kern # 4) versus the Periostin homologs ( <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">Table 2</ref>). Most interestingly, the isoform that was differentially expressed was always member of the Kern gene set. Thus, analysis of N. vectensis gene families identified cnidarian-specific gene duplications (NvCALUa,c,f-h, NvNPC2b, Nv2sym) and A. viridis ortholog analysis showed that among the cnidarian-specific isoform, the Kern genes (AvCALUa, AvNPC2-D and AvSym32) were upregulated both in symbiotic state and in the gastroderm.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Discussion</head><p>Many anthozoans rely on photosynthetic endosymbionts (mostly Symbiodinium sp.) to grow in oligotrophic environments. The symbiotic relationship involves regulatory crosstalk between partners that allows the association to persist. This interpartner communication includes: i) the recognition of the partners, ii) the ability of symbionts to colonize host cells without being rejected by the host immune system, iii) the regulation of symbiont population, and iv) adaptations for mutual transport and exchange of nutritional resources <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref>. In order to identify the genes potentially involved in the molecular dialog supporting this endosymbiosis, we used a microarray approach to compare the gene expression profiles of 11 A. viridis anemones representative of the symbiotic and the aposymbiotic states. We identified a subset of A. viridis genes, which we named ''Kern'', characteristic of the symbiotic (SY) and aposymbiotic (APO) states in the sense that they were preferentially expressed in symbiotic or aposymbiotic anemones. Consequently, the Kern genes are potentially important candidate genes for the maintenance of the symbiosis process. Since in A. viridis, the two tissue layers can be separated, we were also able to assign tissue-specific gene expression. Many genes or gene functions that were expressed more highly in symbiotic anemones  <ref type="table">Table S4</ref>. The star points to the A.viridis isoform belonging to the Kern that is up-regulated in the gastrodem of symbiotic anemones. doi:10.1371/journal.pgen.1002187.g006</p><p>were also expressed more highly in the gastroderm, the symbiont hosting tissue. Functional annotation associated with sub-cellular localization of the Kern gene products allowed us to draw a map of the 39 genes differentially regulated in the symbiotic and aposymbiotic states <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">(Figure 8</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Autotrophy and heterotrophy</head><p>One of the first conclusions from our present model is that many genes that are present in higher abundance in the aposymbiotic state are associated with active vesicle trafficking, both in the endocytotic and secretory pathways, as opposed to the many membrane-bound proteins associated with cellular recognition and adhesion coded by genes in higher abundance in the symbiotic state <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">(Table 1</ref> and <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">Figure 8</ref>). Under aposymbiotic conditions, transcription of several proteins controlling trafficking was markedly enhanced. These include TRAPPC2 and TRAPPC10 (Kern # 22 and 23), which are members of the TRAPP complexes that regulate endoplasmic reticulum (ER) to post-golgi vesicular trafficking <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref>, thus attesting for more active de novo biosynthesis in the aposymbiotic anemone than in the symbiotic host. As part of the same line of evidence, the highly differentially expressed gene AP-2 sigma-1 (Kern # 38) codes for a key protein in the formation of clathrin-coated vesicle <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29]</ref>, implying increased endocytic trafficking. Among other aposymbiotic marker genes, HVCN1 and SLC30a (Kern # 26 &amp; 36) are two ion channels shown to be present in phagosomes and late endosomal/ lysosomal vesicles, respectively <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[30,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b30">31]</ref>. Of note, our dedicated array comprises several oligonucleotide probes for various rab mRNAs (including rab1a, 2a, 7a, 8a and 11a). Rab proteins have been shown to control vesicular trafficking in various species including symbiotic anemones <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[32]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[33]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[34]</ref> where the symbionts have been shown to detour host membrane trafficking resulting in failure of host lysosomes fuse with the symbiosomal membrane <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[34]</ref>. However, in our array results, none of the Av_rab genes were differentially expressed. This does not preclude a role of these Rab proteins in A. viridis symbiosis, as expression regulation may be at the translational level. Interestingly, the fact that vesicular trafficking appears to be much more active in aposymbiotic A. viridis corroborates with heterotrophy, which mostly rely on predation, digestion and de novo synthesis, as opposed to autotrophic symbiotic anemones, in which 60% of carbon flux is provided by symbionts <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">[35]</ref>. Numerous studies have characterized glycerol, lipids and amino acids as the major mobile compounds transferred from the symbiont (reviewed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4]</ref>). At the level of metabolism pathways, Phosphoenolpyruvate carboxykinase (PEPCK-C; Kern # 28) had enhanced expression in aposymbiotic conditions. This enzyme catalyzes the rate-controlling step of gluconeogenesis when pyruvate is used as the substrate. Two metabolic pathways can initiate gluconeogenesis: the PEPCK-C dependent pathway, which is fuelled by pyruvate (product of glycolysis), and the PEPCK-C independent pathway, which is fuelled by glycerol <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[36]</ref>. As glycerol is acquired from the symbiont, PEPCK-C is indeed expected to be down-regulated in the symbiotic state.</p><p>In zooxanthellate anemones, lipids are the second most abundant transferred mobile compounds from the symbiont <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4]</ref> therefore requiring up-regulation by the host of several key regulatory enzymes for fatty acid metabolism. Although mobile compounds have been identified using radioactive tracers <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>, compound transfer pathways from the symbiont remain to be characterized. Four Kern genes were involved in lipid processing pathways, LSD-2 (lipid storage droplet), SDR12 (terpenoid metabolism), 2-hydroxyacyl-CoA lyase 1 and NPC2. These 4 genes were up-regulated in the symbiotic state (Kern # 2, 13, 15, 17 in <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">Table 1</ref>). 2-hydroxyacyl-CoA lyase 1 is responsible for fatty acid alpha-oxidation, a modification specific to fatty acids synthesized from chloroplastic organisms <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[37]</ref>. NPC2 (AvNPC2-D, Kern # 2) is among the most up-regulated genes, substantiating another study which noted that a NPC2 transcript was up-regulated in symbiotic Aiptasia pulchella anemones <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[38]</ref>. NPC2 acts in synergy with NPC1 in the transport of sterols (cholesterol) using the late The presence of symbionts activates the expression of calumenin and sym32 genes via an unknown mechanism. The CRS of the Sym32 protein is recognized as substrate by the activated vitamin K cycle (vitamin K is a cofactor produced from the photosynthetic organism) and in turn is c-carboxylated. Meanwhile, the Calumenin represses the VKOR protein, inhibiting the c-carboxylase. Two forms of Sym32 are thus expected to be produced from this pathway: the Glu-Sym32 and Gla-Sym32 electrophoretypes (likely corresponding to the two spots PI = 8.2 and PI = 7.9, respectively <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">[51]</ref>). Only Sym32 (PI = 8.2) is found to be associated with the symbiosome membrane, underlying a novel functionality for Sym32 and c-carboxylation. doi:10.1371/journal.pgen.1002187.g007 endosomal/lysosomal system <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">[39]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[40]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">[41]</ref>. Noticeably, NPC1 and NPC2 are preferentially expressed in the gastroderm <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">(Table 2</ref>). Based on their tissue expression profile and symbiosis-related regulation, NPC1 and NPC2 appear to be major candidate genes for the transport in A. viridis of sterol compounds produced by Symbiodinium.</p><p>Another notable difference between aposymbiotic and symbiotic states is that aposymbiotic-specific Kern genes showed no tissue expression preference. This is in marked opposition to the numerous symbiosis-related Kern genes expressed principally in the gastroderm. Hence, expression of the latter is both limited to the symbiont-containing cells and correlated with the presence of Symbiodinium. Although the mechanisms underlying such control are yet to be characterized, several molecular dialogs between host and symbiont can be envisaged.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Recognition and non-self tolerance by A. viridis</head><p>The Complement C3 (C3) is a precursor protein involved in adaptive immunity in vertebrates and also in cellular recognition, inflammatory processes and phagocytosis in invertebrates <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[42,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b42">43]</ref>. C3 thus appears central to non-self response in metazoans and homologs have been identified throughout the metazoans, including cnidarians <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[42,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b43">44]</ref>. In the coral Acropora millepora, one C3-like protein has been shown to localize in close association with the symbiosome in the gastroderm layer, supporting a role in recognition of Symbiodinium <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">[44]</ref>. In sea anemones, there are three C3 isoforms in the non-symbiotic N. vectensis genome and a minimum of four different C3 isoforms were identified in the A. viridis EST dataset (PG and CS, personal communication). We monitored the expression of two of these: AvC3-1 and AvC3-2. Although AvC3-1 expression was mainly restricted to the gastroderm and may well represent the A. millepora functional homolog, no differential expression was observed between symbiotic and aposymbiotic anemones (validated by qPCR, <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figure 5</ref>). On the other hand, AvC3-2 (Kern # 37) was expressed in both tissue layers, but was strongly repressed in the presence of symbionts. The functional divergence between the different C3  <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">(Table 1)</ref>, each gene product from the Kern set was assigned a specific sub-cellular compartment or secretion pathway: ExtCell; Extra Cellular milieu; Cyt, Cytosol; Nu, Nucleus; TGN, Trans Golgi Network; ER, Endoplasmic reticulum; LD, Lipid droplets; Mit, Mitochondrion; Per, Peroxisome; Lys, Lysosome; Phag, Phagosome; EE, Early Endosome; RE, Recycling Endosome; LE, Late Endosome; Zoox, Zooxanthellae. The left and right moieties of the diagram show genes with increase transcript abundance in aposymbiotic and symbiotic states, respectively. Circles (aposymbiotic), barrels (solute carrier), and hexagons (symbiotic) represent gene expression specific to epidermis (E, dark grey), gastroderm (G, light grey) or both (E&amp;G, white). Trans-membrane domains are shown by appendages. Each gene number has the corresponding name indicated in the list on the right. Gene products in dashed grey are candidate proteins that could potentially (hypothetic) be present at the perisymbiotic space. doi:10.1371/journal.pgen.1002187.g008</p><p>isoforms and their relative participation in Symbiodinium tolerance remains to be determined. However, based on their respective expression profiles in A. viridis, it is conceivable that recognition of and response to Symbiodinium may be carried out by different C3 paralogs.</p><p>Another recognition process that we uncovered in our experiment is related to the vitamin K-dependent (VKD) ccarboxylation of Sym32, under the control of the Calumenin protein. In human, Calumenin proteins are composed of 6 to 7 Ca 2+ binding EF hand domains. They are principally present in the Endoplasmic Reticulum (ER) due to specific ER retention motifs at their COOH termini <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b44">45,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b45">46]</ref>. Their differences in function are unclear, but they are associated with Ca 2+ dependent processes, especially with post-translational VKD c-carboxylation of several proteins <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref>. The increase of intracellular vitamin K (a cofactor produced from plant) activates two proteins conserved throughout metazoans: Vitamin K1 2,3-Epoxide Reductase (VKOR) and c-Carboxylase. The latter recognizes carboxylase recognition sites (CRS) in newly synthesized proteins and adds a CO 2 group to adjacent glutamic acid (Glu) residues resulting in the production of c-carboxyglutamic acid (Gla)-containing proteins <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">[47,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b47">48]</ref>. VKD proteins have been mainly explored in mammals and include bone marrow proteins such as Osteocalcin, Matrix Gla Protein and Periostin (PN) which are involved in bone formation <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">[49]</ref>. The vitamin K cycle is itself under the negative control of Calumenin <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b45">46]</ref> ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Figure 7B</ref>). In A. viridis, the Calumenin homolog AvCALU-a (Kern # 1) was the most upregulated gene of the symbiotic state detected in the microarray experiments ( <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">Table 1)</ref>. It is also preferentially expressed in gastrodermal cells. It contains an ER retention motif and is thus expected to down-regulate the VKD c-carboxylation in the ER of zooxanthellate A. viridis cells.</p><p>Sym32 was first characterized by Weis and colleagues as a symbiosis-specific protein that is over-represented at the perisymbiotic membrane of the zooxanthellate anemone A. elegantissima (AeSym32), but also present at the surface of gastrodermal vesicles in the aposymbiotic state <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b49">50]</ref>. In A. viridis, the Sym32 ortholog (AvSym32, Kern # 4) is up-regulated by more than 40 fold in the symbiotic state and is principally expressed in the gastroderm ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figure 5</ref>, <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">Table 1 and Table 2</ref>). Both AeSym32 and AvSym32 are composed of two fasciclin I (FasI) domains <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">(Figure 7)</ref>, functionally associated with cell-cell recognition and thus potentially involved in anemone-zooxanthellae interaction <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b50">51]</ref>. Importantly, in both sea anemones, the first FasI domain of Sym32 is highly similar in sequence to the first FasI domain of PN, and contains a sequence motif very similar to the CRS domain of PN characterized in vertebrates <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">[49]</ref>. Sym32 is thus an implicit substrate for the c-Carboxylase in sea anemones. As part of the same line of evidence, a 2D immunoblot of zooxanthellate A. elegantissima extract hybridized with an anti-Sym32 antibody showed the presence of two spots of 32 KDa, one at PI = 7.9 and the other at PI = 8.2 <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">[51]</ref>. Such a PI difference for the same protein could very well correspond to difference between Glu and Gla containing Sym32 proteins since c-carboxyglutamic acid decreases the PI of a protein (e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b51">[52]</ref>). However, analysis of freshly isolated Symbiodinium (FIZ, where most of the perisymbiosomal membrane -of host origin -remains attached around the isolated Symbiodinium cell) of A. elegantissima showed the disappearance of the PI = 7.9 spot in favor of the PI = 8.2 spot <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>. These experiments infer that the Glu-Sym32 protein would localize to the perisymbiotic membrane. Since c-carboxyglutamic acid residues have been shown to modify the three dimensional structure and Ca 2+ binding affinity, Glu-Sym32 and Gla-Sym32 would show different ligand properties <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">[53]</ref>. Moreover, up-regulation of Calumenin shown in our work suggests an inhibition of c-carboxylation which would favor the production of Glu-Sym32 in zooxanthellate A. viridis cells ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Figure 7B)</ref>. Thus, the vitamin K-dependent c-carboxylation of Sym32, with its effect on interpartner recognition and the symbiotic process, is definitively a pathway that should be investigated.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Carbonic anhydrases and the transport of bicarbonate from seawater to the zooxanthellae</head><p>The photosynthetic symbionts are separated from the surrounding seawater by several host membranes: membranes of the epidermal cell layer, the collagenous basal membrane, gastrodermal cells, and perisymbiotic vesicles. The main source of inorganic carbon (Ci) for photosynthesis is seawater bicarbonate (HCO <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3</ref> 2 ), which implies transport of exogenous inorganic carbon through these layers of animal tissue <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b53">54]</ref>. In seawater (pH 8.2), most inorganic carbon is in the form of HCO <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3</ref> 2 , a form that needs carrier-mediation to cross membranes, and that is not readily converted to CO 2 in the absence of enzymatic action <ref type="bibr" target="#b54">[55,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b55">56]</ref>. The currently accepted model for external Ci uptake by the host involves an H + -ATPase acidifying the boundary layer where bicarbonate is converted to CO 2 by an external (likely membranebound) carbonic anhydrase isoform <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>. The uncharged CO molecule then diffuses into the epidermal cell following the concentration gradient created by the extrusion of H + in the external medium. Once in the animal cytoplasm, CO 2 is equilibrated with HCO 3 2 according to the intracellular pH by another CA isoform, which prevents back-diffusion of CO 2 (for review see <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>). The mechanism of transport of Ci through the other membranes to the symbionts is currently debated (for reviews, see <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b56">57,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b57">58]</ref>). However, previous works have highlighted the role of a CA localized on the perisymbiotic <ref type="bibr" target="#b58">[59]</ref> or algal membrane <ref type="bibr" target="#b59">[60]</ref>.</p><p>According to this model, carbonic anhydrases are crucial enzymes for carbon supply to symbiont photosynthesis. In the present study, the expression of two different carbonic anhydrases (Av_CA2-c and Av_CA2-m) was monitored. Both show highly enhanced expression in symbiotic specimens compared with aposymbiotic ones (4 and 2.9 fold, respectively), suggesting that both isoforms could be involved in the symbiosis/metabolic exchanges between partners. This result is consistent with the relevant work of Weis and her collaborators <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b58">59,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b60">61]</ref>, showing that enzyme activity and transcript quantity are higher in symbiotic than in non-symbiotic specimens of sea anemones A. pulchella and A. elegantissima.</p><p>AvCA2-c isoform, the cytosolic isoform, is equally expressed in both tissue layers. We suggest that AvCA2-c catalyzes the intracellular reversible hydration/dehydration of CO 2 into HCO <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3</ref> 2 to facilitate the transport of CO 2 through the membranes and cells <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">(Figure 8</ref>). AvCA2-m is a membrane-bound isoform specifically expressed in the gastrodermal layer of anemones where symbionts are located. This membrane-bound isoform can be located either on the plasma membrane of the gastrodermal cells, or on the perisymbiotic membrane surrounding the symbiont. In the first case, AvCA2-m would favor the transfer of CO 2 from one cell layer to another by preventing back-diffusion of CO 2 through membranes. In the second case, this isoform would catalyze the final conversion of HCO <ref type="bibr">3 2</ref> into CO 2 for photosynthetic needs. It should be noted that, since in N. vectensis at least six different isoforms of carbonic anhydrases have been identified (AM and D. Zoccola, personal communication), other A. viridis CA isoforms are expected to contribute in the Ci transport from seawater to Symbiodinium.</p><p>The previous model of Ci transport assumed that CO 2 crosses membranes by diffusion through concentration gradients between both sides of the cell plasma membrane. For most of the past century, gas molecules such as CO 2 were presumed to cross biological membranes merely by diffusing through the lipid phase. This view was challenged recently by studies demonstrating the permeability of water channel aquaporins and certain Rh-family members to CO 2 <ref type="bibr" target="#b61">[62]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b62">[63]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b63">[64]</ref>. The physiological function of those channels for CO 2 transport seems to be particularly important since, for instance, one Rh protein (RhAG) accounts for up to 50% of the CO 2 transport of human red blood cells <ref type="bibr" target="#b64">[65]</ref>. In A. viridis, we identified two RhAG isoforms, one of which (Av_RhAG1) is preferentially expressed in the gastroderm of zooxanthellate anemones ( <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">Table 2)</ref>. We suggest that these proteins could have a role within the holobiont to facilitate CO 2 uptake, possibly in conjunction with the membrane-bound CA2. In human erythrocytes, RhAG and CA2 are part of the same Band 3 multiprotein complex involved in anion exchanges <ref type="bibr" target="#b65">[66,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b66">67]</ref>. It is worth mentioning that a role of Av_RhAG1 in NH transport is equally valid, as in the cnidarian-dinoflagellate symbiosis, ammonium resulting from host metabolism is not excreted into the surrounding water but is immediately re-assimilated by the algae, either through diffusion or by a transporter, and then recycled <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b67">68]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Is the combination of gene duplication and gastrodermspecific expression a symbiosis adaptation by anthozoans?</head><p>Within the set of Kern genes up-regulated in the symbiotic condition, we noticed that some of the genes with a proposed function in symbiosis, including Sym32, Calumenin, and NPC2, were expressed as 2 or more related copies. Phylogenetic analysis allowed the conclusion to be made that there were cnidarianspecific gene duplications. Remarkably, our expression results in A. viridis showed that these cnidarian-specific duplicates were both preferentially expressed in the gastroderm (hosting zooxanthellae) and in the symbiotic condition.</p><p>Such cnidarian-specific gene duplications could correlate with the amenability of various cnidarians to have accepted photosynthetic endosymbionts during evolution. However, these gene duplications are not restricted to symbiotic anemones (e.g. N. vectensis). Their selective advantage with regard to symbiosis therefore remains to be determined, together with the origin of endosymbiosis in cnidarians: was photosynthetic symbiosis acquired or lost in various branches of the phylum? Moreover, at the transcriptional level, we have shown for several cases that expression of one isoform among the duplicated gene copies was specifically up-regulated both in the gastroderm and in the presence of symbionts. Thus, we suggest that these neofunctionalizations would be associated with the physiological constraints of endosymbiosis and would be tuned to the presence of zooxanthellae by transcriptional control. It is not known how such control is exerted or whether such gene regulation is restricted to symbiotic cnidarians. Comparative tissue expression of the different orthologs in non-symbiotic cnidarians, such as N. vectensis, would provide insight into the adaptive origin of symbiosis.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Coral bleaching and transcription plasticity</head><p>One of our most unexpected results was that outside the subset of Kern genes, many differentially expressed genes were up-or down-regulated in only few individual anemones, despite the fact that anemones were in a fixed symbiotic or aposymbiotic state before sampling. Similar inter-individual variable expression profiles have already been quoted in two studies comparing the response of A. millepora corals to environmental changes <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b68">69]</ref>.</p><p>On the other hand, several groups studying symbiosis breakdown in diverse cnidarian species showed that different cellular mechanisms were observed during loss of zooxanthellae, including apoptosis, necrosis, exocytosis, or phagocytosis <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>. Such variability in the cellular processes involved may reflect distinct causes of bleaching, i.e. different responses to variable environmental changes. Indeed, bleaching can be caused by a multitude of environmental stressors including changes in seawater temperature, salinity, ultraviolet radiation, increased sedimentation, nutrients and pollutants <ref type="bibr" target="#b69">[70]</ref>. In response to different stresses, the host-associated microbiota is greatly and specifically modified within the whole holobiont (i.e. the community composed of cnidarian host, dinoflagellates and associated microbes) <ref type="bibr" target="#b70">[71]</ref>.</p><p>In the case of the Mediterranean symbiotic cnidarian used here, Symbiodinium belongs to the same clade temperate A. However, our results on the gene copy numbers of only 3 genes (EF2, SPS and APX) showed unexpected high polymorphism in the Symbiodinium hosted by anemones collected from neighboring location. In addition, we showed that the abundance of zooxanthellae per host cell is variable within our set of symbiotic sea anemones. Thus, variation in the associated microbiota or in Symbiodinium sub-clades may have stable extended effects on the host gene expression profile. This underlines that, although the term ''bleached'' defines one visual phenotype resulting from various responses, it can result from diverse expression profiles, and probably from various conditions of aposymbiosis. Indeed, not all bleached cnidarians die.</p><p>A. viridis can be sampled at different time points without harm to the anemone, and is therefore an excellent model organism for kinetics experiments. Additionally, since sea anemones are noncalcifying anthozoans, they allow the study of symbiosis-associated processes outside the cross-regulatory pathways of mineralization found in corals. It would be of interest, using the same array technique, to monitor the kinetics of the specific gene expression response to one or combination of different environmental stressors. In addition to giving a transcriptional map of the genespecific response to stress, it would highlight whether different bleaching expression profiles are fixed in time or whether they tend to stabilize at a unique Kern profile after an adaptation period. Moreover, the unique amenability of A. viridis to separate the ectoderm from the endoderm will permit us to partition the scope of the environmental response in the cellular layer hosting the symbionts (gastroderm) and in the tissue in direct contact to the milieu (epidermis).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Materials and Methods</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Collection and maintenance of A. viridis specimens</head><p>Mediterranean sea anemone specimens, Anemonia viridis (Forskål, 1775), were collected in five locations on and around the French Riviera ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure S2</ref>): Antibes (Salis and Croutons sites), Villefranche-sur-Mer, Monaco and Menton. A total of 5 symbiotic and 6 aposymbiotic specimens were used in this study.</p><p>Symbiotic specimens Sy1 and Sy3-5 were collected from Antibes Croutons <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">(Figure S2</ref>), Sy2 was collected from Antibes Salis. These anemones were maintained for several months in seawater aquaria at 17.060.5uC with weekly water renewal. A metal halide lamp (HQI-TS 400 W, Philips) provided light at a constant saturating irradiance of 250 mmol m 22 s 21 on a 12/12 h light/dark cycle. Naturally-occurring aposymbiotic animals were sampled from the public aquaria of the Oceanographic Museum of Monaco and originated from different sites in Monaco (AS1 and AS2) or Menton (AS3). The three other aposymbiotic specimens were obtained after either a thermal stress-induced bleaching (AS4, AS5, collected in Antibes-Crouton) or a treatment with the catalase inhibitor aminotriazol (AS6, collected in Villefranche-sur-Mer, <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>). These latter 3 anemones were maintained in the dark (necessary to keep them bleached) for a minimum of 2 months. Both symbiotic and stress induced aposymbiotic anemones were fed twice a week with frozen Artemia salina.</p><p>Sy3, Sy4 and Sy5 specimens were later subjected to an 8uCtemperature increase (17 to 25uC) to assess imposed stress response. Tentacles were sampled over a 48 h kinetic period (t0, t24h and t48h) and then subjected to RT-qPCR experiments.</p><p>Specimen sampling was always at 10:00 (2 hours after light start) to avoid circadian effect of gene expression fluctuations.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Nucleic acid extraction</head><p>RNA extraction. Total RNA was extracted from whole tentacle samples (epidermis plus gastroderm and zooxanthellae) or separated tissues using Trizol Reagent (Invitrogen), as described previously <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref>. Gastrodermal (gastroderm and zooxanthellae) and epidermis layers were separated as described previously <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>. A DNase treatment (RQ1-DNAse, Promega) was performed on the RNA sample to avoid genomic DNA contamination.</p><p>gDNA extraction. Genomic DNA was extracted as follows: samples (whole tentacles, separated tissue layers (epidermis or gastroderm) or cultured zooxanthellae) were first immersed in [100 mM Tris pH = 8.2; 100 mM EDTA; 500 mM NaCl; 2.5% triton] to block DNases, and then transferred into [4 M Thiocyanante Guanidium; mM Sodium citrate; 1% Triton X100; 50 mg/ml Proteinase K; 5 mM EDTA; 50 mM DTT] before potter homogenization. Homogenates were incubated at 55uC for 1 hour. Genomic DNA was purified by phenol/chloroform/ isoamyl alcohol extraction and isopropanol precipitation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. viridis oligoarray hybridizations</head><p>Over 2,000 genes were selected from the A. viridis clustered and annotated EST collection <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref> for their putative participation in symbiotic processes. Genes were selected by keyword search in their functional annotation for matches with the following terms: intracellular transport, metabolic processes (lipids, proteins), signal transduction, organelle organisation and biogenesis, response to stress, trans-membrane, apoptosis and cell death. Two thousand 60-mer oligonucleotides were designed (Eurogentec, Belgium) and printed on slides in triplicate (Eurogentec, Belgium). A luciferase oligonucleotide was also spotted as an external control. This A. viridis Oligo2K version 1.0 oligoarray is fully described under platform record GPL10546, stored in the Gene Expression Omnibus (GEO) at NCBI (http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo).</p><p>cDNA synthesis and labelling was performed from total RNA using the ChipShot Direct labelling and Clean-up system (Promega), according to the manufacturer's instructions. Five ng of a Lux mRNA exogenous standard was added to each mRNA sample before labelling. RNA quality was evaluated using the Agilent Bioanalyzer 2100 and quantified on a ND-1000 Spectrophotometer (NanoDrop). Then, 500 ng of each labeled sample were mixed in Hi-RPM hybridization buffer (Agilent), and incubated on the array overnight at 47uC. Slides were scanned after post-hybridization washes, using a GenePix 4200A scanner (Axon Instruments). Data acquisition and quality control were performed using Genepix Pro software.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Experimental design and statistical analyses</head><p>Dye-swap experiments were performed for each hybridization condition. Two different sets of hybridizations were performed ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure S3</ref>): i) symbiotic versus aposymbiotic specimens and ii) epidermis versus gastroderm tissues. The same AS6 extract was used as the sample reference in all experiments. Experimental data and associated microarray designs were deposited in the National Center for Biotechnology Information (NCBI) Gene Expression Omnibus (GEO) (http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/) under SuperSeries record: GSE22375 and platform record GPL10546.</p><p>Background (positive offset of 50) was evaluated according as described in <ref type="bibr" target="#b71">[72]</ref>. The data were normalized by the print-tip loess method (within-array normalization) and by quantile method (between-array normalization) using the LimmaGUI package from Bioconductor <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref>. Means of ratios from all comparisons were calculated for each gene, and B test analysis was done using LimmaGUI. Differential gene expression was determined by the Bayesian statistical method (B value), with a cut-off of zero for the B value and a log ratio |M|.0.590 as significant. All normalized data sets were registered in the GEO database under the accession number GSE22375.</p><p>Cluster 3.0 software <ref type="bibr" target="#b72">[73]</ref> was used to estimate the hierarchical clustering between individual anemone array results. The following parameters (complete, average, and centroid linkage) were tested and gave similar results.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Real-time quantitative PCR experiments</head><p>Specific primers amplifying around 100 bp were designed using the software Primer3 <ref type="bibr" target="#b73">[74]</ref>. The primer sequences used in this study are listed in <ref type="table">Table S3</ref>. Amplicon specificity for either A. viridis or Symbiodinium was tested against epidermal (extracts without zooxanthellae) or CZ (zooxanthellae culture) extracts, respectively. Expected length of the amplicons was checked by agarose gel electrophoresis after regular PCR amplification. Primer efficiencies were determined using standard curve analysis with a 10-fold dilution series of pooled cDNA from both control and treated samples (data not shown), and ranged from 1.8 to 2. The qPCR products were sequenced (Macrogen Inc, Korea) and all matched the expected product identities.</p><p>cDNAs were prepared using SuperScriptII reverse transcriptase (Invitrogen) and a mixture of oligodT and random primers, according to the manufacturer's instructions. Transcript level quantification was performed using the SYBR green fluorescence method and a Light Cycler 480 (Roche). The PCR conditions were as follows: 16SYBR green mix (LC480 SYBR Green Master Mix, Roche), 100 nM primers and 2.5 ng of cDNA in a total volume of 15 ml. Each sample was run in triplicate using the following PCR parameters: 94uC for 10 min, followed by 40 cycles of 15 s at 94uC, 20 s at 60uC and 15 s at 72uC, then a dissociation curve step (60 to 95uC) to confirm the absence of non-specific products. The dissociation curves showed a single amplification product and no primer dimers.</p><p>Several control genes were chosen based on the microarray results as a whole (most stably expressed genes, in all tested conditions), and the expression stability of ten putative control genes was evaluated using the GeNorm software <ref type="bibr" target="#b74">[75]</ref>. A reliable normalization factor was calculated based on the expression level of the most stable control genes. The control genes finally selected in this study are RPLP0, RCC2, and COP-c. Expression levels of target genes were normalized using the normalization factor described above and the results given as expression relative to the aposymbiotic specimen (AS6) value as calibrator (reference). The significance of the results was tested using t-tests (software Jump 5.1, Cary, USA). Results were considered statistically significant when P,0.05.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Bleaching quantification</head><p>The relative abundance of zooxanthellae in A. viridis cells was quantified using a real-time quantitative qPCR method. For each organism, three nuclear genes were chosen from available datasets: COP-c (Coatomer subunit gamma), RCC2 (Regulator of Chromosome Condensation protein 2) and NPC1 (Niemann Pick type C1) for A. viridis, and EF2 (Elongation factor 2), Sucrose phosphate synthase (SPS) and Ascorbate peroxidase (APX) for Symbiodinium clade temperate A. Primer design was performed using Primer3 and the same parameters described above; the primer sequences are given in the <ref type="table">Table S3</ref>. Standard curves were generated with six logarithm dilutions of corresponding cloned sequences. Results are expressed as relative quantification of Symbiodinium nuclei (or nuclear genes) to A.viridis nuclei.</p><p>(CeNPC2, NP_497671), N. vectensis (NvNPC2a, XP_001627355 &amp; NvNPC2b, XP_001622874), A. viridis (AvNPC2a, CL214Ct1 &amp; AvNPC2d, CL1319Ct1), Trichoplax adherans (TaNPC2,XP_ 002109765), Saccharomyces cerevisiae (S.cerevisiae, Q12408) and Schizosaccharomyces pombe (S.pombe, Q9C0X9) were aligned with MultAlin and ClustalW. Bayesian phylogenetic tree was calculated using MrBayes 3-1.2. (TIF) <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Figure S7</ref> Phylogenetic analysis of the Sym32/Periostin/BGH3 gene family. A. Sea anemone FasI-containing proteins. Protein sequences for A. elegantissima Sym32 (Aesym32; AAF65308), A. viridis Sym32 (AvSym32; CL363Contig1) and Periostin (AvPN; Rav02077g18) and N. vectensis 2Sym (Nv2Sym; misassembeled [see jgi ESTcluster 2667343_11] and corrected from XP_001629263 and XP_001629262) and Periostin (NvPN; extended from jgi|Nemve1|238669|estExt_fgenesh1_pg.C_70144) were aligned using MultAlin. Signal peptides (yellow highlight) were predicted using SignalP. B. Individual FasI domain alignment and phylogenetic relationships. All the different FasI domains from Human Periostin (HsPN1-4; Q15063) and BIGH3 (Hs_BGH31-4; Q15582) were aligned with those of the sea anemone homologs using MultAlin. The CRS (Carboxylase Recognition Site, as described in <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">[49]</ref>) of the HsPN-1 and HsBIGH3-1 first FasI domains is highlighted. Using the segment of the sequence alignment conserved in all sequences, the best-fitted substitution model was evaluated using ProtTest. Using parameter [LG+G; gamma = 1.755], a Maximum Likelihood tree was determined using phyML. Bayesian phylogenetic tree was calculated using MrBayes 3-1.2. (TIF) </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Symbiodinium quantification by real-time quantitative PCR (symbiont to host nuclei ratio). Symbiodinium nuclear EF2, SPS, APX and A. viridis nuclear COP-c gene copy numbers were assessed by qPCR performed on total genomic DNA extracts from 5 symbiotic anemones (Sy1-Sy5), 6 aposymbiotic anemones (AS1-AS6), in vitro cultured Symbiodinium (CZ) and epidermal tissue fraction (Ep). The histogram represents the relative copy number ratios of EF2, SPS and APX to COP-c, relative to the Sy1 sea anemone, expressed in fold number. doi:10.1371/journal.pgen.1002187.g001</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Differentially expressed genes (DEG) between symbiotic and aposymbiotic anemones. A. Heatmap diagram of DEG. Left column (Sy-Apo) represents expression of the 58 up-(SY) and 78 down-regulated (APO) genes (|M|.0.59, B.0) identified from the batch comparison of the 5 pooled symbiotic versus the 6 pooled aposymbiotic anemones. The following columns to the right represent expression of the same genes in each individual symbiotic anemone (Sy1-5) compared with the pooled aposymbiotic (-Apo) anemones and in each individual aposymbiotic anemone (AS1-6) compared with the pooled symbiotic (-Sy) anemones. The dendogram underneath the heatmap represents the cluster array tree result performed on the entire result dataset (with Cluster3). The color intensity code representing M value intervals is shown below. B. A given gene can be differentially expressed in the batch analysis (SY or APO) although only differentially expressed in few individual sea anemones. Histogram shows the number of individual anemones (3-11) each gene is differentially expressed in. Top and bottom panels: gene distribution of SY and APO genes, respectively. doi:10.1371/journal.pgen.1002187.g002</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>CA2-m, CA2-c, and NPC2-D expression in response to imposed thermal stress. Expression of CA2-m, CA2-c and NPC2-D after 0, 24 h and 48 h of 8uC heat stress was measured using RT-qPCR. Three anemones (Sy3-5) were assayed. Gene expression, normalized to RCC2 and COP-c, is given related to t0. Error bars represent standard error. doi:10.1371/journal.pgen.1002187.g003</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Av_Cluster</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Venn diagram of genes expressed in sea anemone tissues. Distribution of genes (only of cnidarian origin) expressed in the epidermis (Ep) or gastroderm (Ga) compartments (circles), relative to their up-regulation (rectangles) in symbiotic (SY) or aposymbiotic (APO) conditions. doi:10.1371/journal.pgen.1002187.g004</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Tissue-specific expression of targeted genes. RT-qPCRs were performed on the epidermal (Ep) and gastrodermal (Ga) total RNA extracts from 3 different sea anemones. The histogram shows the relative Ep (gray) versus Ga (green) expression of the genes listed on the histogram (error bars represent standard error). doi:10.1371/journal.pgen.1002187.g005</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Figure 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Gene duplication of NPC2 and Calumenin in anthozoans. Calumenin (A) and NPC2 (B) homologs alignments (Figure S5 and S6) were subjected to PhyML maximum likelihood phylogenetic analyses. Best-fitted substitution models were: [LG+I+G+F; I = 0.029 F = empirical and gamma = 1.127] for Calumenin and [WAG+I+G; I = 0.036 and gamma = 5.836] for NPC2. Hs: Human, Dr: Danio rerio, Ci: Ciona intestinalis, Sp, Strongylocentrotus purpuratus, Tc: Tribolium castaneum, Dm: Drosophila melanogaster, Ce: Caenorhabditis elegans, Nv: Nematostella vectensis, Av: Anemonia viridis, Ta: Trichoplax adherans, S.cerevisiae and S.pombe: NPC2 homologs in Saccharomyces cerevisiae (Q12408) and Schizosaccharomyces pombe (Q9C0X9), respectively. Protein sequences are given in</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Figure 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Sym32 gene duplication and putative c-carboxylation regulation model. A. Color code schematization of the PhyML tree for the FasI domains of the Sym32, Periostin (PN) and BGH3 homologs in sea anemones (Ae, A. elegantissima; Av, A. viridis; Nv, N. vectensis) and human (Hs) (see tree in Figure S7b). Each rectangle represents one FasI domain (small yellow rectangles represent the Signal Sequence). FasI domains 1 and 3 are closely related. The first FasI domains of [AeSym32-1, AvSym32-1 and Nv2Sym-1 and -3] are closely related to each other and to a lesser extent with [AvPN-1 and -3, and NvPN-1 and -3] and finally with [HsPN-1 and -3, and HsBGH3-1 and -3]. A similar relationship exists for the FasI domains 2 and 4. AeSym32, AvSym32 and Nv2Sym are probable orthologs, except that Sym32 appears as the first half of Nv2Sym. The putative ortholog of HsPN is NvPN. B. Heuristic Model.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Figure 8 .</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Model of pathways highlighted in the aposymbiotic and symbiotic states of sea anemones. Based on functional homology and protein signature</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Kern set of symbiotic genes.</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>Sign.</cell><cell></cell><cell>Expected cell</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Array</cell><cell>qPCR</cell></row><row><cell>Av_Cluster</cell><cell cols="2">Pep. TM</cell><cell cols="2">localization* Note</cell><cell>Protein Name</cell><cell>Expected role</cell><cell>Fold</cell><cell>Fold</cell></row><row><cell>av01015l05</cell><cell>Nv</cell><cell></cell><cell>ER</cell><cell>EF hand, Ca 2+ binding</cell><cell>Calumenin precursor (Calu-a)</cell><cell>Ca 2+ binding</cell><cell>7.29</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>and Vitamin K cycle</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>CL1319Ct1</cell><cell>SP</cell><cell></cell><cell>End, Lys</cell><cell>Cholesterol transport</cell><cell>Niemann Pick type C2 protein</cell><cell>metabolism-FA</cell><cell>4.39</cell><cell>4.6</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>homolog (NPC2-D)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>CL4283Ct1</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Cyt</cell><cell>CO 2 conversion; pH</cell><cell>Carbonic anhydrase 2 cytosolic (CA2-c)</cell><cell>pH homeostasis</cell><cell>4.06</cell><cell>13.2</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>regulation</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>CL363Ct1</cell><cell>SP</cell><cell>TM</cell><cell>Out. pl. mb</cell><cell>Cell adhesion/</cell><cell>Sym32</cell><cell>cell adhesion</cell><cell>3.36</cell><cell>47.8</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>recognition_fasiclin 62</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>CL263Ct1</cell><cell>SP</cell><cell>TM</cell><cell>Out. pl. mb</cell><cell>CO 2 conversion;</cell><cell cols="2">Carbonic anhydrase 2 membrane (CA2-m) pH homeostasis</cell><cell>2.90</cell><cell>8.6</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>pH regulation</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">av01009g10 N.v.</cell><cell></cell><cell>Sec</cell><cell>Cell adhesion/recognition,</cell><cell>Uromodulin domain (URO domain)</cell><cell>cell adhesion</cell><cell>2.66</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>bacterial defense</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">av02058f16 SP</cell><cell></cell><cell>ECM</cell><cell>No collagen domain</cell><cell>Col protein</cell><cell>cell adhesion</cell><cell>2.53</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>detected in sequence</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>av01002j09</cell><cell>N.v.</cell><cell>N.v.</cell><cell>Trans-mb.</cell><cell>Ig-like domain;</cell><cell cols="3">Tyrosine kinase receptor (Tyr-K Receptor) receptor signaling 2.35</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Tyrosine-protein kinase</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>av02120i19</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Inn. pl. mb</cell><cell>Intracellular signalling;</cell><cell>Catenin delta</cell><cell>cell adhesion</cell><cell>2.17</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>cytoskeletal regulation</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>CL1994Ct1</cell><cell></cell><cell>TM</cell><cell>Mit, Per</cell><cell>Mitochondrial fission</cell><cell>Mitochondrial fission 1 protein (FIS1)</cell><cell>vesicle</cell><cell>1.98</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>av02092k17</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Cyt</cell><cell>Anti-apoptotic</cell><cell>E3 ubiquitin-protein ligase RNF34</cell><cell cols="2">Ubiquitin pathway 1.87</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>CL3310Ct1</cell><cell>N.v.</cell><cell></cell><cell>Sec</cell><cell>Oxidative defense</cell><cell>Secretory glutathione peroxidase</cell><cell>antioxidant</cell><cell>1.85</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>CL298Ct1</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>lipid droplet</cell><cell>Lipid binding; Regulation.</cell><cell>Lipid storage droplets surface-binding</cell><cell>metabolism-FA</cell><cell>1.82</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>of FA &amp; steroid metabolism</cell><cell>protein 2</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">av02096o03 N.v.</cell><cell>N.v.</cell><cell>Out. pl. mb</cell><cell>Collagen production</cell><cell>Prolyl-4-hydroxylase-alpha</cell><cell>Collagen</cell><cell>1.82</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>processing</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>av01005l13</cell><cell>N.v.</cell><cell>N.v.</cell><cell>Per</cell><cell>Fatty acid alpha oxidation</cell><cell>2-hydroxyacyl-CoA lyase 1</cell><cell>metabolism-FA</cell><cell>1.81</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(Plant spec.)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>av01017f01</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Cyt</cell><cell>EF hand, Calcium binding</cell><cell>Visinin-like protein 1</cell><cell>Ca 2+ binding</cell><cell>1.79</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>av02097k23</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Cyt</cell><cell>Terpenoid metabolism (SDR)</cell><cell>Dehydrogenase/reductase_SDR</cell><cell>metabolism-FA</cell><cell>1.72</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>family member 12</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>av01023c17</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Cyt</cell><cell>Ubiquitin carboxyl-terminal</cell><cell>Ubiquitin thioesterase 34 (Ubiquitin</cell><cell cols="2">Ubiquitin pathway 1.71</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>hydrolase 34</cell><cell>hydrolase 34)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>CL187Ct1</cell><cell>SP</cell><cell>TM</cell><cell>Out. pl. mb</cell><cell>ZP domain recognised in</cell><cell>Zona Pellucida-like domain-containing</cell><cell>cell adhesion</cell><cell>1.58</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>receptor-like glycoproteins</cell><cell>protein</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>CL1460Ct1</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Cyt</cell><cell>Catabolism (first step)</cell><cell>Branched-chain-amino-acid</cell><cell>metabolism</cell><cell>21.58</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>of the essential AA (L, I, V)</cell><cell>aminotransferase</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>CL2889Ct1</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Cyt</cell><cell>Dopamine metabolic process</cell><cell>E3 ubiquitin-protein ligase</cell><cell cols="2">Ubiquitin pathway 21.59</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(parkin)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>av01029c01</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Cyt</cell><cell>TRAPPC2 vesicle-mediated</cell><cell>Trafficking protein particle</cell><cell>vesicle</cell><cell>21.60</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>transport (ER to golgi)</cell><cell>complex I sub.2 (Sedlin)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>CL2824Ct1</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Cyt</cell><cell>TRAPPC10 vesicle-mediated</cell><cell>Trafficking protein particle</cell><cell>vesicle</cell><cell>21.63</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>transport (trans-Golgi)</cell><cell>complex II sub.10 (TMEM1)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>CL829Ct1</cell><cell>SP</cell><cell></cell><cell>Sec</cell><cell>Oxidative defense, extracellular</cell><cell>Peroxidasin</cell><cell>antioxidant</cell><cell>21.68</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>matrix, phagocytosis</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>CL1127Ct1</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Cyt</cell><cell>Ion transport &amp; cell volume</cell><cell>STE20</cell><cell>ion transport</cell><cell>21.69</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>CL2771Ct1</cell><cell>SP</cell><cell>TM</cell><cell>Phag</cell><cell>Ion transport &amp; pH</cell><cell>Voltage-gated Hydrogen</cell><cell>ion chanel</cell><cell>21.74</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>regulation, phagocytosis</cell><cell>channel 1 (HVCN1)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>av02120i05</cell><cell>Gal.</cell><cell></cell><cell>Sec</cell><cell>Extracellular matrix and</cell><cell>Galaxin</cell><cell>cell adhesion</cell><cell>21.76</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>cell surface receptor proteins</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>CL240Ct1</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Cyt</cell><cell>Gluconeogenesis</cell><cell>Phosphoenolpyruvate</cell><cell>metabolism</cell><cell>21.81</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(rate-controlling 1st</cell><cell>carboxykinase (PEPCK-C)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>step via pyruvate)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">av02125c09 N.v.</cell><cell>N.v.</cell><cell>End</cell><cell>Metabolism of iodometabolites;</cell><cell>Type III iodothyronine deiodinase</cell><cell>metabolism</cell><cell>21.82</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>inactivation of T4 and T3</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">av02109e14 N.v.</cell><cell>Hyd.</cell><cell>Sec</cell><cell>Oxidoreductase; source of</cell><cell>Polyamine oxidase</cell><cell>antioxidant</cell><cell>21.83</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>ammonium</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Genes differentially expressed (|M|.0.59, B.0) in at least 8 individuals out of our 11 tested anemones were defined as belonging to the ''Kern'' set of symbiotic genes. Each corresponding Uniseq (Av_Cluster) was subjected to a blastX homolog search and analyzed for signal peptide, trans-membrane domain and other protein signatures. When the A. viridis sequence was partial, the N. vectensis (Nv) or Galaxea fascicularis (gene # 27) ortholog was taken into account. From homolog function and protein signature analysis, putative cellular localization and function were assigned. Fold gene expression (symbiotic versus aposymbiotic sea anemones) was determined experimentally from microarrays and qPCR experiments.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Sign.</cell><cell></cell><cell>Expected cell</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Array</cell><cell>qPCR</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Pep. TM</cell><cell cols="2">localization* Note</cell><cell>Protein Name</cell><cell>Expected role</cell><cell>Fold</cell><cell>Fold</cell></row><row><cell>31 av02115o13</cell><cell></cell><cell>Nu, Cyt</cell><cell>Serine/threonine-protein kinase,</cell><cell cols="2">Ataxia telangiectasia and Rad3 related (ATR) DNA damage</cell><cell>21.89</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>PI3/PI4-kinase family</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>32 CL2461Ct1</cell><cell></cell><cell>Cyt</cell><cell>Ubiquitin ligase</cell><cell>Cullin family</cell><cell cols="2">Ubiquitin pathway 21.90</cell></row><row><cell>33 av01046b22</cell><cell></cell><cell>Nu</cell><cell>pre-mRNA splicing</cell><cell>pre-mRNA-splicing factor 18; (PRP18)</cell><cell>RNA processing</cell><cell>22.02</cell></row><row><cell>34 av02084n10</cell><cell></cell><cell>Nu, Cyt</cell><cell>Rev.transcriptase;</cell><cell cols="2">Putative transposon-derived protein ReO_6 transposon</cell><cell>22.12</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Retrotransposon</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>35 av02100k07</cell><cell></cell><cell>Cyt</cell><cell>Detoxification reactive oxygen</cell><cell cols="2">Glutathione S-transferase Y1; (GST class-mu) detoxification</cell><cell>22.15</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>speciess</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>36 av02069c14 N.v.</cell><cell>N.v.</cell><cell>End, Lys</cell><cell>Homeostasis; ion transport</cell><cell>SLC30a2, Zinc transporter 2 (ZnT-2)</cell><cell cols="2">solute transporter 22.24</cell></row><row><cell>37 av01039o13 N.v.</cell><cell></cell><cell>Sec</cell><cell>Can interact with lectins</cell><cell>C3-2 complement</cell><cell>cell adhesion</cell><cell>22.25</cell></row><row><cell>CL627Ct1</cell><cell></cell><cell>Inn. pl. mb</cell><cell cols="2">Clathrin coat assembly protein AP-2 sigma-1</cell><cell>vesicle</cell><cell>22.40</cell></row><row><cell>39 av02114d05 Hyd.</cell><cell></cell><cell>Sec</cell><cell>EGF-like domains; adhesion</cell><cell>Notch-like family</cell><cell>cell adhesion</cell><cell>24.60</cell></row></table><note>*expected sub-cellular localisation: Cyt, cytoplasm; ECM., extracellular matrix; ER, Endoplasmic Reticulum; End, Endosome; Lys, Lysosome; Mit, Mitochodrion; Nu, Nucleus; Per, Peroxisome; Phag, Phagosome; pl.mb. (out. or inn.), plasma membrane (outer or inner); Sec, Secreted; Trans-mb, Trans-membrane.doi:10.1371/journal.pgen.1002187.t001 Table 1. Cont.</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Table 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Examples of A. viridis genes up-regulated in the epidermis (E) or gastroderm (G).</figDesc><table><row><cell>Av Cluster</cell><cell>Expect. cell localization</cell><cell>Protein Name</cell><cell>Expected Role</cell><cell cols="5">DEG Fold Sym/Apo Localization</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Array</cell><cell cols="2">qPCR Array</cell><cell>qPCR</cell></row><row><cell>av01015l05</cell><cell>ER</cell><cell>Calumenin precursor (AvCALUa)</cell><cell>Ca 2+ binding</cell><cell>1 #</cell><cell>7.29</cell><cell></cell><cell>G</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>CL1014Ct1</cell><cell>ER</cell><cell>Calumenin precursor (AvCALUb)</cell><cell>Ca 2+ binding</cell><cell></cell><cell>1.15</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>CL101Ct1</cell><cell>ER</cell><cell>Calumenin precursor (AvCALUc)</cell><cell>Ca 2+ binding</cell><cell></cell><cell>21.27</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>CL363Ct1</cell><cell>Out. pl. mb</cell><cell>Sym32</cell><cell>cell adhesion</cell><cell>4 #</cell><cell>3.36</cell><cell>47.9</cell><cell>G</cell><cell>G</cell></row><row><cell>av02077g18</cell><cell>Out. pl. mb</cell><cell>Periostin</cell><cell>cell adhesion</cell><cell></cell><cell>1.36</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>CL1319Ct1</cell><cell>End</cell><cell>Niemann Pick type C2 protein homolog NPC2-D</cell><cell>metabolism-FA</cell><cell>2 #</cell><cell>4.39</cell><cell>4.6</cell><cell>G</cell><cell>G</cell></row><row><cell>CL214Ct1</cell><cell>End</cell><cell>Niemann Pick type C2 protein homolog NPC2-a</cell><cell>metabolism-FA</cell><cell></cell><cell>21.06</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>CL308Ct1</cell><cell>End</cell><cell>Niemann Pick type C1 protein homolog NPC1</cell><cell>metabolism-FA</cell><cell></cell><cell>1.13</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>CL263Ct1</cell><cell>Out. pl. mb</cell><cell>Carbonic anhydrase 2 membrane (CA2-m)</cell><cell>pH regulation</cell><cell>5 #</cell><cell>2.90</cell><cell>8.6</cell><cell>G</cell><cell>G</cell></row><row><cell>CL4283Ct1</cell><cell>Cyt</cell><cell>Carbonic anhydrase 2 cytosolic (CA2-c)</cell><cell>pH regulation</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>4.06</cell><cell>13.2</cell><cell></cell><cell>ge</cell></row><row><cell>av01043f14</cell><cell>Pl. mb.</cell><cell>Rh AG 1</cell><cell>solute transporter</cell><cell>#</cell><cell>1.58</cell><cell>4.4</cell><cell></cell><cell>G</cell></row><row><cell>av02095l23</cell><cell>Pl. mb.</cell><cell>Rh AG 2</cell><cell>solute transporter</cell><cell></cell><cell>1.11</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>CL506Ct1</cell><cell>Sec</cell><cell>C3-1 complement</cell><cell>cell adhesion</cell><cell></cell><cell>1.47</cell><cell>1.3</cell><cell></cell><cell>G</cell></row><row><cell>av01039o13</cell><cell>Sec</cell><cell>C3-2 complement</cell><cell>cell adhesion</cell><cell>35</cell><cell>22.25</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>CL92Ct2</cell><cell>Sec</cell><cell>MERP-1</cell><cell>cell adhesion</cell><cell></cell><cell>21.57</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>CL194Ct2</cell><cell>Sec</cell><cell>MERP-1</cell><cell>cell adhesion</cell><cell></cell><cell>21.37</cell><cell></cell><cell>G</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>CL51Ct1</cell><cell>Sec</cell><cell>MERP-1</cell><cell>cell adhesion</cell><cell></cell><cell>21.06</cell><cell></cell><cell>G</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>av02096o03</cell><cell>Pl. mb.</cell><cell>Prolyl-4-hydroxylase alpha</cell><cell>collagen processing</cell><cell cols="2">14 # 1.82</cell><cell></cell><cell>G</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>CL3699Ct1</cell><cell>Pl. mb.</cell><cell>Prolyl-4-hydroxylase alpha</cell><cell>collagen processing</cell><cell></cell><cell>21.00</cell><cell></cell><cell>G</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>av02049b06</cell><cell>ER</cell><cell>Procollagen lysine2 oxoglutarate 5 dioxygenase 3</cell><cell>collagen processing</cell><cell></cell><cell>1.24</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>av02062m24</cell><cell>ECM</cell><cell>Collagenase type IV</cell><cell>collagen processing</cell><cell></cell><cell>21.08</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>CL143Ct1</cell><cell>ECM</cell><cell>Collagenase type IV</cell><cell>collagen processing</cell><cell></cell><cell>21.39</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>CL38Ct2</cell><cell>ECM</cell><cell>Collagen-like</cell><cell>collagen precursor</cell><cell></cell><cell>21.07</cell><cell></cell><cell>G</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>CL1481Ct1</cell><cell>ECM</cell><cell>Collagen-like</cell><cell>collagen precursor</cell><cell></cell><cell>21.09</cell><cell></cell><cell>G</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>av01033k13</cell><cell>ECM</cell><cell>Collagen, type IX, alpha 1</cell><cell>collagen precursor</cell><cell></cell><cell>21.10</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>av02101l17</cell><cell>ECM</cell><cell>Collagen like</cell><cell>collagen precursor</cell><cell></cell><cell>21.26</cell><cell></cell><cell>G</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>CL2177Ct1</cell><cell>ECM</cell><cell>Collagen alpha-5(VI)</cell><cell>collagen precursor</cell><cell></cell><cell>1.20</cell><cell></cell><cell>G</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>av01030e14</cell><cell>ECM</cell><cell>Collagen alpha-2(V)</cell><cell>collagen precursor</cell><cell></cell><cell>21.34</cell><cell></cell><cell>G</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>CL253Ct1</cell><cell>ECM</cell><cell>Collagen alpha-2(I)</cell><cell>collagen precursor</cell><cell></cell><cell>1.15</cell><cell></cell><cell>G</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>CL902Ct1</cell><cell>ECM</cell><cell>Collagen alpha-2(I)</cell><cell>collagen precursor</cell><cell></cell><cell>21.06</cell><cell></cell><cell>G</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>CL2629Ct1</cell><cell>ECM</cell><cell>Collagen alpha-1(V)</cell><cell>collagen precursor</cell><cell></cell><cell>21.03</cell><cell></cell><cell>G</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>CL635Ct1</cell><cell>ECM</cell><cell>Collagen alpha-1(V)</cell><cell>collagen precursor</cell><cell></cell><cell>21.23</cell><cell></cell><cell>G</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>CL389Ct1</cell><cell>ECM</cell><cell>Collagen alpha-1(III)</cell><cell>collagen precursor</cell><cell></cell><cell>21.19</cell><cell></cell><cell>G</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>CL4Ct6</cell><cell>ECM</cell><cell>Collagen alpha-1(II)</cell><cell>collagen precursor</cell><cell></cell><cell>21.36</cell><cell></cell><cell>G</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>CL934Ct1</cell><cell>ECM</cell><cell>Col protein</cell><cell>collagen precursor</cell><cell></cell><cell>21.02</cell><cell></cell><cell>G</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>av02058f16</cell><cell>ECM</cell><cell>Col-like protein</cell><cell>cell adhesion</cell><cell>7 #</cell><cell>2.53</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>G</cell></row><row><cell>av01028j14</cell><cell>ECM</cell><cell>Collagen triple helix repeat-containing protein 1</cell><cell>cell adhesion</cell><cell></cell><cell>21.23</cell><cell></cell><cell>E</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>av01009g10</cell><cell>Sec</cell><cell>Uromodulin domain (URO domain)</cell><cell>cell adhesion</cell><cell>6 #</cell><cell>2.66</cell><cell></cell><cell>G</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>av02120i19</cell><cell>Inn. pl. mb</cell><cell>Catenin delta</cell><cell>cell adhesion</cell><cell>9 #</cell><cell>2.17</cell><cell></cell><cell>G</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>CL1994Ct1</cell><cell>Mit, Per</cell><cell>Mitochondrial fission 1 protein (FIS1)</cell><cell>vesicle</cell><cell cols="2">10 # 1.98</cell><cell></cell><cell>G</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>av02071b13</cell><cell>Nu</cell><cell>Tousled-like kinase 1</cell><cell>cell cycle</cell><cell>#</cell><cell>1.82</cell><cell></cell><cell>G</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>CL3005Ct1</cell><cell>Nu</cell><cell>DNA repair protein RAD50</cell><cell>DNA damage</cell><cell>#</cell><cell>1.60</cell><cell></cell><cell>G</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>av02071o11</cell><cell>Cyt</cell><cell>Cytoskeleton-associated protein 5 (TOG protein)</cell><cell>cytoskeleton</cell><cell>#</cell><cell>21.52</cell><cell></cell><cell>G</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>av01002j09</cell><cell>Pl. mb.</cell><cell>Tyrosine kinase receptor (Tyr,K Receptor)</cell><cell>receptor signaling</cell><cell>8 #</cell><cell>2.35</cell><cell></cell><cell>E</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>av02074d19</cell><cell></cell><cell>Sulfuric ester hydrolases</cell><cell>hormone</cell><cell>#</cell><cell>1.63</cell><cell></cell><cell>E</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>CL2622Ct1</cell><cell></cell><cell>Predicted protein</cell><cell>receptor signaling</cell><cell>#</cell><cell>21.59</cell><cell></cell><cell>E</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>CL3901Ct1</cell><cell></cell><cell>Hydroxymethylglutaryl-CoA reductase</cell><cell>metabolism-FA</cell><cell>#</cell><cell>21.73</cell><cell></cell><cell>E</cell><cell></cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head>Table 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Cont.</figDesc><table /><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5"><head>Table S1</head><label>S1</label><figDesc>List of the genes up-regulated in the Symbiotic condition. Legend as in Table 2. (XLS) Table S2 List of the genes up-regulated in the Aposymbiotic condition. Legend as in Table 2. (XLS) Table S3 Primer sequences used in this article. (XLS) Table S4 Gene sequences used in this article.</figDesc><table /><note>(XLS)</note></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">PLoS Genetics | www.plosgenetics.org 1 July 2011 | Volume 7 | Issue 7 | e1002187</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">PLoS Genetics | www.plosgenetics.org</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">July 2011 | Volume 7 | Issue 7 | e1002187</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgments</head><p>We are very grateful to the Oceanographic Museum of Monaco for the sampling of the naturally occurring bleached sea anemone specimens. We thank the members of the IBISA functional genomics platform of Nice-Sophia Antipolis for providing access and support to the microarray facility. We thank the Villefranche-sur-Mer Oceanological Observatory for the access to the Roche Light Cycler. We are very grateful to D. Forcioli for helpful advises in phylogenetic analyses. We are grateful to H. McCombie and L. C. Grasso for editing of this manuscript. We also thank P. L. Merle, T. Zamoum, F. Priouzeau, and B. Poderini for their technical help with the collection and maintenance of sea anemones and zooxanthellae cultures.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Sequence analyses</head><p>Sequencing of either A.viridis library clones or newly cloned cDNAs was performed by Macrogen Inc.</p><p>Signal peptides and Trans-membrane domains were predicted using SignalP and TMHMM, respectively, from the CBS prediction servers (www.cbs.dtu.dk/services). GPI anchors were predicted with PredGPI (http://gpcr.biocomp.unibo.it/predgpi). Other Domains were inferred from PFAM (pfam.sanger.ac.uk). Blast analysis tools used were from NCBI (blast.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov).</p><p>Functionnal annotation of the A. viridis EST dataset (GO annotations) has been performed using Blast2GO <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref>. Statistical assessment of annotation differences between SY-genes (test group) and APO-genes (reference group) was performed using the Gossip package <ref type="bibr" target="#b75">[76]</ref>, that employs Fisher's Exact Test to estimate the significance of associations between two categorical variables.</p><p>Sequence alignments were performed using MultAlin <ref type="bibr" target="#b76">[77]</ref> and ClustalW with Blosum62 default parameters. Alignments were optimized manually using the 2 computer generated alignments as a model. Using the segment of the sequence alignment conserved in all sequences (bordered by the bar above alignments in <ref type="figure">Figures  S5, S6, S7</ref>), the best-fitted substitution model was evaluated using ProtTest <ref type="bibr" target="#b77">[78]</ref>. Using parameters indicated in the Figure legend of each alignment tree, a Maximum Likelihood tree was determined using phyML and branches support were calculated using aLRT <ref type="bibr" target="#b78">[79]</ref>. Alternatively, Bayesian analysis using MrBayes 3-1.2 (mrbayes.csit.fsu.edu) was conducted with the following settings: fixed rate amino acid model was set to mixed (prset aamodelpr = mixed) and proportion of invariable sites model was combined with the Gamma model (lset rates = invgamma). <ref type="figure">Figure S1</ref> The sea anemone model Anemonia viridis and the symbiosis-dedicated oligoarray. A. Schematic section through an A. viridis polyp, showing the two tissues (compartments) composing the animal: the epidermis (''E'') and the gastroderm hosting the photosynthetic zooxanthellae (''G''). B. The 2,000 genes compiled on the oligoarray were selected from an A. viridis clustered and annotated EST dataset according to putative participation in symbiotic processes. Genes were classified by GO terms according to Molecular Function, Biological Process and Cellular Components. Histogram values are given as the percentage of total within each GO category. C. Significant GO terms enrichment between the 136 annotated genes identified as up-regulated in the symbiotic state (SY genes; test group) and up-regulated in the aposymbiotic state (APO genes; reference group). Statistical analysis was conducted using Gossip package which employs Fisher's Exact Test (p value,0.05). (TIF) anemones used in this study and their collection location, as well as the stress which lead AS1-6 anemones to bleach. (TIF) <ref type="figure">Figure S3</ref> Counting of relative host to symbiont nuclear ratio in individual specimen using real time PCR. Total genomic DNA was extracted from the 11 sea anemones tentacles (Sy1-5 and AS1-6), a dissected epidermal tissue (Ep) and culture Symbiodinium (CZ). The gDNAs were used as template for real-time quantitative PCR with primers specific for the Symbiodinium EF2, APX and SPS genes and the A. viridis COP-c, RCC2 and NPC1 genes. A. Comparison of the relative A.viridis gene loci number (top panel) shows that most gene ratios are around 1:1 in the different individuals whereas relative Symbiodinium gene loci number (bottom panel) shows variable numbers, essentially due to variation in the EF2 loci number. B. Comparative gene ratio between Symbiodinium SPS, APX and EF2 versus A.viridis RCC2 (top panel) and NPC1 (bottom panel). Both histograms confirm the symbiotic and aposymbiotic state of the specimen used in this study, individual showing similar pattern than in <ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref>. (TIF) <ref type="figure">Figure S4</ref> Schematic diagrams of microarray experimental design. A. cDNAs from symbiotic anemones Sy1-Sy5 and aposymbiotic anemones AS1-AS5 were hybridized against the same cDNA sample from the AS6 aposymbiotic sea anemone. Dye-swap hybridizations were performed for all experimental conditions. B. cDNAs from E (epidermis) and G (gastroderm+zooxanthellae) tissue fractions from 3 different anemones (Sy3-Sy5) were hybridized against each other or against the AS6 (C+D) reference sample. Dye-swap hybridizations were performed for all experimental combinations. (TIF) <ref type="figure">Figure S5</ref> Phylogenetic analysis of the Calumenin gene family. Human proteins belonging to the Calumenin protein family (as defined in <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref> </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Supporting Information</head></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Technau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Steele</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Evolutionary crossroads in developmental biology: Cnidaria. Development</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">138</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1447" to="1458" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Technau U, Steele RE (2011) Evolutionary crossroads in developmental biology: Cnidaria. Development 138: 1447-1458.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Photosynthetic symbioses in animals</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Venn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Loram</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Douglas</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Exp Bot</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">59</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1069" to="1080" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Venn AA, Loram JE, Douglas AE (2008) Photosynthetic symbioses in animals. J Exp Bot 59: 1069-1080.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Symbiotic Anthozoan: A Physiological Chimera between Alga and Animal</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Furla</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Allemand</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Shick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Ferrier-Pages</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Richier</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Integr Comp Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="595" to="604" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Furla P, Allemand D, Shick JM, Ferrier-Pages C, Richier S, et al. (2005) The Symbiotic Anthozoan: A Physiological Chimera between Alga and Animal. Integr Comp Biol 45: 595-604.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Metabolic interactions between algal symbionts and invertebrate hosts</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Yellowlees</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Rees</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Leggat</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Plant Cell Environ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="679" to="694" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Yellowlees D, Rees TA, Leggat W (2008) Metabolic interactions between algal symbionts and invertebrate hosts. Plant Cell Environ 31: 679-694.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Involvement of H + -ATPase and carbonic anhydrase in inorganic carbon uptake for endosymbiont photosynthesis</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Furla</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Allemand</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Orsenigo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Amer J Physiol (Regul Integr Comp)</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">278</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="870" to="881" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Furla P, Allemand D, Orsenigo MN (2000) Involvement of H + -ATPase and carbonic anhydrase in inorganic carbon uptake for endosymbiont photosynthe- sis. Amer J Physiol (Regul Integr Comp) 278: R870-R881.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The induction of carbonic anhydrase in the symbiotic sea anemone Aiptasia pulchella</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Weis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biol Bull</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">180</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="496" to="504" />
			<date type="published" when="1991" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Weis VM (1991) The induction of carbonic anhydrase in the symbiotic sea anemone Aiptasia pulchella. Biol Bull 180: 496-504.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Catalase characterization and implication in bleaching of a symbiotic sea anemone</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P-L</forename><surname>Merle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Sabourault</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Richier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Allemand</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Furla</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Free Rad Biol Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="236" to="246" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Merle P-L, Sabourault C, Richier S, Allemand D, Furla P (2007) Catalase characterization and implication in bleaching of a symbiotic sea anemone. Free Rad Biol Med 42: 236-246.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Symbiosisinduced adaptation to oxidative stress</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Richier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Furla</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Plantivaux</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P-L</forename><surname>Merle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Allemand</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Exp Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">208</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="277" to="285" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Richier S, Furla P, Plantivaux A, Merle P-L, Allemand D (2005) Symbiosis- induced adaptation to oxidative stress. J Exp Biol 208: 277-285.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Oxidative stress and apoptotic events during thermal stress in the symbiotic sea anemone, Anemonia viridis</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Richier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Sabourault</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Courtiade</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Zucchini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Allemand</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Febs J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">273</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4186" to="4198" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Richier S, Sabourault C, Courtiade J, Zucchini N, Allemand D, et al. (2006) Oxidative stress and apoptotic events during thermal stress in the symbiotic sea anemone, Anemonia viridis. Febs J 273: 4186-4198.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A New Coral Carbonic Anhydrase in Stylophora pistillata</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Bertucci</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Tambutté</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Supuran</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Allemand</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Zoccola</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Marine Biotechnology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="11" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Bertucci A, Tambutté S, Supuran C, Allemand D, Zoccola D (2011) A New Coral Carbonic Anhydrase in Stylophora pistillata. Marine Biotechnology. pp 1-11.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cellular mechanisms of Cnidarian bleaching: stress causes the collapse of symbiosis</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Weis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Exp Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">211</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3059" to="3066" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Weis VM (2008) Cellular mechanisms of Cnidarian bleaching: stress causes the collapse of symbiosis. J Exp Biol 211: 3059-3066.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Carbonic Anhydrase in the Scleractinian Coral Stylophora pistillata</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Moya</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Tambutté</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Bertucci</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Tambutté</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Lotto</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Biol Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">283</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="25475" to="25484" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Moya A, Tambutté S, Bertucci A, Tambutté E, Lotto S, et al. (2008) Carbonic Anhydrase in the Scleractinian Coral Stylophora pistillata. J Biol Chem 283: 25475-25484.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Localization of a symbiosis-related protein, Sym32, in the Anthopleura elegantissima-Symbiodinium muscatinei Association</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Schwarz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Weis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biol Bull</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">205</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="339" to="350" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Schwarz JA, Weis VM (2003) Localization of a symbiosis-related protein, Sym32, in the Anthopleura elegantissima-Symbiodinium muscatinei Association. Biol Bull 205: 339-350.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Weis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Allemand</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physiology. What determines coral health? Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">324</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1153" to="1155" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Weis VM, Allemand D (2009) Physiology. What determines coral health? Science 324: 1153-1155.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Transcriptomic variation in a coral reveals pathways of clonal organisation</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Bay</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Nielsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Jarmer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Seneca</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Marine Genomics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="119" to="125" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Bay LK, Nielsen HB, Jarmer H, Seneca F, vanOppen MJH (2009) Transcriptomic variation in a coral reveals pathways of clonal organisation. Marine Genomics 2: 119-125.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Transcriptome analysis of a cnidarian-dinoflagellate mutualism reveals complex modulation of host gene expression</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Rodriguez-Lanetty</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Phillips</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Weis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Genomics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">23</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Rodriguez-Lanetty M, Phillips WS, Weis VM (2006) Transcriptome analysis of a cnidarian-dinoflagellate mutualism reveals complex modulation of host gene expression. BMC Genomics 7: 23.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The host transcriptome remains unaltered during the establishment of coralalgal symbioses</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Voolstra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Schwarz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Schnetzer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sunagawa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Desalvo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol Ecol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1823" to="1833" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Voolstra CR, Schwarz JA, Schnetzer J, Sunagawa S, Desalvo MK, et al. (2009) The host transcriptome remains unaltered during the establishment of coral- algal symbioses. Mol Ecol 18: 1823-1833.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Differential gene expression during thermal stress and bleaching in the Caribbean coral Montastraea faveolata</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Desalvo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Voolstra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sunagawa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Schwarz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Stillman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol Ecol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3952" to="3971" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">DeSalvo MK, Voolstra CR, Sunagawa S, Schwarz JA, Stillman JH, et al. (2008) Differential gene expression during thermal stress and bleaching in the Caribbean coral Montastraea faveolata. Mol Ecol 17: 3952-3971.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Early molecular responses of coral larvae to hyperthermal stress</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Rodriguez-Lanetty</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Harii</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Hoegh-Guldberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol Ecol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5101" to="5114" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Rodriguez-Lanetty M, Harii S, Hoegh-Guldberg O (2009) Early molecular responses of coral larvae to hyperthermal stress. Mol Ecol 18: 5101-5114.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comprehensive EST analysis of the symbiotic sea anemone, Anemonia viridis</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Sabourault</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Ganot</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Deleury</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Allemand</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Furla</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Genomics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">333</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Sabourault C, Ganot P, Deleury E, Allemand D, Furla P (2009) Comprehensive EST analysis of the symbiotic sea anemone, Anemonia viridis. BMC Genomics 10: 333.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">From Stop to Start: Tandem Gene Arrangement, Copy Number and Trans-Splicing Sites in the Dinoflagellate Amphidinium carterae</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Bachvaroff</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Place</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1371/journal.pone.0002929</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS ONE</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2929</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Bachvaroff TR, Place AR (2008) From Stop to Start: Tandem Gene Arrangement, Copy Number and Trans-Splicing Sites in the Dinoflagellate Amphidinium carterae. PLoS ONE 3: e2929. doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0002929.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Widespread recycling of processed cDNAs in dinoflagellates</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Slamovits</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Keeling</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Current Biology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="550" to="552" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Slamovits CH, Keeling PJ (2008) Widespread recycling of processed cDNAs in dinoflagellates. Current Biology 18: R550-R552.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">limmaGUI: A graphical user interface for linear modeling of microarray data</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Wettenhall</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Smyth</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3705" to="3706" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Wettenhall JM, Smyth GK (2004) limmaGUI: A graphical user interface for linear modeling of microarray data. Bioinformatics 20: 3705-3706.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Demosponge and sea anemone fibrillar collagen diversity reveals the early emergence of A/C clades and the maintenance of the modular structure of type V/XI collagens from sponge to human</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Exposito</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Larroux</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Cluzel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Valcourt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Lethias</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Biol Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">283</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="28226" to="28235" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Exposito JY, Larroux C, Cluzel C, Valcourt U, Lethias C, et al. (2008) Demosponge and sea anemone fibrillar collagen diversity reveals the early emergence of A/C clades and the maintenance of the modular structure of type V/XI collagens from sponge to human. J Biol Chem 283: 28226-28235.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Collagens, modifying enzymes and their mutations in humans, flies and worms</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Myllyharju</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Kivirikko</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Trends Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="33" to="43" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Myllyharju J, Kivirikko KI (2004) Collagens, modifying enzymes and their mutations in humans, flies and worms. Trends Genet 20: 33-43.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The rapidly expanding CREC protein family: members, localization, function, and role in disease</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Honore</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioessays</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="262" to="277" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Honore B (2009) The rapidly expanding CREC protein family: members, localization, function, and role in disease. Bioessays 31: 262-277.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Symbiotic Interactions</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Douglas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994" />
			<publisher>Oxford University Press Inc</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Douglas AE (1994) Symbiotic Interactions. New York: Oxford University Press Inc.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The TRAPP complex: insights into its architecture and function</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sacher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Lavie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Oh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Segev</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Traffic</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2032" to="2042" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Sacher M, Kim YG, Lavie A, Oh BH, Segev N (2008) The TRAPP complex: insights into its architecture and function. Traffic 9: 2032-2042.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zwang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Yarden</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Systems Biology of Growth Factor-Induced Receptor Endocytosis. Traffic</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="349" to="363" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Zwang Y, Yarden Y (2009) Systems Biology of Growth Factor-Induced Receptor Endocytosis. Traffic 10: 349-363.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">pH regulation and beyond: unanticipated functions for the voltage-gated proton channel, HVCN1</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Capasso</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Decoursey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Dyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Trends Cell Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Capasso M, Decoursey TE, Dyer MJ (2010) pH regulation and beyond: unanticipated functions for the voltage-gated proton channel, HVCN1. Trends Cell Biol.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Zinc transporter 2 (SLC30A2) can suppress the vesicular zinc defect of adaptor protein 3-depleted fibroblasts by promoting zinc accumulation in lysosomes</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Falcon-Perez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Dell'angelica</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Exp Cell Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">313</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1473" to="1483" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Falcon-Perez JM, Dell&apos;Angelica EC (2007) Zinc transporter 2 (SLC30A2) can suppress the vesicular zinc defect of adaptor protein 3-depleted fibroblasts by promoting zinc accumulation in lysosomes. Exp Cell Res 313: 1473-1483.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rab GEFs and GAPs</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Barr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Lambright</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr Opin Cell Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="461" to="470" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Barr F, Lambright DG (2010) Rab GEFs and GAPs. Curr Opin Cell Biol 22: 461-470.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Molecular identification of Rab7 (ApRab7) in Aiptasia pulchella and its exclusion from phagosomes harboring zooxanthellae</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Cheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Sung</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Kuo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Fang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biochem Biophys Res Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">308</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="586" to="595" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Chen MC, Cheng YM, Sung PJ, Kuo CE, Fang LS (2003) Molecular identification of Rab7 (ApRab7) in Aiptasia pulchella and its exclusion from phagosomes harboring zooxanthellae. Biochem Biophys Res Commun 308: 586-595.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">ApRab11, a cnidarian homologue of the recycling regulatory protein Rab11, is involved in the establishment and maintenance of the Aiptasia-Symbiodinium endosymbiosis</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M-C</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M-C</forename><surname>Hong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y-S</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M-C</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y-M</forename><surname>Cheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biochemical and Biophysical Research Communications</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">338</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1607" to="1616" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Chen M-C, Hong M-C, Huang Y-S, Liu M-C, Cheng Y-M, et al. (2005) ApRab11, a cnidarian homologue of the recycling regulatory protein Rab11, is involved in the establishment and maintenance of the Aiptasia-Symbiodinium endosymbiosis. Biochemical and Biophysical Research Communications 338: 1607-1616.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Energy relationships between Anemonia sulcata and its endosymbiotic zooxanthellae</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Stambler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Dubinsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Symbiosis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="233" to="248" />
			<date type="published" when="1987" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Stambler N, Dubinsky Z (1987) Energy relationships between Anemonia sulcata and its endosymbiotic zooxanthellae. Symbiosis 3: 233-248.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Metabolism in the era of molecular biology</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Hanson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Biol Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">280</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1705" to="1715" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Hanson RW (2005) Metabolism in the era of molecular biology. J Biol Chem 280: 1705-1715.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Purification, molecular cloning, and expression of 2-hydroxyphytanoyl-CoA lyase, a peroxisomal thiamine pyrophosphate-dependent enzyme that catalyzes the carbon-carbon bond cleavage during alpha-oxidation of 3-methyl-branched fatty acids</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Foulon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Antonenkov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Croes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Waelkens</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Mannaerts</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">96</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="10039" to="10044" />
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Foulon V, Antonenkov VD, Croes K, Waelkens E, Mannaerts GP, et al. (1999) Purification, molecular cloning, and expression of 2-hydroxyphytanoyl-CoA lyase, a peroxisomal thiamine pyrophosphate-dependent enzyme that catalyzes the carbon-carbon bond cleavage during alpha-oxidation of 3-methyl-branched fatty acids. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 96: 10039-10044.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Suppression subtractive hybridization identifies genes correlated to symbiotic and aposymbiotic sea anemone associated with dinoflagellate</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kuo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Z-C</forename><surname>Liang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C-H</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Experimental Marine Biology and Ecology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">388</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="11" to="19" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Kuo J, Liang Z-C, Lin C-H (2010) Suppression subtractive hybridization identifies genes correlated to symbiotic and aposymbiotic sea anemone associated with dinoflagellate. Journal of Experimental Marine Biology and Ecology 388: 11-19.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cellular cholesterol trafficking and compartmentalization</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Ikonen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="125" to="138" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Ikonen E (2008) Cellular cholesterol trafficking and compartmentalization. Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol 9: 125-138.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Intracellular trafficking of Niemann-Pick C proteins 1 and 2: obligate components of subcellular lipid transport</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Liscum</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Sturley</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biochim Biophys Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1685</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="22" to="27" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Liscum L, Sturley SL (2004) Intracellular trafficking of Niemann-Pick C proteins 1 and 2: obligate components of subcellular lipid transport. Biochim Biophys Acta 1685: 22-27.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Transfer of cholesterol by the NPC team</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Vance</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell Metab</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="105" to="106" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Vance JE (2010) Transfer of cholesterol by the NPC team. Cell Metab 12: 105-106.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multi-component complement system of Cnidaria: C3, Bf, and MASP genes expressed in the endodermal tissues of a sea anemone, Nematostella vectensis</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kimura</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Sakaguchi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Nonaka</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Immunobiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">214</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="165" to="178" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Kimura A, Sakaguchi E, Nonaka M (2009) Multi-component complement system of Cnidaria: C3, Bf, and MASP genes expressed in the endodermal tissues of a sea anemone, Nematostella vectensis. Immunobiology 214: 165-178.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genomic view of the evolution of the complement system</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Nonaka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kimura</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Immunogenetics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="701" to="713" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Nonaka M, Kimura A (2006) Genomic view of the evolution of the complement system. Immunogenetics 58: 701-713.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Analysis of evolutionarily conserved innate immune components in coral links immunity and symbiosis</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Kvennefors</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Leggat</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Kerr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Ainsworth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Hoegh-Guldberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Dev Comp Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1219" to="1229" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Kvennefors EC, Leggat W, Kerr CC, Ainsworth TD, Hoegh-Guldberg O, et al. (2010) Analysis of evolutionarily conserved innate immune components in coral links immunity and symbiosis. Dev Comp Immunol 34: 1219-1229.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A molecular specificity code for the three mammalian KDEL receptors</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Raykhel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Alanen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Salo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Jurvansuu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Nguyen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Cell Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">179</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1193" to="1204" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Raykhel I, Alanen H, Salo K, Jurvansuu J, Nguyen VD, et al. (2007) A molecular specificity code for the three mammalian KDEL receptors. J Cell Biol 179: 1193-1204.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Warfarin and the vitamin K-dependent gammacarboxylation system</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Wallin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Hutson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Trends Mol Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="299" to="302" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Wallin R, Hutson SM (2004) Warfarin and the vitamin K-dependent gamma- carboxylation system. Trends Mol Med 10: 299-302.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Vitamin K-dependent gamma-glutamylcarboxylation: an ancient posttranslational modification</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Bandyopadhyay</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Vitam Horm</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">78</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="157" to="184" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Bandyopadhyay PK (2008) Vitamin K-dependent gamma-glutamylcarboxyla- tion: an ancient posttranslational modification. Vitam Horm 78: 157-184.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The vitamin K cycle</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Oldenburg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Marinova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Muller-Reible</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Watzka</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Vitam Horm</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">78</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="35" to="62" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Oldenburg J, Marinova M, Muller-Reible C, Watzka M (2008) The vitamin K cycle. Vitam Horm 78: 35-62.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Periostin, a member of a novel family of vitamin K-dependent proteins, is expressed by mesenchymal stromal cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Coutu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Monette</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Rivard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Blostein</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Biol Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">283</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="17991" to="18001" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Coutu DL, Wu JH, Monette A, Rivard GE, Blostein MD, et al. (2008) Periostin, a member of a novel family of vitamin K-dependent proteins, is expressed by mesenchymal stromal cells. J Biol Chem 283: 17991-18001.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Differential protein profiles reflect the different lifestyles of symbiotic and aposymbiotic Anthopleura elegantissima, a sea anemone from temperate waters</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Weis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Levine</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Exp Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">199</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="883" to="892" />
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Weis VM, Levine RP (1996) Differential protein profiles reflect the different lifestyles of symbiotic and aposymbiotic Anthopleura elegantissima, a sea anemone from temperate waters. J Exp Biol 199: 883-892.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Symbiosis-enhanced gene expression in cnidarian-algal associations: cloning and characterization of a cDNA, sym32, encoding a possible cell adhesion protein</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Reynolds</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Schwarz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Weis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Comp Biochem Physiol A Mol Integr Physiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">126</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="33" to="44" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Reynolds WS, Schwarz JA, Weis VM (2000) Symbiosis-enhanced gene expression in cnidarian-algal associations: cloning and characterization of a cDNA, sym32, encoding a possible cell adhesion protein. Comp Biochem Physiol A Mol Integr Physiol 126: 33-44.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The vitamin K-dependent bone protein is accumulated within cultured osteosarcoma cells in the presence of the vitamin K antagonist warfarin</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Nishimoto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Price</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Biol Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">260</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2832" to="2836" />
			<date type="published" when="1985" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Nishimoto SK, Price PA (1985) The vitamin K-dependent bone protein is accumulated within cultured osteosarcoma cells in the presence of the vitamin K antagonist warfarin. J Biol Chem 260: 2832-2836.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Structural basis of membrane binding by Gla domains of vitamin K-dependent proteins</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Rigby</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Morelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Grant</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat Struct Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="751" to="756" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Huang M, Rigby AC, Morelli X, Grant MA, Huang G, et al. (2003) Structural basis of membrane binding by Gla domains of vitamin K-dependent proteins. Nat Struct Biol 10: 751-756.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b53">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mechanisms of carbon acquisition for endosymbiont photosynthesis in Anthozoa</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Allemand</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Furla</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Bénazet-Tambutté</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Can J Bot</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">76</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="925" to="941" />
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Allemand D, Furla P, Bénazet-Tambutté S (1998) Mechanisms of carbon acquisition for endosymbiont photosynthesis in Anthozoa. Can J Bot 76: 925-941.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b54">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evidence for bicarbonate transport in species of red and brown macrophytic marine algae</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Cook</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Lanaras</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Colman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Exp Bot</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="977" to="984" />
			<date type="published" when="1986" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Cook CM, Lanaras T, Colman B (1986) Evidence for bicarbonate transport in species of red and brown macrophytic marine algae. J Exp Bot 37: 977-984.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b55">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Transport and fixation of inorganic carbon by marine algae</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Kerby</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Raven</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Adv Bot Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="71" to="123" />
			<date type="published" when="1985" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Kerby NW, Raven JA (1985) Transport and fixation of inorganic carbon by marine algae. Adv Bot Res 11: 71-123.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b56">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sources and mechanisms of inorganic carbon transport for coral calcification and photosynthesis</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Furla</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Galgani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Durand</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Allemand</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Exp Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">203</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3445" to="3457" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Furla P, Galgani I, Durand I, Allemand D (2000) Sources and mechanisms of inorganic carbon transport for coral calcification and photosynthesis. J Exp Biol 203: 3445-3457.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b57">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dinoflagellate symbioses: strategies and adaptations for the acquisition and fixation of inorganic carbon</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Leggat</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Marendy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Baillie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Whitney</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ludwig</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Funct Plant Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="309" to="322" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Leggat W, Marendy EM, Baillie B, Whitney SM, Ludwig M, et al. (2002) Dinoflagellate symbioses: strategies and adaptations for the acquisition and fixation of inorganic carbon. Funct Plant Biol 29: 309-322.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b58">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effect of dissolved inorganic carbon concentration on the photosynthesis of the symbiotic sea anemone Aiptasia pulchella Carlgren: role of carbonic anhydrase</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Weis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Exp Mar Biol Ecol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">174</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="209" to="225" />
			<date type="published" when="1993" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Weis VM (1993) Effect of dissolved inorganic carbon concentration on the photosynthesis of the symbiotic sea anemone Aiptasia pulchella Carlgren: role of carbonic anhydrase. J Exp Mar Biol Ecol 174: 209-225.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b59">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Inorganic carbon uptake for photosynthesis by the symbiotic coral/dinoflagellate association. II. Mechanisms for bicarbonate uptake</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Al-Moghrabi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Goiran</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Allemand</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Speziale</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Jaubert</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Exp Mar Biol Ecol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">199</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="227" to="248" />
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Al-Moghrabi S, Goiran C, Allemand D, Speziale N, Jaubert J (1996) Inorganic carbon uptake for photosynthesis by the symbiotic coral/dinoflagellate association. II. Mechanisms for bicarbonate uptake. J Exp Mar Biol Ecol 199: 227-248.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b60">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Carbonic Anhydrase Expression and Synthesis in the Sea Anemone Anthopleura elegantissima Are Enhanced by the Presence of Dinoflagellate Symbionts</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Weis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Reynolds</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physiological and Biochemical Zoology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">72</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="307" to="316" />
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Weis VM, Reynolds WS (1999) Carbonic Anhydrase Expression and Synthesis in the Sea Anemone Anthopleura elegantissima Are Enhanced by the Presence of Dinoflagellate Symbionts. Physiological and Biochemical Zoology 72: 307-316.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b61">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Concentration-Dependent Effects on Intracellular and Surface pH of Exposing Xenopus oocytes to Solutions Containing NH /NH 4 (+)</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Musa-Aziz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Jiang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L-M</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Behar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Boron</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Membrane Biology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">228</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="15" to="31" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Musa-Aziz R, Jiang L, Chen L-M, Behar K, Boron W (2009) Concentration- Dependent Effects on Intracellular and Surface pH of Exposing Xenopus oocytes to Solutions Containing NH /NH 4 (+). Journal of Membrane Biology 228: 15-31.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b62">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Lack of the Rhesus protein Rh1 impairs growth of the green alga Chlamydomonas reinhardtii at high CO2</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Soupene</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Inwood</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kustu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">101</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="7787" to="7792" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Soupene E, Inwood W, Kustu S (2004) Lack of the Rhesus protein Rh1 impairs growth of the green alga Chlamydomonas reinhardtii at high CO2. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America 101: 7787-7792.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b63">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The tobacco aquaporin NtAQP1 is a membrane CO2 pore with physiological functions</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Uehlein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Lovisolo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Siefritz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Kaldenhoff</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">425</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="734" to="737" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Uehlein N, Lovisolo C, Siefritz F, Kaldenhoff R (2003) The tobacco aquaporin NtAQP1 is a membrane CO2 pore with physiological functions. Nature 425: 734-737.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b64">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evidence that aquaporin 1 is a major pathway for CO2 transport across the human erythrocyte membrane</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Endeward</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Musa-Aziz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Cooper</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Pelletier</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The FASEB Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1974" to="1981" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Endeward V, Musa-Aziz R, Cooper GJ, Chen LM, Pelletier MF, et al. (2006) Evidence that aquaporin 1 is a major pathway for CO2 transport across the human erythrocyte membrane. The FASEB Journal 20: 1974-1981.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b65">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Protein 4.1R-dependent multiprotein complex: New insights into the structural organization of the red blood cell membrane</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Salomao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Hartwig</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">105</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="8026" to="8031" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Salomao M, Zhang X, Yang Y, Lee S, Hartwig JH, et al. (2008) Protein 4.1R- dependent multiprotein complex: New insights into the structural organization of the red blood cell membrane. 105: 8026-8031.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b66">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Band 3 multiprotein complexes in the red cell membrane; of mice and men</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Van Den Akker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Satchwell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Williamson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Toye</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Molecules, and Diseases</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="8" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Blood Cells</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">van den Akker E, Satchwell TJ, Williamson RC, Toye AM (2010) Band 3 multiprotein complexes in the red cell membrane; of mice and men. Blood Cells, Molecules, and Diseases 45: 1-8.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b67">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Uptake of ammonium by the scleractinian coral Stylophora pistillata: Effect of feeding, light, and ammonium concentrations</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Grover</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J-F</forename><surname>Maguer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Reynaud-Vaganay</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Ferrier-Pagès</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Limnology and Oceanography</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="782" to="790" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Grover R, Maguer J-F, Reynaud-Vaganay S, Ferrier-Pagès C (2002) Uptake of ammonium by the scleractinian coral Stylophora pistillata: Effect of feeding, light, and ammonium concentrations. Limnology and Oceanography 47: 782-790.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b68">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Variation in antioxidant gene expression in the scleractinian coral Acropora millepora under laboratory thermal stress</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Nbm</forename><surname>Császár</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Seneca</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Marine Ecology and Progress Series</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">392</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="93" to="102" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Császár NBM, Seneca FO, vanOppen MJH (2009) Variation in antioxidant gene expression in the scleractinian coral Acropora millepora under laboratory thermal stress. Marine Ecology and Progress Series 392: 93-102.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b69">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Coral Bleaching -Capacity for Acclimatization and Adaptation</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Coles</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Brown</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Advances in Marine Biology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="183" to="223" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Coles SL, Brown BE (2003) Coral Bleaching -Capacity for Acclimatization and Adaptation. Advances in Marine Biology 46: 183-223.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b70">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Metagenomic analysis of stressed coral holobionts</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Vega Thurber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Willner-Hall</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Rodriguez-Mueller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Desnues</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Edwards</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Environmental Microbiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1752" to="1766" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Vega Thurber R, Willner-Hall D, Rodriguez-Mueller B, Desnues C, Edwards RA, et al. (2009) Metagenomic analysis of stressed coral holobionts. Environmental Microbiology 11: 1752-1766.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b71">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A comparison of background correction methods for two-colour microarrays</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Ritchie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Silver</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Oshlack</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Holmes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Diyagama</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2700" to="2707" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Ritchie ME, Silver J, Oshlack A, Holmes M, Diyagama D, et al. (2007) A comparison of background correction methods for two-colour microarrays. Bioinformatics 23: 2700-2707.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b72">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Open source clustering software</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>De Hoon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Imoto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Nolan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Miyano</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1453" to="1454" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">de Hoon MJ, Imoto S, Nolan J, Miyano S (2004) Open source clustering software. Bioinformatics 20: 1453-1454.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b73">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Primer3 on the WWW for general users and for biologist programmers</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Rozen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Skaletsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Methods in Molecular Biology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">132</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="365" to="386" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Rozen S, Skaletsky H (2000) Primer3 on the WWW for general users and for biologist programmers. Methods in Molecular Biology 132: 365-386.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b74">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Accurate normalization of real-time quantitative RT-PCR data by geometric averaging of multiple internal control genes</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Vandesompele</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">De</forename><surname>Preter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Pattyn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Poppe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Van</forename><surname>Roy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>resear- ch0034.0031-research0034.0011</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Biology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Vandesompele J, De Preter K, Pattyn F, Poppe B, Van Roy N, et al. (2002) Accurate normalization of real-time quantitative RT-PCR data by geometric averaging of multiple internal control genes. Genome Biology 3: resear- ch0034.0031-research0034.0011.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b75">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Biological Profiling of Gene Groups utilizing Gene Ontology</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Blüthgen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Brand</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Cajavec</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Swat</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Herzel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Informatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="106" to="115" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Blüthgen N, Brand K, Cajavec B, Swat M, Herzel H, et al. (2005) Biological Profiling of Gene Groups utilizing Gene Ontology. Genome Informatics 16: 106-115.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b76">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multiple sequence alignment with hierarchical clustering</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Corpet</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucl Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="10881" to="10890" />
			<date type="published" when="1988" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Corpet F (1988) Multiple sequence alignment with hierarchical clustering. Nucl Acids Res 16: 10881-10890.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b77">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">ProtTest: selection of best-fit models of protein evolution</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Abascal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Zardoya</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Posada</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2104" to="2105" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Abascal F, Zardoya R, Posada D (2005) ProtTest: selection of best-fit models of protein evolution. Bioinformatics 21: 2104-2105.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b78">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A simple, fast, and accurate algorithm to estimate large phylogenies by maximum likelihood</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Guindon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Gascuel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Syst Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="696" to="704" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Guindon S, Gascuel O (2003) A simple, fast, and accurate algorithm to estimate large phylogenies by maximum likelihood. Syst Biol 52: 696-704.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b79">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Copyright of PLoS Genetics is the property of Public Library of Science and its content may not be copied or emailed to multiple sites or posted to a listserv without the copyright holder&apos;s express written permission</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Copyright of PLoS Genetics is the property of Public Library of Science and its content may not be copied or emailed to multiple sites or posted to a listserv without the copyright holder&apos;s express written permission.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b80">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">However, users may print, download, or email articles for individual use</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">However, users may print, download, or email articles for individual use.</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
